Mushishi
Interview with the Director
What was your first encounter with 'Mushishi' like?
I guess you could say
that I first encountered it
when I picked up the manga.
When glancing at the cover of the manga,
I couldn't tell what the story was about.
But, the kanji characters
for "Mushishi" were quite powerful.
So that had a big impact on me.
The cover has just the title
and a man whose name is Ginko;
it looked very different to me.
I couldn't tell what it was from the cover.
I couldn't tell what it was about.
So, that made the shock
I got when I read it bigger...
since I read it when I didn't
know what it was about.
It turned out that, how should I put it,
it's not something that
deals with good and evil.
It's not something that
portrays only happy endings.
focuses only on characters.
It's not something that
emphasizes story settings too much.
The Mushishi manga is something
that's really close to the feeling
of meeting and talking with people.
I think the manga fans
probably feel this way about it.
When you meet someone for the first
time, you say, "How do you do?"
You don't know what this person is like,
but you start talking about things,
like "Oh, you like this?"
or "Oh, I play this sport, too."
As you talk with this person,
you end up learning more about him/her,
like, "Oh, he/she likes this one, too,"
or "Oh, he/she gets upset if others
do this kind of thing to him/her."
So, there're many things that you'll
learn as you socialize with this person.
The Mushishi manga
gave me a similar impression.
As you read on, you'll learn, "Oh, Ginko
gets worked up in this kind of situation."
Also, "Oh, there's mushi like this."
Like this, you'll discover new things.
So, if you read it at
different times in your life,
you'll be surprised to find
things that you missed before.
This is a manga that makes you notice
many things that you overlooked before.
What do you keep in mind when animating 'Mushishi'?
Just to make it exactly like the manga.
I like manga books.
In the past,
when a manga I liked was animated,
I couldn't enjoy it that much.
I always thought things like,
"Oh, no! They changed it like that?" or
"I liked this part, but they omitted it..."
So, I thought, "When I create a show,
especially since it is a wonderful
work that I became attached to,
I absolutely don't want
to twist things around."
I really want people
to have the same feelings
no matter which one they experience
first, the manga or the anime.
I wanted to create it
so that there is no difference
between reading the manga
and watching the anime,
so that it won't make a difference even if people go back and forth.
In that sense, I'd make
absolutely no changes.
I'd add no strange modifications.
But, I didn't want it to be
just an imitation of the manga.
So, of course, while carefully thinking
about what would be needed and
what I should do to make animation,
I thought I should focus
on creating animation.
I paid attention to that part a lot.
What is the highlight of 'Mushishi'
and what was challenging about it?
The highlight of the show...
is the expression of the "Mushishi" world.
The background art, light, and water...
Those things are common to our world...
things that you find anywhere...
The air the characters
breath in. The raindrops...
Everyone treats these things
very, very carefully.
Waki-san, who is the art director,
Hama-san, who is the shooting director,
Tanaka-san, who is the sound director,
Okuda-san, who is
in charge of sound effects...
Everyone pursues the same thing.
So, if I am to say what
the highlight is, that would be it.
The world of "Mushi-shi" is also the highlight.
The staff thinks that you
probably don't often see
this kind of world expression
in anime these days.
Since we've been creating the show
with this idea that shows like Mushishi,
which focus on the world, are rare,
the world is really the highlight.
Things that were challenging...
Especially for the staff,
for example, there's a scene that
shows the movement of mushi.
We needed about 1000 pages
for 6 or 7 seconds.
The animators had to draw
them all in detail by hand.
They draw the movement little by little,
so I think that's a lot of work,
but I don't think that's
something that was challenging.
At any rate, I read the manga.
I keep in mind to read the manga.
I read the original work... That's all.
So, if you like the manga,
all you need to do is just read it.
Well, if I say it that way, it sounds
like I'm doing it without thinking,
but the toughest thing may be
when I have to convey the good part
of this work to others.
For example, "In this episode,
this is the good part," or
"In this episode, this action by the
episode's main character was interesting."
it's actually quicker for them to
understand it if they read the manga.
Although it'd be quicker if I ask
them all to sit down and read it,
since several hundred people
are involved in the project,
I can't force them all to read it.
They all have limited time.
There're, of course, people
who work on things that we present.
It's a type of work
whose appeal is hard to explain
and is easier to understand if you
read the manga or watch the anime,
so when I have to explain the
appeal of "Mushishi" to people,
you can probably say its tough.
Please tell us about the 'Mushishi' staff
Producing animation is a team effort.
It's something that you won't see the
completed product if someone is absent.
We're creating this series at an anime
production company called Artland.
The staff members are incredibly
committed to the project.
You can see that in the results.
So, I feel really lucky that I am able to
produce this show at a company like this.
Also, I can say this for everyone.
Umakoshi-san, Waki-san, Sugawara-san,
whose photos were used in the opening,
Masuda-san, who was
in charge of the music...
Every single piece of work
that has been completed has...
how should I put it, the power
of the original work in them.
It's no exaggeration to say
that everything is thanks
to the power of all the staff members.
I really appreciate it.
Have there been any
'just between you and me' stories
while working on 'Mushishi'?
"Just between you and me" stories while working on "Mushishi"...
When I create the DVD jackets
with Umakoshi-san,
we have one little story line
that we base them on.
You might not find this interesting.
It's a simple thing.
The jacket for DVD volume 1
shows Ginko walking towards you.
And, the jackets after that show
Ginko sitting down, looking around, etc.
We draw them based on a story line
that Umakoshi-san and I decided on.
We decided not to tell anyone about it.
You asked me for "just between you
and me" stories, so here it is.
Right... we designed the DVD jackets
based on one story line.
Another story is about...
[ kago = cage ]
Artland created an annex office called
"Mushi-Kago" for the Mushi-shi project.
Well, it's just an ordinary house.
Everyone works upstairs there,
and I work downstairs.
Since I get really busy with work,
I put a futon on the floor and sleep there.
But the staff doesn't show
any consideration...
Even when I'm sleeping, I'm awakened
by loud noises from the photocopier.
Also, even when I say,
"it's really freezing downstairs,"
they'd just say, "Oh, really?
it's been like that lately".
They have one of the latest
heating/AC units upstairs,
so it's very warm there.
And, it's very cool during
the hottest days in the summer.
I have an old heating/AC unit
from long ago downstairs,
but it doesn't work at all.
When I set the heater for about
30°C (86°F), it finally warms up.
Well, I guess many people probably
wanted to hear fun stories
for "just between you and me" stuff,
but the reality is it's a sad world.
Even if it's the director of the show,
people would make photocopies
while he's sleeping,
or he's put in a room where
the heater isn't even working.
I wanted people to know a little about it.
I guess that's it for the inside stories...
Please tell us about
the 'Mushishi' opening
I was already thinking about using
Ichigo Sugawara-san's published photos
for the opening from the planning phase.
The finished opening created
by combining those photos
with the acoustic guitar
music by Ally Kerr-san
was something that greatly
exceeded my expectations.
What I was aiming to create was
something that starts late at night
as if it's flowing in.
When I thought about people
who stay up that late,
I thought there wouldn't be that many
who routinely stay up that late.
So, I think the viewers would be divided
into those who were
looking forward to the show,
or those who happened
to have that channel on.
For those who were looking
forward to it, I wanted them to think,
"Whoa, it's really starting" when they see
"Original Story by Yuki Urushibara".
I thought that even those who knew
the manga very well would be excited
when they see an opening that has
drawings of nothing in particular
and doesn't hint at all at the content
of the show that is about to start.
I hoped that they'd wonder
what the show would be like.
And, for those who happened to be
tuning in, I wanted them to think,
"For some reason, I like this," or
"There is something about this opening."
It doesn't matter if they only saw
"Original Story by Yuki Urushibara"
or they saw only the title "Mushishi"
and even changed the channel.
I was hoping that the person who
changed the channel would ask someone,
"I don't know if it's a
variety show or a drama,
but I saw a show titled "Mushishi"
late at night. What's that?"
Or he/she would check it in a search
engine on the Internet and find out,
"Oh, that was anime?" or
"Oh, there's a manga for this."
I hope that people would start watching
the show with those things as an entrance.
Please tell us about
the 'Mushishi' endings
Each "Mushishi" episode
is different from the others;
some episodes have
happy endings, others don't.
An episode about sea
and an episode about mountains...
I knew from the planning phase that
it'd be difficult to use the same ending
for all these episodes.
So, I asked Masuda-san if he
could create different music
for each episode as much as possible.
Masuda-san gladly accepted saying,
"Why don't I? Let's do all the episodes."
"After all, I agree that it wouldn't work if
we use the same music for each episode."
This is how it came to be.
Normally, I think it's almost impossible
to make these things happen...
I can't think of a good way to describe it,
but the music he created
for each ending is just incredible.
At the ending of each episode, I think,
"This is great music.
it's well-suited for this episode."
Well, I know that's just natural
since Masuda-san created the music
specifically for that episode,
but you know what I mean.
Masuda-san likes the manga
very much, too.
When speaking of ideals, I think
something incredible is being created.
I'm feeling that it
didn't have to be this good,
but I'm just amazed that something
this incredible could come out.
I really appreciate it.
What do you want to convey
through 'Mushishi'?
What I want to convey...
I feel that it's not something
that I should say myself.
I think this is a show that gives
a different impression to people
depending on their situation, for example,
students who are preparing
to take school entrance exams,
people who have just moved,
people who have just
accepted the job offer, etc.
I think the manga is like that, too.
So, if you ask me if there's something that
I want to convey, it's a little different.
I want them to feel something.
I'm hoping to convey something.
Anything. It doesn't matter what it is.
It can be little things, such as
"I don't know why but it made me cry," or
"I don't know why, but it made me
really want to see the rural scenery,"
or "It made me want to go to the sea," etc.
I want people to feel
even little things like that.
What makes me the happiest is
when they want to watch it again.
I want them to feel like,
"I want to watch it again,"
or "I guess I'll bring out the DVDs and try
watching it again in several years," etc.
This is a show that gives you
a different impression
depending on the feelings
you have at the time.
So, if you watch it again
after a long interval,
this series will probably continue
to stay alive during that time.
I'm hoping that this will
become a series like that.
Mushishi
From the Director to the Viewers
I think this is a wonderful show that
is very faithful to the original work.
Well, how should I put it...
I'd like if you way Ginko feels about things
like how relaxed he is throughout the series
when you watch the DVDs.
Thank you.