Mushishi
Production Studio Tour
This is the "Mushi-shi" production studio,
commonly known to us as "Mushi-Kago".
[Mushi-Kago]
It's Artland's annex office,
located in the Tokyo metropolitan area.
Design by: Ms. Urushibara
Created by: Mr. Umakoshi
(Character Design / Illustration Direction)
[Mushi-Kago] 2nd Floor
This is the second floor of "Mushi-Kago".
Here, they mainly work on
episode direction as well as illustration.
Key illustrations are checked
by each episode director.
Desk of Mr. Umakoshi
Character Design / Illustration Direction
[Mushi-Kago] 1st Floor
On the first floor of Mushi-Kago,
there is Director Nagahama's desk
as well as a meeting space.
My work isn't exciting.
Storyboards check by the director
In order to express the
original work faithfully,
he carefully compares
the storyboards with the manga.
Meeting space
Artist: Urushibara
"To: Director Nagahama, Looking forward to
the show. Yuki Urushibara April 18, 2005"
Artland
This is Artland's second floor.
Here, they mainly work on
key illustration and animation.
Here, they work on color design
and coloring based on the animation.
What we've shown you up to this point
is only a part of the entire
anime production process.
Outside of this, various other processes
and many other people's efforts
are added to create the anime Mushishi.