What's wrong?
What is this?
Say dear,
do you think this is a tooth?
I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
Mushishi
I reached... for you
Seeds rooted in the flesh and blood of our ancestors.
Reach out with green, green leaves.
Bear heavy, heavy fruit.
The Heavy Seed
Hey,
can you sell me something to eat?
Look at these crops.
We had a cold summer; we're
barely getting by ourselves.
I can't help you.
Try the neighboring town.
They've got quite a crop this year.
Yo, don't tell him that stuff.
You'd best avoid it. The rice there isn't normal.
They get an ample harvest every time there's a disaster.
It's the ancestors' curse, they say.
It's a cursed harvest.
The ancestors are going to take someone away again.
Who's it going to be this year?
The ancestors always take the weakest one first.
Wow, those are fine crops.
Who are you? What do you want?
I was just wondering if you could
sell me something to eat.
There's nothing to give to outsiders. We
don't get enough rice to last the year.
We need to stock as much as we can while we can.
Yeah? So is this year's big crop a miracle?
Yeah.
The ancestors are protecting us through the
soil because we worship them diligently.
And they take one of you in exchange, huh?
Seems a bit harsh for something your
ancestors would do, doesn't it?
It can't be helped.
I see it differently.
Can you tell me a little more about it?
I've been told that it's been this way for a while – every
time there's a disaster, we get a strong harvest.
And every such year, someone would
grow a "divine fang" in their mouth.
The tooth falls out at the end of autumn,
and the person dies.
The life is an offering made to the ancestors.
That's what we've all been told.
Everyone's been thankful though.
If it weren't for the miracles, we wouldn't have
survived until now in this barren land.
Do all the lost ones share something in common?
It's always the weakest one, I'm told.
The bodies are buried?
Yeah.
And the teeth?
The Saishu-sama enshrines them.
Saishu: chief mourner
The chief mourner?
He's the man who manages all
of the festivities in this town.
I've been taught a lot, because I'll be taking his role.
After the teeth fall out, they become
visible only to the Saishu-sama.
So the Saishu-sama enshrines them.
Why are you going to be following his path?
I'm like the chief mourner; sometimes
I see things that others can't.
I'd like to see that "Saishu".
Saishu-sama!
He's probably in the garden around the back.
A diary and Agricultural texts.
It's been a while since I've had a guest.
Who exactly are you?
I'm a Mushi-shi, Ginko.
I'm looking for a "Narazu seed".
I see.
Sane, you still have work to do, don't you?
Come back when you're done.
We've got a big crop this year. We'd better
be ready or we won't be able to keep up.
Yeah.
What's wrong, are you still worried about your mother?
Don't worry, don't worry.
She'll be okay.
Here, give her this.
Yeah.
I've been told that you Mushi-shi folk
have been here in the past as well.
But you're wasting time. There is no such seed here.
Well then, are you saying the crops here
are thanks to your ancestors' powers?
"Ancestors' powers", huh?
Indeed, that's part of it.
It's thanks to everyone's faith that we can
all work without abandoning this land.
But that's not all.
We've spent countless years studying
ways to fertilize the soil.
At times, that effort brings us results like this year's.
Our harvest is growing each year as well.
So, about the "divine fang".
It's not impossible for a grown man to grow a tooth.
That's got nothing to do with the harvest.
Now, leave please.
Let me ask one more thing.
What?
You seem to know about the "Narazu seed".
Yeah, I've heard about it from my elders.
Koumyaku: stream of light
That a Mushi-shi contained a
"Koumyaku" in it – or something.
Right.
You can sense the "Koumyaku" yourself, can't you?
Being that you can see Mushi.
The weaker a Mushi is, the more
light they expose themselves to,
because they're close to the Kouki, the root of all Mushi.
A Koumyaku is a channel in which Kouki flows.
In a sense, it is life itself.
Manipulated correctly, it can be used for anything – even immortality or resurrection.
Of course, such an action is highly taboo to us Mushi-shi.
Yet, countless exceptions exist.
That seed is one of them.
Buried in soil, it'll yield fertility in the area for a year,
and a being will be stolen of its life as compensation.
That is the record that has been passed down to us.
So, what do you plan to do with it when you find it?
Destroy it? Use it?
That happens to be what I want to ask as well.
What would you do if you could save many
lives at the expense of one life?
I'd use it.
If such a seed exists, it'd be a sin
to let such an opportunity go.
But to bury it with the knowledge that someone
will surely die is tantamount to murder.
No matter how many lives are saved as a result,
one life is taken away regardless of their will.
Anyone would surely dirty their hands with such a crime,
if one person's sacrifice could save two lives.
Naturally, in the short term it's difficult not to use it.
But you use it once, you'll have
to use it many times more.
The seed is alive. Each time you
use it, its influence increases.
It could eventually unbalance things.
So you're saying you wouldn't use it?
Could you not use it?
I wouldn't know.
I don't remember living in a village.
I'd ditch the land before it could happen.
Our ancestors' bodies lie here in this land, in this soil.
We developed the land and finally
got to where we are now.
This is our one single achievement.
Wouldn't one foul the soil by planting
such an abomination in it?
What are you talking about?
This is all just a "what-if".
I know that's right.
If such a seed existed,
I'd think it over more carefully.
Yes,
such a seed does exist in the hands of one man.
Like the heavy grains of an overripe ear of rice, it
inevitably falls from the hands and onto the soil...
not knowing the forthcoming suffering of man.
Are you done talking?
Yeah, mostly.
So are you going to help everyone?
Yeah, but I need the agreement
of everyone in the village,
after I tell them about how the "cursed harvest" works.
Can you go gather everyone in one spot?
Yeah. But what are you planning?
Are you suggesting that we burn the farms?
That we have no choice but to destroy the seed
before the "divine fang" appears in someone?
Yeah, that's right. So you finally admit.
You're mistaken.
You're not helping anyone.
Are you going to make everyone starve?
Everyone just needs to be gone for a year.
It shouldn't be hard for everyone to disperse
and live on their own for a year elsewhere.
The burned ashes should fertilize the soil in the spring.
How many people do you think will
come back once they're gone?
People can bear with it because they don't know.
Because they don't know what a real big harvest is.
This is how it's supposed to be.
I won't let you spread any crazy rumors.
Saishu-sama!
Is the old man ill?
I don't know.
He's been sick these days; been taking medicine.
Medicine?
I think it's the stuff in here.
I don't know what you were thinking
drinking such poison,
but don't you think you'd be a bit irresponsible
to just let yourself die?
Say, Mushi-shi-san.
Considering you intended to burn the crops,
you must not have come to
use the seed for yourself.
Please.
I've decided that I'd be the last victim of the seed.
It's been said that the seed was brought back
from somewhere by the chief mourner two generations ago.
Since then the seed had been used countless
times each time there was a disaster.
To prevent confusion, only the chief
mourner knew of the seed.
It was twenty years ago that we first had to consider
the use of the seed in my generation.
I better use it.
At this rate...
I'm going out.
Okay, take care.
I'm doing the right thing.
I was thoughtful for the whole village.
This is the right thing to do.
I'd never known that my wife was
holding anything back from me.
That autumn, it was my wife that
possessed the "divine fang".
Please.
Eat the rice.
Or you'll die too.
What are you doing?
Eat it even if it hurts.
I think I can bear dying, if you're
going to be eating my life.
Even such rice,
my body consumed greedily.
Later, I was about to throw out
the seed that fell from my wife.
But I thought about the inevitable
arrival of the next disaster.
And...
I realized that I could use the seed just one more
time without seeing anyone becoming a victim.
And this year, that time has come.
I plan to have Sane dispose of the
seed when it falls from me.
I learned that if it is buried in a so-called
"Koumyakusuji", it'd lose form.
Koumyakusuji: koumyaku channel
However, I don't intend to explain
the nature of the seed.
Is that really okay with you?
You must want to live to see this land
prosper more than anyone else.
I already can.
So long as we don't give up.
This land will slowly become richer.
There will eventually be a time when
we can live without worries.
I don't know how many generations it'll take.
I wouldn't be able to see it with my eyes anyway.
All right.
Do what you want.
One more thing I want to ask you.
Saishu-sama!
Mom's going to be fine now.
She's getting better with the rice.
Really. I'm glad to hear.
Just like I told you.
Yep.
Say, Sane. I have something I need to tell you.
Something really important. Listen carefully.
Yo, Sane, your prayers aren't the same as last year's.
Hey, has the "divine fang" shown up on anyone yet?
Nope, haven't heard about it.
Maybe the harvest this year wasn't cursed.
So then this rice must have been
the result of our effort alone.
Hey.
The festival's going well.
Everyone's having fun.
It's okay.
I'll do as you said.
Saishu-sama.
Why does it have to be this way?
This is just wrong.
Don't tell anyone what I'm about to do.
One more thing I want to ask you.
I said the Koumyaku is life itself, but it isn't enough
to just pour it into an organism to revive it.
However, it's the seed that makes it possible.
This is a gamble.
I'm willing to bet that if a lifeform eats
it, they could come back to life.
But unlike with the plants, the seed
will no doubt remain in your body.
In which case, you will become an immortal...
"thing", beyond a lifeform.
Would you risk it?
Wasn't that your most forbidden act?
Would you be forgiven for such a thing?
No one will know if you keep quiet.
I don't know if it'd succeed, and I don't
know if it'd be in your best interest.
But if you'd like to try it...
This is my apology to you for wrangling out the
truth about the seed from your wounds.
This is a crime I'm willing to commit.
Think it over carefully.
My answer wouldn't be any different,
whether I think it over or not.
I'd still like to watch over the land.
I'd still like to see what happens to it.
I want to see if what I did was the right thing to do.
The abundant harvest of that year would become
a tale that was passed down for ages.
At the same time,
a strange legend was born.
During the year in which the long lasting
"cursed harvest" came to an end,
the rice that was produced had revived a dead man.
The man became immortal and walked the lands.
Every so often, he'd come back and bring with
him new techniques to fertilize the land.
The
Heavy
Seed
The
White
Which
Lives
Within
the
Ink
Stone
The White Which Lives Within the Ink Stone.