I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
Give birth to me once more.
I want to meet you all over again.
I want to see this lovely ocean once again.
Shrine in the Sea
Who was that?
Don't know... I'm not really sure,
but he came asking about uminaoshi.
Really?
I wonder how he heard about it...
I came all this way with nothing to show for it...
Islanders are tough people.
Well, I'll just take it slow.
Hm?
What's that glow?
It's too bright to be sea-fireflies and
too dim to be fishing lights...
Beats me...
Oh... you can see them?
You know a lot about things like that?
Well, yes... It's how I make my living.
Mom!
Grandpa's back. Let's have dinner...
Oh, it's the man from this afternoon.
You're welcome to come over if you like.
There are too many snakes around to camp out at night.
Grandpa, we have company.
Now that's a rarity...
Who is he, Mana?
She's Isana.
So she is. Sorry, Mio.
I don't think it'll appear anymore...
since the moon is out.
Oh, I see.
Ginko-san...
Did you come here to ask about uminaoshi?
Do you know something?
That glow always appears around that rock over there.
There's a trench we call the Dragon's
Palace below that rock.
People who lose their lives there are reborn looking exactly the same.
Ginko-san...
Did Isana look like a normal child to you?
Are you saying?!
She's the uminaoshi of my mother.
Dad!
Don't do it, Dad.
She's still alive.
Mio... no one has ever survived this disease.
She won't be able to come back unless we submerge her while she's alive.
I don't want you to!
Forgive me... Mio...
I'm afraid of dying and going away forever...
I want to fall asleep thinking that I will come back here...
Let me do it.
Mom...
Mom!
Mio, tomorrow is the day...
The full moon is finally here.
Please... don't you want to see your mother again?
I do, and so do all our relatives.
We're all waiting for Mana to return.
I know it's been hard on you to lose your husband and then your mother.
All the more reason having a child will give you something to live for.
Mio, please... You're the only one we can turn to.
All right...
If seeing that child will comfort you all...
then I will give birth to it.
But the child is no longer my mother.
Promise me that you won't call her Mana.
Just one will do.
Any one?
Yeah. If a person swallows it, it will become a child who will look the same
as the person we submerged
in the sea within the past month.
That was how Isana was born.
Any chance she's the child of your late husband?
My husband died two years before Isana was born.
I want to know what that child is.
I'm not really sure yet,
but she did appear human...
and there's no denying that you gave birth to her.
It's better if you just think of her as a child that looks a lot like her grandmother.
Mio...
What's the matter?
Can't fall asleep?
When that happens, this is what Mommy does.
I imagine myself as a huge fish,
swimming slowly downward into the quiet, blue ocean...
Then before I know it, I'm asleep.
Mom...
What's the matter?
Nothing.
Good night, Isana.
Don't worry.
Yup, that's right.
They say I'm Grandma's uminaoshi.
There are lots of people like that.
Oh, that child is one.
When she was about six, she was bitten by a snake and almost died, but she was reborn.
That woman over there is one, too.
Soon after she got married, a shark attacked her and she was reborn.
Her husband waited nearly twenty
years to marry her again.
They were all reborn and are living happy lives.
Are you happy, too?
I feel at a loss when someone calls me "Mana,"
But it doesn't bother me since Mom
doesn't call me that way.
So I'm happy to have been born to Mom.
I love this ocean, this island, everything...
I can't see anything in there...
It'd be unsafe to approach the glow at night...
Maybe I'll wait for them to spawn at full moon.
Then you'll stay until then?
Yeah.
Wow look at how lovely that is!
An island where one can regain lost loved ones...
An island where one can choose never to say goodbye...
In that sense, this is a true paradise...
But yet...
A child that resembled my mom... I was able to feel that way when she was a baby.
After all, I don't know what
my mother looked like as a child.
But as she got bigger,
her face changes little by little...
and everything, such as her
personality and minute habits,
is becoming close to that of the mother I knew...
My mother is gone,
But she looks just like her and calls me Mom.
The daughter I gave birth to and
raised doesn't seem like my own...
Hm?
They're coming from deep down in the Dragon Palace...
Those globules... I think they're created by some sort of mushi, after all.
I don't have any proof, but it all makes sense if you think of it this way...
What I found inside those globules
was the embryos of various animals...
The form fundamental to all...
The fact that one who swallows a globule
becomes pregnant with a child identical to the one who was submerged at sea
suggests that this mushi can return animals to their very embryos.
Which means...
That child is physically identical to your mother.
From here on, she'll resemble her more and more.
But since she was born and raised by you,
she cannot turn into your mother.
To her, you are every bit her "mother".
Yes... I have to be strong...
Ginko!
I'm thinking of leaving tomorrow
if the weather will allow it.
What?
I won't know what to do if I stay here any longer.
I don't have the right to take away your happiness.
Thank you, Ginko...
If Mom is about to die, I'm going to give birth to her.
I can't imagine life without Mom.
I think you'd better wait and see today.
It could be a typhoon.
I guess I have no choice.
The storm's getting worse...
I didn't know there are actually
times when you can't fall asleep.
Of course. It's just that I know a good way to fall asleep.
When you can't sleep, it helps if you imagine
that you're a huge fish swimming down into the ocean.
Swim past the coral, with
the remora or such at your side...
slowly downward into the dark deep...
Then you'll gradually...
Mom?
I'm sorry... I'm a little... thirsty...
I'm fine. Wait here for me.
I have to be... strong...
It's going to get swept out...
Mio!
My boat is missing.
You don't think?!
Hey, look at that.
She's over there!
Wait, Isana!
Don't go near that glow! It'll eat you alive.
Don't rush in! We'll approach cautiously.
Okay!
Mom! Over here!
They're surrounding the boat.
What do we do?
Isana!
Stay away!
Please!
Wait!
You're all right!
Isana, what about you?
I'm okay.
Get in, quickly!
Darn... I can't... fight this...
If they eat me like this, will they
turn me into an embryo as well?
To a time before everything begins...
Gosh... that's a really bad...
... joke.
They're letting go...
Now! Get out of the water quickly...
The storm has... passed!
And... why did they suddenly...
So that's it...
The moon is out...
Although I know only a very little about these mushi,
they seem to glow to attract and capture animals,
then return them to their essence
before discharging them.
That is probably their nature.
You may be able to say they're mushi that feed on the "time an animal lived".
Anyway, you both know about those mushi very well.
Give it time and your issues will work themselves out.
Yes...
In any case, Isana,
you jumped into the water without
a second thought, didn't you?
You scared the lights out of me.
Sorry about that.
Even if they ate your mother,
you would've seen her again if you gave birth to her.
Yeah...
But then they would've eaten up
the time Mom had lived, right?
That'd be sad...
I'd rather see Mom die while she's still my mom
than give away her entire lifetime to someone else.
You think just like I do.
That's just what I'd expect of my child...
On that island, uminaoshi will probably continue as a regular occurrence,
helping to put the dying at ease
and filling the void in the hearts of those left behind...
Perhaps being able to die without having that wish
is a rare and fortunate blessing.
Shrine
in the
Sea
The
Sound of
Rust
The Sound of Rust.