I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
On my wedding day, I passed through
the forest to the north.
I believe that's when it attached itself to me.
It was there all of a sudden, a green thing, on my gown.
It was only after the wedding that I noticed it.
It seemed very vile.
The following year, I gave birth to my first child.
This is my boy – Watahiko.
He's been getting weaker and weaker
since the stains began to appear.
Every time I see it, I remember that stain.
Forgive me if I'm wrong.
Did he have a human form when he was born?
No.
He didn't even resemble an animal.
Cotton Changeling
I never thought I'd be called back to
their home only three months later.
Ginko!
Thank god you came.
Did you read the letter? Did I make it in time?
Yeah. Come in, quick.
I'm sorry.
I meant to do as you said.
No, that's fine. Thanks for letting me know.
But honestly, I never thought it would happen so soon.
Yeah.
He's growing frighteningly fast.
Did he have a human form when he was born?
Aki, are you all right?
I'll take it from here.
It wasn't even an animal.
It didn't even cry.
It was a green, formless thing.
Aki!
It's getting away!
Shit!
It slipped into the floor in the blink
of an eye and disappeared.
My wife wanted a child dearly.
But then she gave up and became depressed.
And one year later...
What's that sound?
Is it from under the floor?
Someone must have abandoned him.
No. It's that child from back then.
Our child.
He looks a lot like Aki.
He must have grown to take a human form.
Inside, I was terrified, but I convinced
myself to believe her.
This child, Watahiko, grew quickly.
He loved small fish and berries.
In just over six months, he grew
to the size of a three year old.
But he still had the mind of a baby.
Emotionless and without speech.
But he came to look more and more like us,
and we became attached.
One night...
Is that a cat?
Damn it, it's annoying.
There was another baby under the floor.
He's just like Watahiko in every way.
We'll have to raise him the same way.
Maybe we'll have more?
Don't say that, that's scary.
But she was right.
Watahiko was born again and again.
I tried digging underneath the floor,
but I never found anything odd.
This year though, something odd
happened to our first born.
Green stains appeared on his skin,
and he'd sleep for most of the day.
Our doctor gave up completely.
Then we heard that you may be able to help.
Unfortunately, we Mushi-shi can't save him.
This is the end of his lifespan.
There's a Mushi called Watahaki.
They float around in the air.
They invade the wombs of pregnant
human women and infest the egg.
They are born as a pile of goo,
and quickly escape into floors and ceilings.
A year later, they send a "Hitotake" to the person's home.
The timeline of their births matches
the Watahaki's pattern.
Though, can I check under your floor just in case?
No thanks, I don't need a light.
There it is.
It's huge too.
No mistake. It's a Watahaki.
No way. I don't see anything.
Look carefully at this dirt in the sunlight.
Hitotake are connected to the Mushi's
main body by a thread-like bond.
They're just part of the Mushi, sending nutrients to it.
It can't be.
That boy will soon have finished
his task and undergo necrolysis.
When he dies, his body will emit
a huge number of "spores".
You'll have to kill him before that happens.
What are you saying?
Why do you think I called you?
Save him from that Mushi thing you speak of.
There is no "child" for me to save.
Those "children" are Mushi bearing your likeness.
And these are what killed your true child-to-be.
Please. You have to understand.
Sorry.
You have a right to despise me.
Thanks for convincing your wife.
She still won't even talk to me.
We've raised him for over three years.
I'm not surprised.
But she wants to keep the rest of the children.
I beg you! Let them live!
They're harmless until they become sick.
I promise.
Before our second and the next child emit their spores,
I will kill them.
Watahaki have a life expectancy of ten to thirty years.
There's no telling how long this'll go on
or how many "children" you'll have to kill.
Would you still do it?
Yeah.
I promise.
You said you were terrified of those things.
Do you still want to raise them?
I just don't want to make my wife sad.
Aki truly adores the remaining four.
There's no telling what'll happen to her if we lose them.
She was married before to a large retailer's
family beyond the mountains.
Over there, she gave birth to their son and heir.
But he died in less than a year in a stupid accident.
They divorced because of that.
How?
How can it be so cruel?
Up until now, every child known to be
a Watahaki's child was destroyed.
That way, they let the roots run dry.
Not one was ever allowed to live after the first.
They might change for the worse.
But...
On the other hand,
they might not.
I don't like killing everything I'm
not sure about. It's too blunt.
I can't stay here to watch,
but I'll be back within three months
to see how things are.
Send a letter there if something happens.
Yeah.
I can't thank you enough.
And in less than three months, a letter came.
There.
He's here.
It's him.
We're going to be killed.
It's fine.
Don't worry.
Watahiko?
He's coming.
Yeah.
My wife finally seems to agree.
We're raising an abomination.
We've got to do what we've got to do.
Aki, Ginko's here.
Thank you for coming.
It's fine.
Ginko, this way.
Yeah.
Ginko?
Ginko!
You're awake.
Ow. Ow. Ow.
You should lie down.
I wanna leave.
I don't know how to apologize.
I'll keep her in the bedroom until it's all over.
Yeah, that'd help.
I thought she understood.
Seems like things have changed.
Yeah. I was going to tell you right away.
It's not just that they're growing faster.
One time, our fourth was cracking nuts.
I'd only taught our second one.
It took our second child a long time to figure it out.
He must have learned from watching.
They seem to have begun to think.
Oh, you're drenched. Let's get you changed right now.
Daddy.
Daddy, I'm hungry.
Aki, he's talking!
Oh yeah? I'll get you something to eat right away.
Then our second child began showing those symptons.
It's too early.
It just happened to our other child.
We have to do it.
It's our duty.
Daddy, I'm afraid to die.
Don't kill me. Help me.
I want to live.
It'd become a human thing.
We couldn't do it,
even if it was my child's enemy.
This is bad.
They've gained cognition.
No, they must have been capable all along.
They might have experienced fear
after the first one's death.
And their individual knowledge is being
shared amongst all of them.
Each are parts of a whole connected at the roots.
They obtain five times the amount
of information at once.
They'll learn fast.
But... "human-thing"?
No, what lives in his mind is only a thinking spore.
We've failed.
We're going to get killed. We're going to get killed.
We have to protect the seed. I think there's a way.
I can't remember. I can't remember.
I learned how to speak and now I can't remember...
The seed... How do we protect the seed?
How do you feel?
Well, I can sorta stay up.
I see. That's good.
Your second child's in the inner room, right?
I'll be going there.
Then I'll destroy the root and
take the rest of the "children".
I can't leave them with you any longer.
Help me. Don't kill me.
I don't want to die.
Give it up.
Why are you going to kill me?
Because you consume human children.
It's not our fault.
It's not our fault either.
But we're stronger.
So you're going to die along with your seed.
I see.
Then we have no choice.
Let's do it.
Those bastards... They're going to burn the entire root.
I see. Did you kids...
I read it on the scroll that you had.
Normally, we could do it instinctively.
This is the only way we can protect the seed.
We win.
Ginko!
Don't come in! Go outside!
Watahiko... Where are the children?
They set the fire.
Move!
They'll do anything to protect the seed.
That's what those Mushi do.
They are my children now!
Aki!
Watahiko?
Watahiko!
Watahiko.
The root's completely gone.
When Watahaki are in danger, they disconnect
the Hitotake from the roots
and attempt to save the seed at least.
The Hitotake change form and enter a long sleep state.
This is it?
I don't know when they'll be reborn.
It might be after you die.
In either case, I'll leave it with you until the time comes.
All right.
I'll take good care of it.
What did you give them?
A crystal.
It was supposed to keep me fed.
What a waste.
Why did you do that?
You're a strange being.
Look who's talking.
Weren't you supposed to sleep?
That's what it says in all the records.
Dunno. I'm not sleepy.
Why haven't you killed me yet?
Because you're still alive.
You're a strange being.
Whatever, just go to sleep already.
Cotton
Changeling
Shrine
in the
Sea
Shrine in the Sea.