I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
In my world... there's the sense of
smell, sound, taste and touch.
These are all I have...
And these are all I need.
What's that?
There's something in my eyes...
Eye of Fortune, Eye of Misfortune
Thank god, I've finally come to the main road.
"From all over the ceiling they hang..."
"creatures that resemble black strands of hair"
"When nightfall comes they grow longer"
"And get in your nose so you can't sleep."
This story is about mushi...
Who told you that story?
My father told me.
Would you like to hear some more, mushi-shi-san?
How did you know that I am a mushi-shi?
Well, I just had a feeling...
Anyway, don't make that kind of face...
Won't you listen some more?
Look, it's getting dark, so why not stay around here?
Master!
Yes, Ma'am!
I have a guest here.
All right, I'm coming.
Hey... I'm not staying here...
Here, let me carry your luggage.
...I said!
Hey, let me go. Give me back my luggage!
Well... what story should I talk about next?
Is your father a mushi-shi as well?
All your stories sound very real.
Yeah, he was.
Has he retired already?
He passed away...
Because my eyes weren't helpful...
You can't see at all?
Actually, I can see very well.
What do you mean?
I saw the Ganpuku.
You saw the Ganpuku?
That's amazing!
It's supposed to be a myth! Where did you see it?
Then, I'll talk about myself next.
In return, I have a favor to ask of you.
Could you go bury these eyes of mine in the mountains?
Amane!
Dad!
Welcome back!
How did your work go?
My father was a mushi-shi, so he was often away from home working, leaving me at home.
I loved to listen to the stories about his trips.
I've obtained something amazing this time.
There's this mushi called Ganpuku,
which is said to be able to improve your eyesight after you look at it.
It's been said to be only a myth until now.
But I gained possession of
the eyeball of a man who saw it.
Eyeball?
Don't worry, it was taken out after he died.
I heard that this man was able to see more clearly after seeing the Ganpuku
for a few years before he died.
And this eyeball remains without decay since his death.
This may be a clue to finding the Ganpuku.
Amane... I'll make you able to see even if it takes the rest of my life.
I promise... you just wait...
Whoa!
Dad?
Is something wron-
Don't open the door!
What... was that?
It was a mushi, hiding in the eyeball!
That could be the Ganpuku!
My father looked around for it in the mountains, but he couldn't find it.
And a month later...
What's that?
There's something in my eyes...
Could this be... what it's like to be able to see?
Ouch!
Something just got in my eyes.
Huh?
Dad...
You must be... my dad, right?
Huh?
Amane?!
Amane!
I understood for the first time
what it meant to be able to see.
It was something that I could never imagine.
And it was a wonderful thing, far beyond my imagination.
Ultramarine blue... Light purple.
Pink... Orange...
They're wild geese.
Wow, they're very neatly lined up.
You're Saki-chan. And you're Fusa-chan.
How are you able to see?
I saw a shiny, flower-like thing.
My eyes could see further than any of my friends'.
I can see you in the bush, Yo-chan!
And then...
I found you!
It's no fun because you find us too quickly.
You can't be "it" anymore.
As time passed by... I started seeing places that I shouldn't be able to see.
Like the hill through the wall...
...and the mountain range behind that hill...
...and even the sea far beyond that mountain range...
I became able to see them even from the room.
I was fascinated with the unfamiliar
sceneries and people's lives.
But soon after, I started feeling
dizzy, and I could hardly walk.
It was only when I closed my eyes that peaceful darkness would visit me.
So I spent most of my time with my eyes closed.
But after living like that for a while, I started seeing something else.
Ah! Watch out!
Never mind...
Whoa!
Are you all right?
Ouchhh... There was a sudden gust of wind...
What was that I just saw?
When I closed my eyes, I would see the future and the past of people around me.
And soon people started coming over to ask me to read their future.
Everything I saw became true.
Rumors that I was a clairvoyant spread.
And even people from neighboring
villages came to see me.
Next summer, you'll fall into a river and die.
Please don't go near the river for any reason.
But even though I warned people, I was never able to change what I saw in my visions.
And eventually, the people who came to see me
only asked about thieves or other
unsavory types of people.
Although my eyes proved useful for people, all my friends left me.
It can't be helped...
People must think clairvoyants are creepy.
Even though I can see what's going to happen, nothing changes after all...
I stopped seeing people's past and future.
But... then...
Ah?! What?
I can see outside through my eyelids...
Amane, I'm going out.
Amane? What's wrong?
I see your future and the scenery
outside at the same time.
I feel dizzy...
That's strange.
Don't worry... I'll get used to it soon...
I'll be back in three days. Take it easy, okay?
All right.
But father never came back.
After that, I went to the mountains every single day
to look for my father using my clairvoyance.
And one day, I finally saw my father lying on the bottom of a ravine.
Then I started my journey
in order to grieve for my father.
Along the way, I told the stories
I heard from my father
while playing my lute
for money during the journey.
And after I finally arrived at
the site of my father's remains,
I no longer wanted to return to the village to which my father would never return.
Since then, I've been playing the lute
on the street for a living.
And as time passed, I could see more and more through my eyelids.
There was nothing to obstruct my view.
And it was tough for me to stand
the light during the day.
But there was still one thing that I couldn't see.
That was... my own future.
But now I was able to see it.
The fact that you would pass through this place...
...and the fact that I would have to ask you to do something like this...
...that was all foreseen.
And you want me to tear out your clairvoyant eyes and bury them in the mountains?
If I were to ask someone else to do it,
I would've done it myself long ago.
These eyes once brought me so much joy,
so I managed to live with them until now, even though I hated them.
However, this pair of eyes soon
won't belong to me anymore.
Just like the Ganpuku that I saw,
it'll get out of my eyeballs and go under ground
to wait for the next pair of new eyeballs to come.
And I don't want anyone to have
the same experience as me.
That's why I want you to bury
my eyes deep in the mountains.
Are you saying that you saw all that in your visions?
I don't get it...
I'd understand if you were
asking me to cure your eyes...
We can't say for sure there is no way to cure your eyes, you know.
I just told you... that the things I saw can't be changed.
The things my eyes see are something that exist in a far, unreachable place
and are already destined to happen.
You know...
I still can't swallow everything you've told me tonight...
I'll do what I can do.
Even if you write to your friend for help, you won't get a useful reply.
Is that so?
Why are you so eager to help me?
Is it because you lost your left eye?
You can see that with your clairvoyance, can't you?
In your case, I can't see anything, because your childhood is pitch black.
My oldest memory is of walking alone in some dark, unknown place when I was about ten.
I couldn't see anything.
I kept groping about in the dark,
and then the moon came out.
Even after this pure-white, illusionary moon set,
what rose was yet another moon.
After walking for along time in that place,
I finally came to a place where the sun rises.
I still remember well how I appreciated
the sunlight back then.
Aren't you scared of losing light forever?
Of course I am.
But a world with only light is just as scary.
You can see everything but you can't change anything...
Or you can't see anything but you can live freely...
Which one do you think is more fortunate?
I think that living in the darkness,
remembering the light, is not so bad.
What's wrong?!
I'm all right.
I just... saw it again.
How far did you see?
I saw it to the moment that the lives of my eyeballs come to an end.
Her eyes were not able to see
through her eyelids before...
She could only see other people's futures.
But now she can see through her eyelids and is able to see her own future...
Does that mean that she is becoming another person to her eyeballs?
A mushi that takes shelter in the eye
after someone looks at it...
It changes the eyeballs into something else that can live on after the person dies.
And soon it will take over the eyeballs completely and then leave the body...
If that's the case...
the time for it to leave must be close.
There is still no reply...
Things that are already destined to happen...
Huh? I can't see behind the ceiling...
What's going on?
I can see... normally...
Ah? But... my eyeballs are moving by themselves...
Hold on! I'll give you a painkiller.
Even... without... eyeballs...
...tears still flow.
How far did you see?
I saw it to the moment that the lives of my eyeballs come to an end.
After the eyeballs leave my eyes,
they are buried in the ground.
After a while, they reveal
themselves from the ground,
and a beast walks toward them.
Beautiful flowers are reflected
upon the eyes of the beast.
And as they are slowly being absorbed into the eyes,
then everything goes dark.
You should have a reply from your friend by now.
...research...
...no known treatments...
Are you going back to your village?
Well... I'm not sure.
I just want to live by myself for a while.
I'm so glad that I don't know what will happen anymore.
And if you happen to see me, please say hello.
I'll be a much better lute player by then.
Eye of
Fortune,
Misfortune
The
Sound
of
Footsteps
on the
Grass
The Sound of Footsteps on the Grass.