I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
Sunrise Serpent
It sure is peaceful.
Yeah, no kidding.
This calmness is going to spoil us all.
My wife's been sleeping all day recently.
She hardly even makes breakfast.
"How suddenly the morning comes in Spring", huh?
Dawn in Spring by Meng Hao-ran
She's gotten really forgetful these days too.
The other time she left our kid at the market.
Ouch.
Hope she hasn't forgotten who
you are when you get home.
I actually wish she would.
Your wife doesn't have trouble
sleeping at night, does she?
She sleeps with a loud snore all the time.
That's good.
No, it's not.
It gives me a hard time whenever I try to sleep.
I have snoring medication if you want.
Does it work?
Thanks a lot.
Hey, what you were just talking about...
About the snoring medication?
No, about forgetting things.
Is it bad if you can't sleep at night?
Is there something that's bothering you?
I'm home.
Mom?
Help me, Kaji!
There's a weird thing...
Weird thing?
A crab?
Have you forgotten crabs too?
They always come from the river
around this time of the year.
Do they?
Oh, you're Kaji's friend, aren't you?
No, he's not. I just met him.
He's a Mushi-shi, Ginko-san.
Mushi-shi?
Mind if I step in for a while?
Come in.
I'm Kaji's mother, Sayo.
That's how she always is.
She's always been on the slow side.
I mean, she's been forgetting things a lot.
But ever since sometime last spring,
she'd forget really weird things.
There was a big crowd of people buying dango that day,
so I got some for Mom on my way home.
This is so good.
I've never had anything like this.
What are you talking about? You've
had them every now and then.
No way.
Are you saying that I'm eating behind your back?
Mom had forgotten everything about dango.
And another time...
I figured I should sell off the ones I don't wear.
What's wrong?
I don't remember having this.
You took really good care of it because
you said it was really expensive!
Did I?
I remember this.
I haven't worn it much because
it doesn't look good on me.
She'd just forgotten the patterned kimonos
that she doesn't wear often.
It's cold today.
Yeah.
You scared me!
Don't be so strange.
Strange?
All I did was sneeze.
Sneeze?
She'd forgotten what a sneeze was.
When we went to a relatives' place for New Year's...
Kaji, who were those two people in the back again?
Uncle Masa and Aunt Mitsu.
And beside them?
Your sister.
Even her sister?
That does sound strange.
It sounds more like progressive
amnesia than forgetfulness.
See?
And she's always awake working, day and night.
She used to take naps under that tree between chores.
There's definitely something wrong with her.
Dinner's ready.
Please join us, Ginko-san. Though
we don't have anything fancy.
Kaji.
Write down as much stuff that your
mom's forgotten as you can.
What's that?
Please, go ahead.
It's a kagezen for my husband.
Kagezen: meal offering
Kagezen?
Yes. He's a traveling salesman, traveling for a full year.
You know, they say he won't be
hungry on his trip this way.
Well, it's just to make me feel better.
She hadn't forgotten that he's
died or something, has she?
Time to eat.
It's a waste of food, I tell you.
It's not all that much.
But you're eating that much less, aren't you?
Who do you think Dad's traveling for?
He must be a lot hungrier than I am.
Even though he hardly makes any money.
He could just work nearby.
Kaji.
He should be home by now.
He hasn't even sent a single letter.
It's because he makes you worry so much
that you end up going dull.
Enough!
Kaji!
How rude of him to just eat and leave.
I'm sorry.
I'm sure he just wants his father to be here.
My husband's got nothing going for
him other than being a nice guy.
He must have gotten lost somewhere.
Seems like he's not just worried about his dad though.
I know.
You must have been called here by him, weren't you?
Yes. I got the gist of it.
Is there anything you can tell me about it?
Nothing yet.
Is that so...
Please, for my son, and of course for myself.
Please do something.
At this rate...
I'm eventually going to forget
about him and my husband.
And then I'm going to forget that I've forgotten.
I'm just so afraid.
Are you done?
Yeah, for the most part.
Watermelon
Bucket
Sake
What are you doing?
Sparrow
Snail
Ginkgo Nut
Watermelon
Bucket
Mochi
Sake
Rainbow
Lightning
Fog
I was hoping there'd be a pattern
to the way she's forgetting things.
But I can't quite figure it out.
Say, is there anything common amongst
the relatives that she's forgotten?
They all live on the other side of the river.
We don't see them at the market or anything.
She's just forgetting all the things
she doesn't see very often.
No, in that case, she should have
long forgotten her husband.
It's getting late. Doesn't look like she's
going to sleep any time soon though.
Yeah.
She says she has a hard time trying to sleep.
So she weaves all night long, thinking
about Dad so that she doesn't forget.
I got it.
If she could at least sleep...
waiting would be a bit easier for her.
A warm wind,
the scent of flowers,
the sound of weaving.
Normally, such a night...
would be a night to fall into a deep, deep slumber.
She's finally dozing off.
She's awake already?
Is it morning already?
Breakfast, breakfast.
What's wrong?
I was right.
A Mushi that eats memories?
Yeah. It's called a Kagedama.
It's a translucent, black sheet-like Mushi
that likes to submerge in the shadows of old, tall trees.
There they wait for people and animals to sleep,
and enter the brains through their ears.
Then the hosts become unable to sleep...
and slowly lose their memories.
There's one of those in the cherry tree's shadow?
Seems so.
Once they consume a certain amount
of memories, they multiply internally.
The duplicates escape from the hosts during
the short time that they're asleep.
Those then hide back in the tree's
shadow. That's how they multiply.
Normally they're frail, and they vanish under sunlight.
But once they're inside, they enter deep into the brain,
and there's nothing that can be done.
So there's no way to help?
Their only known weakness is exposure to light.
But there's no way to shine light in your head.
However, there might be a way to protect
what you don't want to forget.
Let's say that the memories in your
brain are sorted into drawers.
With ones about dango, your
distant relatives, sneezing...
They're all stored in countless drawers within your brain.
The Kagedama takes away entire drawers.
It doesn't matter how interested you are in any of it.
It seems almost random.
However, there's one area of memories
that remains untouched.
The things you do, see and think every day.
Cooking, weaving, your son,
and your husband, whom you see in your mind.
It might be that the Kagedama are
leaving the everyday things for last
in order to keep their host alive.
Then, are you saying I wouldn't forget those things?
That's just my guess.
And it could be that once you've got few memories left,
those remaining memories will be consumed as well.
There are only two things that I can recommend.
Learn as many new things as you can,
and repeatedly recall the things
that you don't want to forget.
I understand. I will do that.
That's right, Mom.
You shouldn't just wait at home.
You should go out more.
You're right. I think I'll do that.
How 'bout we go find Dad?
Oh, you look so silly.
I've always been thinking of doing it.
But I was afraid of finding out what happened to him.
I'm tired of waiting though.
But how?
Dad often talked about the city to the west.
How about we try there first?
Is she going to be okay?
You'll come with me, right, Kaji?
Well, see you.
Thanks for everything.
Thank you too.
Take care.
Yes, be well.
I'm not sure that was the best thing for them to do.
A year passed until I saw them again.
Hey, you're back.
Ginko-san.
Welcome.
Tea  Shop
What would you like?
Let's see...
Looks like your mom's doing well.
Yeah.
Did you get to meet your dad?
Yep.
He was in the town to the west.
Living with another family.
Oh, yeah. I know them.
Try that house over there.
How's that?
Do you like it?
Mom! Why aren't you saying anything?
Mom!
Mom walked in silence for the entire trip home.
She'd neither eat nor sleep, and eventually...
Mom?
You should...
Mom! Mom!
She must have been tired.
She slept for days.
It's morning.
Something just went out.
Mom!
What's with that look?
I slept so well.
Well then, time for breakfast.
Where are we?
Mom...
Why are we here again?
We were coming home from hiking.
Was that it?
What was that sound?
Don't worry about it.
Just eat something.
Let's do that, I'm starving.
And then...
let's hurry...
and go home.
That morning, Mom had forgotten everything
except about me, about home, and a few close things.
She must have had most of her memories
consumed when she shut herself in.
But she still remembers about me
and about how to cook and stuff.
It must be because we go outside every day
to see new things like you told us to.
She forgets most of it by the next day,
but she's enjoying it every day.
Does she still not sleep at night?
Yeah, she still weaves all night.
Ah.
Same old, huh?
Yeah.
Same old.
I'm home.
Welcome home.
It's almost dinner; go wash your hands.
Okay.
Mom, that's one too many servings again.
You're right. There's only the two of us.
I wonder why I thought to do this.
I feel better when I do this though.
I wonder why.
Why was it again?
Sunrise
Serpent
Pickers
of Empty
Cocoons
Pickers of Empty Cocoons.