I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
Hey, Fuki.
Yes?
You're only working for us until next year, right?
Yes.
What are you going to do after that?
Do you have work back at home?
Nothing yet.
Then why don't we...
Nevermind, I'll tell you later.
It's the morning star.
Seijirou-san,
what do you think that is?
What?
There's a string coming from the sky.
A string?
I wonder where it's coming from.
String from the Sky
There, there.
Please stop crying,
or we can't go home.
Look, the sky's full of stars.
I wonder where that star went.
That comet with a tail.
Hey, wait!
Are you serious?
About the comet?
Yes, yesterday.
Where?
Around there.
Which way was it going?
Um, that way.
It was waving and twinkling.
I've never heard of such a comet.
Well, I guess it'd be a big discovery if they do exist.
All right, I'm gonna find it.
You were... Fuki, was it?
Nice find.
In the end, I never did find such a star.
We hired Fuki as a nanny for my troublesome sister.
She'd say bizarre things occasionally,
and the villagers often looked coldly on her for that.
Hey, Fuki!
Fuki!
She's not here either, sir.
Enough.
She got tired of babysitting and ran off.
That ungrateful girl.
Father!
Fuki would never...
She'd never abandon her work.
She was trying to pull a "string" at the riverbed, and...
and then she disappeared in front of my eyes.
Seijirou-bocchan, can't you think
of some better excuses for her?
I'm serious.
Fuki...
Where've you gone?
What's going on here?
Huh?
Where am I?
Who is he?
Why am I...
walking through the mountains with him?
Here, drink this.
You've got to drink this and get better.
I can't take care of you forever.
You want to get better too, don't you?
Better?
You don't remember anything?
Shoot.
You were exposed to a strong Mushi presence.
You've become something very ambiguous.
I doubt anyone else can see you right now.
That white string coming out of your hand.
It must be because you touched that.
Left untreated,
you'll become less and less human.
Are you helping me?
Who knows.
I'm just doing what I want to do.
Well, y'know.
Just gotta bear it.
Yeah,
you're starting to look better.
Am I?
Come on, let's go.
Where are we going?
We're finding a village.
You'll recover quicker if you're with people.
If you can't remember anything, just
ask a nearby village to let you stay.
But which way are we supposed to go?
There's something shining under the ground.
Yeah.
I bet you can see it pretty well right now.
This place is a Koumyakusuji.
What are those things shining?
It's called Kouki.
It's a swarm of preborn Mushi.
Are Mushi...
those small things hiding in the dark
or flying around in the sky?
Yeah.
It's pretty.
Don't look at it too much.
It's toxic to your eyes.
If you look at it for too long, you
won't be able to see sunlight.
There's a river of light up above too.
That one's shining even at night
with the light from the sun.
Watch this river instead.
Wow, you're right.
It's like a reflection of the other one.
They're apples and oranges.
Be careful not to get them confused.
I slept so well.
The girl didn't cry last night.
Thank goodness.
What's wrong?
I have to go home.
You remember?
Over there!
I was living at the bottom of those mountains.
You...
You're Fuki, aren't you?
The one that disappeared?
Oh, it is.
It's Fuki.
Just where did you run off to?
Um...
I was in the mountain.
We searched the mountain for quite a while.
Where were you hiding?
I wasn't hiding.
I just pulled on a string dangling from the sky
and then everything went black.
And when I came to,
I was in the mountain.
Here we go again.
Did you run off and come home scared?
But it's a bit too late.
They already hired a new nanny.
No way.
Fuki?
Seijirou-san.
You're safe?
Yes.
Are you hurt?
I'm fine.
That man over there helped me.
I can't thank you enough.
Please, come to my place.
Come on Fuki, let's go.
But they already have a replacement.
I can't go back.
Then come back as my bride.
I decided I'd tell you that when you got back.
Okay?
Nonsense.
I won't allow it.
Sorry to keep you waiting.
Is everything okay? It sounded like an argument.
Yes.
I didn't expect him to accept it right away.
So what was it that you wanted to talk about?
Tell me what happened when Fuki disappeared.
I'm not sure you'd believe me.
Fuki said she saw a string dangling from the sky that day,
and she made a gesture like pulling
at something in the air.
Right then...
she bolted up into the sky,
and she disappeared high up.
Nobody believed me.
I never thought much about the things
that Fuki said she saw until I saw that.
I see. Tenpengusa.
It's a Mushi living high up in the sky.
Mushi?
Yeah.
They're creatures of the yin, living on
the border between yin and yang.
Fuki called them "things hiding in the
dark and flying around in the sky".
There aren't many that can see them,
but they exist everywhere in the world.
You can see those things Fuki sees too?
Well, I make a living dealing with them.
I'm a little envious.
Fuki is quite a lucky woman.
But be careful for her.
She hasn't completely recovered
from the Mushi's influence yet.
Tenpengusa usually take the form of balloons with tails.
They dwell in the skies above special
regions called Koumyakusuji.
They live on small light consuming Mushi in the sky.
At night, they often look like squirming stars.
Hence they also have the name Mayoiboshi.
Mayoiboshi: a wandering, lost star
...that way.
It was waving and twinking.
At times when they can't get enough food,
they extend their tentacles down close
to the surface like fishing lines.
They look like strings.
And when an animal touches one,
it'll get pulled up into the sky,
but it will get tossed out because
the Mushi can't consume it.
Most of the time they'll hit the ground and die.
Fuki got lucky; she landed on a tree and survived.
But Fuki must have come close to being consumed.
She's had a strong exposure to the Mushi's presence.
That's why you couldn't find her when you
went to look for her in the mountains.
Fuki had become invisible to the human eye.
She's gotten better with this drug,
but she's not fully recovered.
She's still in an unstable state, attached
to the sky with the string on her hand.
If it gets worse it'll happen again.
For Fuki to return to human,
she needs more than just this drug.
She needs to have the will to remain human.
It's up to you to make her feel that way.
Well, I guess that's none of my business.
Okay.
I'll make sure of that.
It's a shame you won't stay here for a while.
I can't stay for much longer.
We'll be holding a wedding sometime soon.
I hope you'll come then.
Don't mind me.
But it's all thanks to you.
All right.
I'll see you around.
But...
the letter I received since then...
was to inform me that Fuki vanished again.
How did this happen?
Ginko-san.
My father wouldn't let us get married.
We spent a long time trying to persuade him.
Fuki was having a hard time.
And then Fuki slowly became lighter.
Every time there was some wind,
she'd flutter up into the air.
As time passed, she became unable
to stay on the ground.
Fuki.
Come down, please.
I don't know how to get back down.
Just when Dad's about to give in.
He can't see you like this.
I'm sorry.
I can't control my body.
Stay still, okay?
And take the medicine.
Okay.
And one day...
Fuki.
Fuki!
That was it.
I couldn't find her anywhere.
I thought I told you.
You have to hold her down.
I did what I could!
So that everyone else would accept her!
But...
with Fuki the way she is...
You, more than anyone,
are having a hard time accepting her.
It's because you rejected her that she
can't sustain her human form.
Can't... sustain?
You can't see her,
but she's right here.
No way.
If you don't want to lose Fuki, you have to accept her.
Accept her?
I can't see or touch her.
How?
You're the only one that can do it.
The last thing keeping her here...
is your presence.
What the hell am I supposed to do?
Fuki...
Seijirou-bocchan, why are you always looking at the stars?
I'm not sure.
You know when you have a bad day, you
look at the stars and they're always there.
For some reason,
I find it relaxing.
Me too.
When I get sad because the girl won't stop crying,
I count the stars to distract myself.
So it's a little disheartening when it starts getting bright.
They start disappearing one by one,
and before I know it, they're all gone.
I wonder where they all are during the day.
Silly Fuki.
They're still there during the day.
Really?
Really.
You just can't see them because the sun's so bright.
They're all there above the sky.
They don't go away.
Even if you can't see them.
They're always there.
Fuki.
It was a creepy sight to behold, they'd say.
A marriage was held on short notice
without a bride.
Yet the groom...
Drink up, Fuki...
acted as if there was one.
Or maybe... like this?
Everyone whispered that the groom had gone mad too.
Days passed,
and he began living alone at the edge of the village.
He'd still talk to his imaginary wife,
and the villagers began to ostracize him.
But eventually...
Seijirou-san.
Huh? Isn't that... that...
It's Fuki.
Just when did she come home?
People could see Fuki again,
and she lost her habit of disappearing.
String
from the
Sky
A
Sea of
Writings
A Sea of Writings.