I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
A horn from someone who was infected
with the silence-eating Ah.
I see, this is a rarity.
And over there?
A wine cup drawn by the child with God's left hand.
What?
That guy's known for hating Mushi-shi.
You need to take drama lessons, if you want to lie.
Well,
I don't want to sell it if you don't
want it, Adashino-sensei.
It's worth too much for a collector's hands.
Well, I might as well take a look.
I don't mind selling it, but there's something
I want you to help me with.
I ran into something odd on the way here.
Something odd?
Yeah, have you heard of it? The liquid Mushi.
The "Ikinuma".
The Traveling Swamp
I saw a lot of swamps when I
crossed the mountain range.
Another swamp.
But every time I took another route and
looked back through the mountains,
it'd be gone without a trace.
And as soon as I passed one mountain,
another swamp would show up.
Am I being fooled by bandits or something?
You were at the other swamp too, weren't you?
Is there another passage through this mountain?
For a moment I couldn't believe my eyes.
Her hair was incredibly green.
As if it was dyed to the roots with the swamp water.
Hey...
Is there something over there?
Do you mind if I ask you something too?
This swamp... it's not a normal one, is it?
This swamp is traveling.
It seeps into the soil, and then comes back up again.
It seems to want to pass this mountain, like you do.
Oh? That's impressive. A living swamp.
So you're traveling with it?
Why?
Well, anyway, beyond here is the sea.
I'm headed for the fishing village over there.
I guess you won't be able to keep up with
the swamp once it reaches the sea.
By the way, I want to check out
the swamp tomorrow morning.
Sure.
It's too dark right now.
This might be quite a find.
I never thought you'd believe
that the swamp is traveling.
Yeah, I believe in most phenomena.
It's just how my job is.
Job?
I'm a Mushi-shi.
Mushi tend to cause really bizarre phenomenon.
There's one called Suiko – a "liquid Mushi".
It's a colorless liquid, but it's a living creature.
It lives in old water veins and often
settles in ponds and wells.
Those who drink a Suiko
become incapable of breathing without being in water.
And if you leave them, they turn
into liquid and drain away.
Meanwhile, the Mushi would suddenly vanish.
Given that such a thing exists, I wouldn't be
surprised that there's a moving swamp.
So you didn't find it eerie either?
I...
never thought to fear it.
The first time I saw it, it was so powerful and mystical.
Powerful? What did it look like?
I was swimming in the turbulent pits of the swamp.
I got caught in a stream and I
couldn't get back to the top.
And then...
Something big and green...
swam calmly up through the raging stream.
By the time I came to, I was sitting beside a swamp.
This color...
I realized then,
that this swamp is only pretending
to be a swamp right now.
It's really the green thing from before.
By then, my hair had turned this color.
I must have died once already,
but the swamp told me that I can live.
So this swamp is the only place I can be.
At least...
wear this.
Trust that you are going to be
the wife of the God of Water.
We'll take care of your mother, do not worry.
You will be remembered
as the heroic child who saved the town from disaster.
Continue to drink, and your body
will become translucent,
and eventually drain away.
You're leaving.
It's submerging.
Hey, are you leaving already? Have it wait a little longer.
I wanna check it out.
Thanks for teaching me so much.
I'm going to become part of this swamp.
Hey, wait!
It's gone.
Shit.
Why didn't I notice?
It was an aging Suiko.
It must have traveled away after it vanished from a well.
I'm going to become part of this swamp.
Idiot.
Do you know what you're saying?
The swamp told me that I can live.
Didn't you say...
that you wanted to live?
The swamp was headed to the sea, wasn't it?
A swamp heading to the sea, huh?
You know something about it?
I heard from an old fisherman
that sometimes, a green thing the size
of a whale would come down the river
and die dispersed into pieces in the sea.
He's never seen it happen himself,
but he said that it was as if it were coming to die.
Anyway, let's hurry.
It must not have made it to shore yet;
the fishermen are still calm.
Here it is.
Groundwater
Tunnels
This is a map of the underground
water veins. It's a rare item.
Apparently, it was made by finding
"water pulses" with a pendulum.
This better be accurate.
I've tried digging wells; it's about fifty-fifty.
This vein matches with the places that I saw the swamp.
Suiko really do travel through underground water veins.
But it branches off here.
There's no telling where it's going.
Hey, Ginko.
Check out this map.
It's a map of what the rivers might have looked
like tens of thousands of years ago.
The river mouths are the same, but they're
otherwise all over the place. It's cool.
Look, I don't have the time to
put up with your collector's...
Let me have a look.
They match. What's that mean?
This vein was originally a river.
When a river dries up, it often leaves
behind layers of sediment.
Rain water seeps down into those layers.
Even if a river dries up, it remains
underground as a water vein.
The swamp might be following the path in its memory.
To find a place to die, huh?
Almost like salmon or sweetfish.
So it should arrive at this mouth here.
We won't be able to catch it once it's in the sea.
Adashino.
Can you gather some people?
We're going to set a net across the mouth of the river.
All right, pull!
Sorry to call so many of you. You all okay with this?
Yeah, us fishermen aren't doing jack right now.
There's no fish in the sea these
days. It's like they're all dead.
And it's by your request, Adashino-sensei.
You doctors sure are spoiled.
Nah, we're just people of "virtue" or something.
So, Ginko.
You don't know if the girl will be in a state
catchable with a net yet, do you?
Nope. We'll have to hope so.
Well... why do you want to save her so badly?
Although of course, you must feel some guilt.
I could understand if she wanted to live,
but she wanted to become part
of the swamp, didn't she?
She might be better off that way, as cruel as it sounds.
That green wine cup.
It belonged to the kid's grandmother.
She was no longer human nor Mushi. The only way
she could have shown herself to her grandson,
was to repair the wine cup that
was given to her by the Mushi.
She'd then never become human again,
but that was what she wanted.
But I don't know if that was truly the best choice.
To become a Mushi is different – it's
not the same as dying normally.
Mushi exist between life and death.
It's like being an object and a person at the same time...
like being alive and dead at the same time, a "thing".
Don't you think that's an unimaginable
hell compared to an instant death?
The human soul slowly decays.
She's headed in that direction.
Yet the last time I saw her, she was dressed festively.
There couldn't be anything more cruel than that.
Nothing's showing up.
Did you just hear that?
It's here!
What the hell?
Kill it, quick!
It's going to take the net away!
Don't!
There's someone inside!
Hold on!
She passed through.
There was someone in there with a red kimono.
It was too late.
Hey, check out this huge catch!
Over here too.
What the hell is this?!
Ginko, we found the girl.
She's alive.
Except...
she was in a jelly form.
Doctor.
How's the girl?
Looks like the sea water flushed all the green stuff out.
She's in about a pearl form right now.
There's swarms of fish here eating
the green thing's corpse.
The shore's black with fish.
Let me see her for a moment.
She brought us so much good.
Hey!
Can you hear?
I could feel the swamp dying in the sea...
I was melting into the swamp...
I was scared...
but I was sad that the swamp was dying.
That swamp's been alive for tens of thousands of years.
You were with it for its final journey.
Glad to have met it, no?
Yes.
Hey, Io.
Adashino-sensei.
Wow, big catch today too.
Yes, there's fish from afar as well.
They've grown so big eating the swamp's corpse.
Your hair's all black now.
Yes. I can't breathe underwater anymore.
But that's fine.
I want to live with my own strength, here
by the sea where the swamp died.
Another swamp.
One, two, three, four...
So it was surfacing...
to create offspring.
A swamp is born and in time stagnates.
At the death of the world in which it creates,
it carries its own legs and begins to move.
The
Traveling
Swamp
Those
Who
Inhale the
Dew
Those Who Inhale the Dew.