I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
All that is in my world...
is smell, sound, taste and touch.
That is all.
That is enough.
What is this?
There's something in my eye.
Eye of Fortune, Eye of Misfortune
Man, I'm finally in a city.
From the ceiling hangs
Like hair, a black strand
At night downward it grows
"I can't sleep, it gets in my nose!"
Wow.
That's a Mushi she's talking about.
Where'd you hear that story?
From my father.
Do you want to hear more, Mushi-shi-san?
How'd you know I'm a Mushi-shi?
I just got that feeling.
Oh come on, don't look so shocked.
Come listen.
Come on, it's getting late. Let's find an inn.
Boss!
What's up?
We've got a customer.
Okay, be right there.
Look, I don't intend to stay the ni–
I'll take your luggage.
I said...
Let go! Give me back my stuff!
Now then,
what should I talk about next?
Is your dad a Mushi-shi?
All your stories seem to be true.
Yeah, he was.
Is he gone now?
He's dead.
Only because my eyes were of no use.
You can't see anything?
No, I can see well.
What's up with that?
I saw a Ganpuku.
You saw a Ganpuku?
Damn. That's a really rare Mushi.
Where'd you see it?
Then I think I'll talk about myself next.
But...
I want you to do something for me.
Could you bury these eyes in the mountains for me?
Amane!
Amane.
Dad!
You're home. How was work?
My father, a Mushi-shi, often left me home alone.
More than anything, I loved listening
to my father's travel stories.
I got something awesome this time.
There's a Mushi called a Ganpuku.
It was thought to be a myth until now.
But I got my hands on an eyeball of a guy who saw one.
An eyeball?
Don't worry, I took it after he died.
For the few years after he saw the Ganpuku,
his eyesight kept getting better and better until he died.
And here's that eyeball, not even rotten.
It might lead us to the Ganpuku.
Amane,
I'm going to make sure you can see,
even if it takes me my whole life.
I promise. Just wait.
Dad?
What's wro–
Don't open it!
What was that?
A Mushi. It was in the eye.
It might have been the Ganpuku.
Dad searched all over the mountains,
but he couldn't find it.
About a month later...
What is this?
There's something in my eye.
Could this be...
what it means to see?
Ow!
There's something in my eye.
Dad?
It's you, right, Dad?
Amane.
Amane!
For the first time, I understood what it means to "see".
I could never even imagine it.
And it was more ecstatic than
I could have ever dreamed.
Dark blue.
Violet.
Pink.
Orange.
Those are geese.
They're lined up so neatly.
Saki-chan and Fusa-chan.
How come you can see now?
I saw something that looked like a shining flower.
My eyes could see further than any of my friends' could.
There you are in the grass, You-chan.
And then...
Peek-a-boo!
Amane-chan, you're too good at finding us.
You aren't allowed to be it.
With time, I came to see things in places
that couldn't have been seen.
The hill beyond the wall,
the mountain range beyond the hill,
and even the sea far beyond the mountains.
I could see all of it from inside my own room.
I loved watching distant scenes and people's lives.
But...
Soon I started feeling dizzy and had trouble walking.
The only time I could have peace and
darkness was when I closed my eyes.
Since then, I've had my eyes closed a lot of the time.
But as time passed again, I began to see new things.
Watch ou–
Nothing.
Are you okay, mister?
The wind got me.
I just saw...
When I closed my eyes, I could see the
past and future of those around me.
People began to show up asking
for their futures to be told.
The visions I saw all became reality.
Rumors spread that I was an oracle.
People even gathered from neighboring towns.
Next summer, you will fall into a river
and die.
Please, don't go near any rivers.
But even when I warned them, what
I saw would never change.
And then people only came to inquire
about thieves and cheaters.
My eyes were always cherished,
but in time, I had no one I could call a friend.
They can't help it.
Oracles are just creepy.
I can't even change anything I see.
I stopped seeing people.
But soon...
What?
I can see outside through my eyelids.
Amane, I'm going out.
Amane?
What's wrong?
I can see your future and the outside both at once.
I'm dizzy.
That's odd.
I'm fine.
I'll get used to it.
I'll be back in three days.
Take it easy.
Okay.
But my father never came home.
Day after day, I searched for my
father with my second sight.
And one day...
I found my father in the bottom of a valley.
I traveled to mourn for my father.
I walked, telling my father's stories
on my biwa to raise money.
And after I finally arrived at my father's remains,
I didn't intend on returning home
to where my father was no more.
I continued traveling in the cities, playing my biwa.
As time passed, I could see more
and more through my eyelids.
Nothing could obstruct my vision.
I couldn't even stand straight during the day.
But there was something I still couldn't see.
My own future.
And now, I can see that as well.
I knew you'd pass by.
I knew I'd have to ask this of you.
I foresaw all of it.
So you want me to pull out those eyes of yours
and throw them out in the mountains?
I would have done that myself if that was
all that I was going to ask of you.
These eyes brought me happiness at a time,
so I lived with them even though they're vile.
But soon these eyes will not be mine.
Just like the Ganpuku that I saw,
it's going to fly out of my eyeballs,
dig itself into the ground
and wait for a new set of eyes.
I want you to bury them deep in the mountains,
so that no one has to go through what I did.
And you can see all that?
My God.
I'd understand if you wanted your eyes fixed.
I can't be sure there aren't any treatments.
I told you that what I see can't be changed.
What my eyes see is "fate" far beyond our grasp.
Hey,
I can't just sit back and take everything you told me.
I'm going to do everything I can.
Your friend won't have anything good to say.
Yeah?
Why do you want to help me so much?
Is it because you lost your left eye?
I'm sure you can see it with your eyes.
I can't see your childhood. It's pitch black.
My oldest memories are from when I was around ten.
I was walking in the dark, in the middle of nowhere.
I couldn't see a thing.
I fumbled around, and soon I saw the moon.
The phony-looking white moon
set, and again rose a moon.
After I wandered through there for a long time,
I finally came to a place where I could see the sun rise.
I still remember how thankful I was for that sunlight.
Aren't you afraid of losing light forever?
I am.
But I'm more afraid of a world with nothing but light.
If you could see everything but couldn't change any of it
or if you could live in freedom in darkness...
Which do you think is more fortunate?
I think it might not be that bad living
in the dark, remembering the light.
What's wrong?
I'm fine.
I just saw it again.
How far ahead can you see now?
Until the moment that these eyes die.
Her eyes could never see through her eyelids.
They could only see others' futures.
For her eyes to see her own future
and to see through her eyelids –
could it be that her eyes are
becoming independent of her?
The Mushi infects the eyes by being seen.
It transforms the eyes so that they
live on after the body dies.
In time when it completely takes over, it leaves the body.
If that's the case, it's going to split off soon.
Still no response to my letter.
"Fate" far beyond our grasp.
Huh? I can't see past the roof.
What...
I can see properly.
Huh? But...
My eyes are moving on their own.
Shit!
Hold on, I'll get you some pain killers.
I guess you don't need eyes to shed tears.
How far ahead can you see now?
Until the moment that these eyes die.
My eyeballs are there buried in the dirt.
Soon they arise, and an animal approaches.
Beautiful flowers appear in the animal's eyes.
And as soon as they get sucked into its eyes,
everything becomes black.
Hey, you should have gotten your letter by now.
...research...
...no known treatments...
Are you going back to your hometown?
I don't know.
I want to go on alone for now.
I'm happy that I can't see the future.
Well then, say hi to me if you ever see me somewhere.
I'll get better at the biwa.
Eye of
Fortune,
Misfortune
The
Sound
of
Footsteps
on the
Grass
The Sound of Footsteps on the Grass.