What's new?
This Kimono Jacket.
Oh? That's a nice painting on the back.
It's by a brilliant painter from a little while ago.
Every now and then there's someone
cooking in these mountains.
Sometimes you see white things rising in the picture.
Waving like the smoke from houses.
Clothes That Embrace the Mountain
I never knew someone's living so deep in the mountains.
No one lives any further than here.
But there's a lot of smoke rising.
Someone must be burning coal then.
The mountain god is making dinner.
Gods cook too?
How else would they eat?
Gods don't get hungry.
Mushishi
He's taking a bath then.
Hey, kids,
hurry home and make our dinner.
Okay.
Let's go.
There was something strange
in the mountains back then.
The mountain is still there just as it was,
but it's not the same as it was then.
Back then, it was as if the village
was embraced in a soft robe.
Sis, what's this?
I made it so that you wouldn't be a
disgrace in front of your master.
I knit it with the silk from silkworms in the mountains
and dyed it with the trees and grass from the mountain.
Kai, if you can't come back, that's okay.
Dad will forgive you if you become great.
But let this remind you of the village.
Thanks, Sis.
I'll be sure to become a great artist.
I want to start painting.
I wonder what Sister and the others are up to.
Hey, you.
Wash those plates there please.
Yes.
It's getting warm.
Hey, come help.
Okay.
Is this your haori?
Whose haura is this?
It's mine.
I'm sorry. I just wanted to do it.
You did this?
Yes.
I don't like it.
I don't like it at all.
Sensei.
Come up to the painting room tomorrow.
Though there isn't much for me to teach you.
Shoot, I'm out of paint.
Just when I was almost done.
Sensei,
how's it going?
The due date's close.
Yeah, leave it to me.
Now, what am I going to do?
I don't have anyone I can borrow money from.
Nothing to sell either.
Pretty raggy, isn't it? I can't give you much.
Please!
I'll come back to get it right away.
It's an excellent piece.
Sure does have your touch to it.
It's hard to believe you're still unknown.
I like it.
How's this?
Could you make another one by next month?
My grandson has a wedding coming up.
It'd be a great opportunity for
you to become better known.
Gladly! I'd love to do it.
Damn.
I can't be sleeping.
It was very well received.
I got all these requests.
I'm proud of you. I'm expecting great things.
Yeah!
Now, how should I compose the next one?
Master, the mail for today.
Yeah, leave it there please.
More deadline reminders.
Don't they ever get tired?
Might as well save themselves the trouble.
I was shocked.
It was a huge landslide.
I heard a whole village got swamped.
I could have been hit too.
It was some village at the skirts
of some mountain to the west.
Can't be.
Can't be my village.
I can't be wasting my time.
This is a precious time for me.
I'm going to get more famous.
That's impressive. It sure is your work.
But Sensei,
are you sick or something?
The last piece I saw was literally flowing with life.
No, I must be thinking too much.
Shit.
What the hell?
You seem tired.
Take some medicine and rest.
But...
Don't worry.
Your fame is virtually set in stone.
Kai,
how do you feel?
Drink this, you'll feel better.
Sister.
How many years ago was it that she married?
I wonder how she's doing.
Dad...
Would he forgive me now?
It's been ten years since then, huh?
I only remember them at times like this.
I'm so selfish.
But I want to see them again.
I want to walk through the scent of the village.
What am I so worried about?
They're my family.
I'm sure I'll be able to make good paintings again.
Can't be...
No...
Auntie?
Is that you, Kai?
What happened here?
Your sister sent you a letter, didn't she?
You haven't read it?
It must have been three years now.
It was a horrible landslide.
Most of the houses and farms got washed away.
We talked it over and decided to send you a letter.
To ask you to come back to help us with your fame.
What about Dad and Sister?
Your dad died in the landslide.
The next year, your sister gave birth to this kid and died.
I don't mean this in a bad way. Just go back to town.
Don't ever come back.
He was a really popular painter.
One day he just vanished, and that was it.
That painting is worth quite a bit in itself.
Yeah?
What do you think?
It's rather heavy for light silk.
I do sense Mushi in it too.
You could sell it to that collector doctor then.
How's this price?
You do say it hasn't caused any harm so far,
but until we find out what it is, it's not safe.
I can't expect to sell it for much.
I'll buy it for half of that price.
You've got to be kidding.
I bet you bought it for the price of a rag.
No, no, I'm sure you could figure
out what it is and sell it for a lot.
It'd be bad if it were a pest.
There aren't any Mushi-shi that would
pay big bucks for stuff like this.
Wait!
Fine.
I have one more piece of information.
It's said that this mountain is
at the painter's home village.
How's that, doesn't that give you a good lead?
Half price.
All right, fine.
I'm sorry to hear.
But please, you must return.
I can't go back.
I can't paint anything anymore.
Nothing comes to mind when I pick up my brush.
The mountain looks like a stranger to me.
Just like I'm a stranger to the villagers here.
I might as well move off to nowhere.
What's this?
I can taste the mountain's soil.
I don't get dizzy these days.
I feel light too.
Hey, Toyo, are you alone again?
I'm taking these to your place.
Is Auntie home?
Auntie went cold.
What are we going to do about the kid?
He has relatives on his father's side.
They're far, but we'll have to give him to them.
Let me...
Let me take care of him!
Please!
He's slow growing and slow learning.
You couldn't take care of him.
I'll take good care of him.
Please.
Please don't send him off afar.
Toyo, hold this please.
That's good.
That's not right. Give it to me.
That'll just tip right over.
Here, don't spill it.
He's already five years old.
But he's still a baby.
Yum!
Here, good work.
Give it to your nephew.
He's gonna love this.
It's back.
The mountain's back.
What's that smoke?
What is this?
Ah, damn it.
I thought I was going to die.
I knew I shouldn't have bought it.
Who the hell are you?
Hey, I'm not anyone suspicious.
It's light.
That's...
It's my haori.
So I searched for this mountain in the painting
to figure out what type of Mushi it is.
But as soon as I got into the mountain,
something strange happened.
What?
My luggage is getting heavy.
What the hell?
When I finally got out of the dirt,
the Mushi were gone from the haori.
Well, it's not a big deal.
The Mushi in the haori seem to
have been this land's Ubusuna.
Ubusuna?
They're a dirt-like Mushi that have
their own specific habitats.
Though they're only in dirt form
when they're underground.
They seem to become a smoggy mist when they rise.
There seems to have been a huge landslide here.
A lot of the Ubusuna must have gotten
washed away when that happened.
Those Ubusuna found this haori,
and attached themselves to it.
There seemed to be a lot of them.
Ubusuna can't live in other lands,
so they must have gathered in.
This cloth was made here, right?
Yes.
My sister made it for me entirely out of
materials from here in the mountain.
I could recall the smells and sounds of the mountain
with it when I first left the village.
Ubusuna gather where there's the scent of their home.
They exist in small amounts in all plants that grow there.
And humans take in Ubusuna when they eat.
Because they're so abundant they're not very strong,
and they lose all influence once the host leaves his land.
It does seem to try to protect you from other Mushi
once you return to your home town though.
Could it have anything to do with a kid's slow growth?
It might happen if he doesn't get enough
Ubusuna during his weaning period.
In which case, a lot of Ubusuna returned to this land,
so he should catch up in time if
you give him lots of local food.
I see.
Hey, you don't need this haori anymore, do you?
Could you sell it to me, please?
I was planning on selling it off.
Please!
It's precious to me.
Fine.
But on one condition.
A haori with Ubusuna in it.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
Smoke rises from the mountain
in the painting once in a while.
In a while? How often?
Once in ten years, maybe.
That really is once in a while.
The painting sure is nice too though.
Isn't it?
It's by a mysterious ingenious artist.
I wanna see it come out.
Well, it almost got me killed.
I'm sure I'm not guilty.
On this?
Yeah. The same painting.
Do you not have paint?
No, I have some.
That's amazing.
It's a mountain.
That's right, Toyo, it's the mountain.
Draw more.
All right,
here goes.
Clothes
That
Embrace
the
Mountain
String
from the
Sky
String from the Sky.