What's wrong?
Hmm... I wonder what this is...
Say, dear...
Do you think this is a tooth?
I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
Mushishi
I reached... for you
Oh seedling that sprouts from
our ancestor's flesh and blood...
Grow green, green leaves.
Bear heavy, heavy seed.
The Heavy Seed
Excuse me...
Can you sell me something to eat?
Take a look at these rice paddies!
This summer has been too cold.
We've our hands full trying to gather
enough stock for ourselves.
Just give it up.
Go to the village past the next mountain.
I heard that they're the only ones with
a bountiful harvest this year.
Hey, don't give him bad advice.
You'd better not go there.
The rice there is not normal.
They get a bountiful harvest every time
when there's a disaster.
I hear it's a curse by their ancestors.
It's a "parting harvest".
It's a "parting harvest."
Meaning, someone will be taken by our ancestors again.
Who will it be this year?
The ancestors choose from the weakest among us.
Wow. What impressive rice paddies!
Who are you? What do you want?
Well, I was just wondering if you wouldn't mind selling me something to eat.
We don't have anything to give to strangers.
We don't harvest enough every year.
We've to store our harvest when we can.
I see, then you're saying that this year's
bountiful harvest is a miracle?
That's right.
Our ancestors watch over us
since we always worship them.
And in exchange, they take a life, right?
That's a pretty harsh thing for your ancestors to do.
We don't have... a choice.
You don't look like you really believe that...
Will you tell me what's going on?
Every time a natural disaster occurs, the fields of this village produce a bountiful harvest.
I've heard it's been happening from very long ago.
And, in such years, without fail, in the autumn,
someone sprouts an auspicious tooth in their mouth.
That tooth falls out at the end of autumn
and that person... dies.
It's been told through the generations that the life is an offering to the ancestors for the bountiful harvest.
Still, we all have been thankful for it.
Without these miracles,
none of us would've been able to
continue living on this unfertile land.
Did those who lose their lives have anything in common?
It is said... the weakest go first.
Are the bodies buried?
Yeah.
What about the tooth?
The tooth is kept in the shrine by the head priest.
Head priest?
He's the person who takes care of
all the religious services in this village.
I'll eventually take his place,
so he's teaching me various things.
It's said that soon after the tooth falls out,
it's only visible to the head priest.
That's why the head priest is the one who keeps it.
Why were you chosen to be his successor?
Because, like the head priest, sometimes I'm able to see things that others can't.
I'd like to meet your head priest.
Head priest!
I wonder if he's in the back fields.
Agricultural literature, and a journal...
It's not often that I've a visitor.
Hm?
Just who are you, anyway?
I am a mushi-shi, Ginko.
I'm looking for something called the Narazu seed.
Well...
Sane, aren't you in the middle of your fieldwork?
Come back when you're done.
This year, we have a bountiful harvest.
We won't be able to catch up
unless we're well-prepared.
Okay.
What? Are you still worried about your mother?
It'll be okay. She'll be fine.
Don't worry.
Here, let her eat this.
Okay...
I've heard that some mushi-shi came to these parts during the previous head priest's time, as well.
But you're wasting your time.
There's no such seed here.
So you're saying this good harvest is
because of your ancestors' grace?
Our ancestors' grace?
Of course, that is a factor, too.
Because of everyone's faith, we're able to work without abandoning this village.
But that's not all.
For many years, we've all been
studying ways to enrich the soil.
The result can be seen at times
with harvests like this one.
Every year, our crops increase, too.
Then what about the auspicious tooth?
Adults can sprout a tooth on rare occasions.
It has nothing to do with the harvest.
Please be on your way now.
May I ask just one more question?
What is it?
You seem to know about the Narazu seed.
Yes, I've heard about it from the previous head priest.
It's a seed that a mushi-shi sealed a "light vein",
or something like that, into it, I think...
That's right.
You probably can even intuitively
understand what a "light vein" is,
because you seem to have the ability to see mushi...
The feebler the mushi is, the more light it takes on.
That's because it's so similar to the Kouki,
which is the basis of mushi.
The light vein is the path in which the Kouki runs.
In a sense, it is life itself.
If you can manipulate it, it can be used for anything—
even immortality or resurrection.
Of course, doing so is the biggest
taboo among mushi-shi.
However, there've been many cases of it happening.
That seed is one of them.
If you plant it in the ground, it'll bring a good
harvest for that year in that area
but in return, it'll take a life from among those that benefited from it.
That's what we know of it.
And? What do you plan to do
with that seed once you find?
Would you destroy it or would you use it?
I was going to ask you that same question.
What would you do?
What if you obtained a seed that could save
many lives at the cost of one life?
I'd probably use it.
If such a seed really does exist, it would be a sin not to use it and let people suffer.
But, if that person planted the seed knowing that it'll cost one person's life—
it's the same as murder.
No matter how many lives can be saved,
the person who dies is forced to be
a sacrifice regardless of his or her will.
If that's the cost of the sin,
then anyone would dirty their hands...
if it means saving two lives at the cost of one.
Indeed, when you look at it from the short span of one year, it'd be senseless not to use it.
But once you use it, you'll keep using it.
And, that seed is alive.
Each time you use it, more powerful the effect is.
Eventually, it could become something
that destroys the balance.
So you're saying you wouldn't use it?
Could you afford... not to?
I don't know. I've never lived in a village.
And I would leave that place
before it came to that point.
Here... in this land...
Our ancestor's flesh and blood sleep here!
They pioneered the land and made it what it's today.
That's our only pride!
Doesn't planting something abnormal in that ground mean you're violating the soil?
What am I saying? This is all supposition.
I know what you're saying.
If there really is such a seed...
...I would think about it more carefully.
That's right...
Such a seed is too much for one man to handle.
Just like an overabundant rice stalk hangs its head,
that seed will certainly fall from
that man's hands, onto the soil below...
unaware of the suffering it'll cause
the people in its aftermath.
Oh! Are you done chatting already?
Well, pretty much.
And... will you save us all?
Yeah. But I first need to get
the consent of the entire village...
after I explain how the "parting harvest" works.
Can you have everyone gather somewhere?
S-sure. But... just what are you planning to...
Are you suggesting we burn down the rice paddies...
...because we've no choice but to destroy the seed before someone sprouts an auspicious tooth?
Yeah, that's right. So you're finally admitting the truth.
You've got it wrong.
Even if we do that, no one will be saved.
Are you trying to make everyone starve to death?
All you've to do is live somewhere else for a year.
Once everyone lives separately, they can probably survive one way or other for a year.
By spring, the ashes should have fertilized the soil.
How many do you think will return
once they leave this land?
They're able to tolerate it because none of them know...
what a real bountiful harvest is!
This is how it should be...
I won't allow you to tell everyone such strange tales!
Head priest!
Does he have some kind of illness?
I'm not sure, but he didn't seem well of late,
and I saw him taking medicine sometimes.
Medicine?
I'm pretty sure this contains it.
I'm not sure for what reason
you've been taking this poison,
but isn't it irresponsible to die
leaving things the way they're?
Say, mushi-shi...
Since you're suggesting we burn the rice paddies,
it doesn't seem like you came hoping to use that seed.
Please... I've made the decision to be
the last sacrifice for the seed.
The one who is said to have brought
the seed here in the first place,
is the head priest before the previous one.
Thereafter, every time a natural disaster occurred, the seed was used,
but in order to prevent panic,
only the head priests knew the truth.
It was 20 years ago when the first natural disaster occurred after I became the head priest,
and I'd to consider using the seed.
I have to use it! If I don't...
I'm stepping out.
Okay. Be careful.
It's for the best.
I was only thinking of the best
interest of the entire village.
It's... for the best.
So I was unaware that my wife was
hiding her illness from me.
In autumn, the one who sprouted
the auspicious tooth was... my wife.
Please, dear.
Have some rice,
or you will die, too...
What are you doing?
Please eat it even if it hurts.
If you eat my life, I don't feel afraid of dying.
Despite it being the rice that it was,
my body greedily accepted it.
I was going to throw out the seed which had eventually fallen out of my wife.
But... I started to think about the next natural disaster, which was sure to come sooner or later.
Then I realized I could use the seed one more time without having to sacrifice someone's life.
Finally, this year,the time had come to use it.
I plan to have Sane destroy the seed
that falls out of my mouth.
I hear it'll be destroyed if it's buried in the place that you call the path of the light vein.
But I don't plan to tell him about the seed.
Are you really okay with that?
More than anyone, you want to live here and see the future of this land, right?
I can see it; if we don't give up,
this land will slowly become fertile.
Surely, the day should come someday
where we can live comfortably.
I don't know how many generations it'll take...
But either way, I won't be able to
see it with my eyes anyway.
All right. I'll let it play out as you wish.
But let me ask you one more thing.
Head priest!
My mom... She's gonna be okay now.
She's eating and slowly getting better.
Really? That's good to hear.
I told you so.
Yeah.
Say, Sane. We need to talk.
It's really important. I want you to listen carefully.
Hey, Sane, the ritual prayer sounds
different from last year's.
Say, no one has sprouted an auspicious tooth yet?
Yeah, I haven't heard any news of it yet.
Maybe this year's bountiful harvest
wasn't a "parting harvest."
Then that means that it's truly
due to all our hard work...
Hey.
The festival... is carrying on fine.
Everyone is having fun.
Don't worry.
I'll do exactly what you asked.
Head priest...
Why does it have to be this way?
This isn't how it should be!
Don't tell anyone what I'm about to do.
Let me ask you one more thing.
I told you that the light vein is like life itself,
but it can't revive a living being even if it was taken in.
But the one thing that can resuscitate life is that seed.
It's a gamble but, even animals would be able to come back to life, if that seed is ingested.
Only, unlike vegetation, the light vein will probably continue to live within you.
If that happens, you'll become an immortal being...
Can you handle that?
I thought doing that's the biggest
taboo among mushi-shi.
Can you... get away with doing that?
If you don't say anything, no one will find out.
I don't even know if it'll work.
I'm not even sure if it'll spell happiness for you.
But if you're willing to take a chance...
This is my apology to you for wrangling out the
truth about the seed from your wounds.
I don't mind dirtying my hands a little.
Give it a lot of thought.
I don't have to think too hard to give you my answer.
I want to see it through after all...
how this land will develop...
...and whether what I've done up
till now was right or not.
Thereafter, it's said that...
the story of that year's bountiful harvest was forever talked about in that village.
At the same time, a strange legend had also begun.
The rice harvested by that year's bountiful harvest,
the first not to be a "parting harvest",
was said to have resurrected a man.
The man became ageless and immortal,
traveling around the country,
and at times returning to convey new farming methods to enrich the land.
The
Heavy
Seed
The
White
Which
Lives
Within
the
Ink
Stone
The White Which Lives Within the Ink Stone.