I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
They are distant creatures.
Primitive and peculiar, they are things unlike
any animal or plant we've grown to know.
In time and with fear, Man has
come to call them "Mushi".
Mushi
Morning, Sui.
Morning, Biki.
The Light of the Eyelids
How are you?
Do your eyes still hurt?
Hey, Biki...
Yeah?
You're the only one I'm going to tell.
I know...
why I'm sick.
There are Mushi in my eyes.
They live there.
They've always been there in my eyes.
Sui is the youngest daughter of the head family.
About half a year ago, she developed
a sickness that made her eyes hurt.
It's a strange sickness, and no eye doctor
could figure out what caused it.
Before they could find a treatment, the smallest
bit of light would cause her eyes pain.
She was left with my family to hide in the dark shed.
It may have been the best thing to do for her,
but it seemed to me as if she
was being abandoned here.
There's another set of eyelids behind our eyelids.
It's a place where light can never reach.
And that's where the Mushi are.
Second eyelids?
Yeah.
Do you know how to close them, Biki?
I'll tell you.
Close your eyes.
Can you see anything?
Nope, nothing.
Oh, but...
Something's flickering.
And it's moving in my eyes.
Yup.
Even if you shut your eyelids, your eyes
are still watching your eyelids.
You haven't really closed your eyes.
So when you want real darkness,
you close your eyes again.
And then true darkness sets in from above.
I can't do it.
Really?
You sure are clumsy.
We play in the deep darkness.
You can't really see anything when you enter the shed.
But after a while, things start to show their
form on the other side of the darkness.
How come I can see?
It's pitch black in here.
Because there's a stream of light beneath the ground.
Huh?
You can see it if you close your second eyelids.
If you watch the true darkness for a long time.
You start to see specks of light in the distance.
And they start to overflow.
If you look carefully, you'd see that they're all Mushi.
But when I try to go closer...
No.
Don't go any closer to the stream.
I don't even know who he is.
A one-eyed man is always there to say
that from the other side of the stream.
So I always watch from a distance.
Sometimes...
I wonder.
The things Sui sees with her eyes shut...
What are they?
Biki!
You're staying in the shed for too long.
I burned her old blindfold.
And I disinfected both my hands and the dishes.
But that doesn't mean you won't get infected.
The head family abandoned her because
they were afraid of that, right?
So we have to...
I know.
That's right.
She's a very good girl.
I have to bear with it, don't I?
Stay with her so that she doesn't
lose the light in her soul.
But please...
don't fall to the same illness.
Really?
You'll...
be here?
What was that?
No way.
It can't be.
It can't be, Mom.
Biki,
are you still sleeping?
Biki!
Biki?
What's wrong?
I'm...
not letting Biki come anymore.
He contracted your illness.
It's not your fault.
He shouldn't have been so compassionate.
Who's there?
If you open the door, Biki...
Don't worry.
I'm an expert in this field.
I gave him medication and painkillers.
He'll get worse if you leave him in the dark.
Who are you?
Oh, excuse me.
I'm Ginko, a Mushi-shi.
I heard rumors about the girl in the shed.
Eye doctors can't handle it;
you have to ask for us Mushi-shi.
Biki... will Biki be okay?
Yeah, it hasn't been long since his Mushi hatched.
Medicinal treatment should do the trick.
Biki.
Biki...
I'm sorry.
I'm sorry...
Sui!
You're up.
Do your eyes still hurt?
No.
Good, it worked.
Sui's sickness is caused by something
called Manako-no-Yamimushi.
They breed in darkness.
You stayed with Sui in the dark for too long.
You know Sui?
One-eyed.
She was there when I closed my second eyelids.
Huh?
The light in that stream isn't of the
same substance as light on Earth.
It's poisonous to the eyes to look at it up close.
He has a left eye.
Maybe he's not the person Sui was talking about.
We're going to start treatment on Sui after sundown.
Okay.
Got it.
Sui.
You...
I told you not to go into that stream.
Sui...
Sui's eyes are dead.
But I'll see what I can do.
Your eyeballs get consumed by the darkness when
you close your second eyelids for too long.
All right then, Sui.
We're going to lure the Mushi out with the moonlight.
Slowly open your eyes with your second eyelids closed.
Come out, Mushi.
It's light.
Mushi?!
There!
Sui, that's enough.
Close your eyes.
That does it.
Now for Sui's eyeballs.
Bugs.
Bugs in her eyes.
Nope, they're no good.
I'm not sure if this'll work, but...
I'm giving this to Sui.
You need to stop freaking out.
Relax. It's just an artificial eye.
This is the liquefied Mushi from earlier.
It'll turn even a glass ball into an eyeball.
Can I ask you something?
That stream of light that the two of you saw.
What is it?
Close your second eyelids.
Have you forgotten?
And the path to darkness will be opened.
You used to be like that, too.
It is said that man forgot how to close his
second eyelids once he found light.
But those who lived may have been better off.
For it is said that many have lost
sight by watching it for too long.
The second eyelids.
True darkness.
Light of a different nature.
The swarm of countless essences of
life swimming beneath our feet.
It got really bright all of a sudden,
and then it was pitch black again.
Then my feet fell through, and I could
see the light flowing way down below.
It was only for a brief moment right after
that Mushi-shi put that eye in you,
but it was really pretty.
I felt like I was being drawn in.
I wished I could watch it forever.
I'm done.
Sui left the shed.
She sees trees, flowers, light.
She'll never be seduced by that strange
light in the darkness again.
I wonder if that man lost his real
left eye the same way Sui did.
The Light
in the
Eyelids
Tender
Horns
Tender Horns.