I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
Mushishi
I reached... for you
Hey... Kid...
Are you still alive?
One-Eyed Fish
You've the ability to see mushi?
There is no need to be afraid.
The type of mushi that give off light
don't have much influential power.
Or is it me you're afraid of?
Drink this. It'll help with your injury.
Okay...
I need you to hurry and get well and leave.
I don't want you to stay long.
Yuck.
Mom...
Mom!
That's odd.
I wonder if we took the wrong road.
Mom!
What, Yoki, are you seeing those weird things again?
Don't worry, don't worry.
They're just illusions.
You've to be strong.
There's no need to be afraid.
I can move my foot a lot better now.
I wonder what kind of fish they are?
They're pure white with green eyes.
They're all missing an eye.
It's because of the mushi living in the pond.
Don't come near here at night or at daybreak.
Uhm... those are not... illusions, are they?
They're neither beings like us, nor illusions.
But they do affect us.
Are they totally different from us?
They're of a different existence
but they're not disconnected from us.
That's a different form of what we consider "life".
I see. I get it.
I can walk now without a cane.
Yoki, isn't your foot better by now?
You've a home to go back to, right?
I don't... have a place to go home to.
I tagged along with my mom,
who was a traveling peddler.
And... my foot... it still hurts when I walk.
I see.
By the way, I've been wondering all this time...
What kind of mushi live in the pond? Tell me.
Ah... well, the best way I can
describe them is "darkness".
Darkness?
Yes. There are two types of darkness.
One is inside a shed, a moonless night,
or when you close your eyes.
It's the darkness that happens
when the sun or light is obscured.
The other darkness is "perpetual darkness".
During the day, they lie motionless
in dark places like this,
but at night, they come out of
the pond to eat smaller mushi.
Why did the eye and hair color
change for you and the fish in the pond?
At dawn, sometimes the pond sparkles silver.
It's probably decomposing the mushi it ate into light.
It seems that if you're constantly
exposed to that, you become like this.
Then, won't you lose your other eye if you stay here?
You saw the fish in the pond, didn't you?
Oddly, there are no fish with both eyes gone.
That's probably the way it happens.
Come now, the sun will soon set. We'd better go in.
What are those mushi called?
Mushi with the characteristics of
darkness are called Tokoyami...
The mushi that give off light seem to be a different mushi that live in Tokoyami,
but I don't know if those mushi have a name.
I call them "Ginko".
How about this one?
You can't eat it.
Then, what about this one?
You can try biting into it.
Don't swallow it.
It's hot!
Ick, what is this?
It won't kill you.
Your stomach will even toughen up from it.
Awful!
Oh! They're balled up!
You broke them up?
They'll ball right back up again.
Whenever I walk through the mountains,
it's a common occurrence.
Hey, can I do that, too?
This isn't something you do just for fun.
I know.
It's a bit strong.
Nui!
Let's turn on the light.
Oh, sorry.
I wasn't aware since I can see in the dark.
Is it because of the Ginko?
Probably. But it's a convenient ability to have.
You know, Yoki, when you walk alone
through the mountains at night,
you may suddenly become unable to see the moon that was shining on the road
and the stars disappear so you become disoriented.
Although it's a common occurrence,
if it seems as though you're starting
to forget your name and past,
it means the Tokoyami is getting near.
It's said that you can escape if you can
somehow remember something.
And what if I just can't remember anything?
It doesn't matter what it is.
They say to come up with a name for yourself.
That'll do?
But they say you won't be able to remember anything
from the time you'd the previous name.
Say...
Do you mind if I ask why you live here?
Sure, I don't mind.
Past these mountains lies my hometown.
Although it's isolated, it's a beautiful village.
Because I've the tendency to attract mushi,
I'm unable to live in one place,
so I became a mushi-shi who traveled
around the villages, driving mushi away.
Still, I frequently returned to my village.
To meet my parents and friends,
but above all my husband and child.
However... one day, I was told that many villagers,
including my husband and child, father and friends, went into the mountains, never to return.
After searching around in the mountains,
I realized that Tokoyami lived in this pond.
I'd heard from other mushi-shi
what happens and what to do
when captured by the Tokoyami.
So I continue to live here,
with the hope that the villagers
are still wandering around somewhere.
How long have you been here?
It's been six years maybe.
By yourself for that long...
I wonder if the others have
the same appearance as you do now?
I'm sure... they do.
I'll help you look for them.
That's okay, right?
So let me just stay...
No!
Why not? Why can't I?
Because I want to do this alone.
That's the only reason.
Don't make that your excuse to stay here.
If you say any more, I'll have you leave right now.
Nui is hiding something.
There's a reason why she doesn't want me to stay.
Come on out, Tokoyami, Ginko.
What's with that fish?
Its good eye is being consumed and...
It disappeared!
Yoki!
What are you doing?
I told you it wasn't good to be exposed to that light...
Nui... The reason why all the fish
only have one eye is because
they disappear when both eyes are gone.
You knew that?
It's not that they disappear.
The light emitted by Ginko
turns living things into Tokoyami.
It's the same thing as disappearing!
If you knew that, why didn't you do anything about it?
You were a mushi-shi, right?
Why do you allow such a terrifying mushi to live?
Do not let fear and anger cloud your vision.
They're all just being as they're.
We're the ones with wisdom,
so we should avoid those things that we can.
Mushi-shi are people who've been seeking how to do that since long ago.
I, too, have been taking notes on Ginko.
And, by the time I finally realized the fate of the fish,
I'd already been exposed to too much light as well.
I took the one-eyed fish out of the pond
and tried repeatedly to protect them from the light.
However,
once the fish started turning white,
although there was a small delay,
they eventually lost both eyes
and turned into Tokoyami.
No... then you're saying...
Still, I refused to believe that
my husband and child became Tokoyami.
I stayed alive by avoiding exposure to
the light and searched for them.
But, after all that,
I eventually came to realize
that all the answers were here.
It's too late to do anything.
Yoki, if you understand what I'm saying, leave here.
No! I'm sure something can be done.
You should leave, too, Nui!
Don't be silly!
I'm beyond help, and I thought
I really didn't care anymore...
but it just makes things harder if you stay.
Please, leave already.
I'm sure you can live on the road.
You're better off not having a beloved home.
No! My home is here!
It's where I've lived the longest.
No. This place is where the Tokoyami and I live.
It's not a place for you.
I've done enough, right?
The pond...
Nui !
Don't go! Don't go!
Nui?!
Wait!
Don't go! Nui!
What have you done?!
Nui? It's you, isn't it?
Go back!
What about you?!
It's too late for me.
Ginko will awaken soon.
Get as far away as you can.
Come now... hurry!
Your hand... I don't feel anything.
It's neither cold nor warm.
Your hand is still warm.
And not just your hand.
I no longer have eyes,
but when you look at me, it's warm like sunshine.
After living near that dim pond,
you don't know how nostalgic it made me feel.
Now, Yoki. From here on, walk with one eye closed.
Give one eye to Ginko
in order to get away from the Tokoyami.
But close the other eye tightly,
so that you'll see the sunlight again.
Oh, no! Ginko is waking up!
Nu!
So that's Ginko...
An eye-less fish... at the bottom of perpetual darkness.
Do not let fear and anger cloud your vision.
They're all just being as they're.
I smell dirt.
There's the moon again.
How many times is this?
I don't know anymore.
My name...
In times like this, what was I supposed to do?
The next day...
...my right eye was staring at the sunlight.
Who are you? I've never seen you
around in these parts before.
H-hey!
Hey, I'm back.
Are you well enough to be up? Don't overdo it.
Yeah.
So were you able to remember anything
else besides your name?
No.
Don't worry. If you like, you can live here.
In any case, let's pay a visit
to the village head tomorrow.
The only thing was...
The hole of my left eye, even in the sunlight, was black as if it was seeped in darkness.
And it attracted weird things.
If it continues to do that, misfortune is sure to follow.
That's the feeling I get.
Hey! Ginko! Dinner time!
Huh?
Ginko? Hey!
Where did he go?
One-Eyed
Fish
One-Night
Bridge
One-Night Bridge.