I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
There was a hole in the mountain.
There's the Reihou. Sure is a sight.
Soba please, miss.
All right, two coming up.
And sake too.
Excuse me, man.
It's gone.
The Sleeping Mountain
Someone has to go.
But it'll be the same thing all over again.
We can't go into the mountains right now.
Mujika-dono said so too.
No, that's why we're worried about him.
Are you arguing about the mountain?
Who are you?
I'm a Mushi-shi.
Something's not right about the mountain,
so I figured I might be of help.
Hey, did he say Mushi-shi?
He did say Mushi-shi.
What?
Elder.
Right.
Well then, can we ask something of you?
Can you search the mountains
for a Mushi-shi named Mujika?
For generations, there has been an omniscient
"Master" of the mountains.
Mujika-dono is the one person
who knows the Master's will.
We have always followed his directions when necessary.
This is also one of his instructions...
During the harvest seasons, such as now, we are
forbidden to venture deep in the mountains.
However, Mujika-dono has disappeared,
and several of us ventured into the mountains
against his orders to find him.
They developed a fever and almost lost their lives.
The energy here is overwhelming.
A little sweet, a little bitter... it sticks to my skin.
This place is a Koumyakusuji.
Koumyakusuji: koumyaku channel
The river of life flows through here.
Especially during fruitful seasons such as now.
All the mountains rise in energy.
Enter without preparation and you can lose
consciousness from exposure to it.
Since there's a Koumyakusuji, there must
be a "Master" here to keep control.
Something must have happened to the Master
to cause the mountain's anomalies.
So then our Mushi-shi must know about it.
A kid from the village?
Hey.
What are you doing here?
I'm looking for Mujika.
I'm Mujika's student.
So he has students.
Keep this in between your back teeth.
It's bitter.
Bite it when you start feeling dizzy.
It's an analeptic.
You could've told me earlier.
Stay here for a while.
I'll find your master.
What are you doing?
Muguranori.
There are Mushi that make up the mountain's
"nerves", called Mugura.
I'm going to merge my consciousness with the
Mugura and scout through the mountain.
Here they come.
Not here.
Not this way, go around.
To the other side of the mountain.
There!
He looked this way.
He pulled the Mugura off of me.
Are you all right?
I see.
Let's go.
This way.
What, really?
Was that a bell? It must be around seven.
I don't remember a bell over there.
He should be here somewhere.
Over there!
Hey!
Mujika!
So you slipped and hurt your leg...
...and I was there eating the fruits and grass.
I had water too.
I couldn't impart the Master's thoughts
to the villagers. My apologies.
Not to mention, being saved by a fellow Mushi-shi.
Ginko's the name.
I'm Mujika.
I'll have to thank you.
I've always thought of this mountain as my backyard.
Didn't think that I'd fall at a place like that.
I sure am getting old.
It might be time to retire.
As the Master of the mountain?
Only the real Master of the land or a
man using the Master's techniques
could pull Mugura off of an invader.
The reason for the mountain's anomalies
is that you, the Master,
were stuck in the gully, and couldn't
maintain control of the mountain.
Yeah.
But from tomorrow on, I should be able to continue
my job as the Master, even with this broken foot.
The mountain will return to normal.
I've heard it's painful for a human to become a Master.
Is there a reason you're doing it?
You must have noticed, this place is a Koumyakusuji.
We had a decent Master here that
controlled the mountain's energy.
But... one of the villagers killed it by accident.
The river water smelled of alcohol.
The greenery became overripe and rotted.
I used to be a traveling Mushi-shi too, way back then.
I came here often and saw that the villagers were
troubled, so I decided to stay here as the Master.
My wife didn't live long, probably
due to the mountain's energy.
So that child is going to be the next Master?
Yeah.
He's a pretty good mountain climber.
He is, isn't he?
He was born of the mountains
and raised by the mountains.
You saw how many kids there were in the village, right?
The women give birth one after another because
of the water from the mountain.
We can't raise them all, so they get
abandoned in the mountains.
He's probably the only one who
hasn't been eaten by animals.
But his siblings who stayed in the
village were all short-lived.
It's been a year since his parents learned
that he was alive, and brought him here.
That's rather selfish.
Well, it is, but there's nothing that can be done.
It's all for the best.
A bell?
This late at night?
Have you always been a traveling Mushi-shi?
Yes, I have.
Because I attract Mushi.
I'd turn any place into a Mushi hive
if I lived there for too long.
Dispelling Mushi came naturally to me.
So you've got no choice but to be a wanderer.
Well, it suits me well. It's not bad.
Really?
I haven't had a chance to set foot outside
this mountain in a long time.
I envy you.
For better or worse, this mountain
is where my grave will be.
I'm going to let the villagers know.
Go easy on yourself until I'm back, okay?
I know.
You better not come back until
the ban is lifted too, all right?
Well then, good luck.
Okay. Take care.
Mujika,
I'm still your student, right?
Of course.
Traveling here from the village is good training.
You'll be a great Mushi-shi in no time.
Hey, they're back!
Kodama's here too. Mujika-san's well.
It's coming closer.
It's not because of the wind.
Where's it coming from?
Ginko-san!
That sound's not right. There
aren't any bells around here.
Dad says he can't hear anything.
Do you think it's a Mushi?
Let me ask you something.
Have you been taught the Master's technique?
Master's?
The technique for a human to become a Master.
You enter a constant Muguranori state by
containing Mugura within your body.
Even when you're asleep, you receive all
the senses of the mountain's plants.
If you can bear that, and you
can manipulate the Mugura,
you'll have the strength to sustain
the mountain's extreme energy.
I haven't learned that yet.
I see.
The Mushi causing the bell to ring
isn't anything to worry about.
Go home and get some sleep.
Where are you going?
I was in the middle of a stroll.
All right?
The mountain's dead silent.
It must be close.
The old bastard called up some serious trouble.
Where is he?
That sound...
It's coming from the peak.
Is there something you still need?
You aren't injured, are you?
You were hiding there to call a "Kuchinawa".
What are you talking about?
That bell sound that's approaching.
It's the Kuchinawa's howls.
The Master-eating Mushi.
It eats Masters of mountains, Masters of
swamps, and takes the Master's place.
And it's a Mushi that brings stability to the land.
It's my mission to do this.
Don't interfere, please.
It was a magnificent Master.
A magnificent Master that took the
form of a great, elderly boar.
It was my fault.
I shouldn't have even mentioned it.
I'll listen to it later. Get out of the mountain, quick.
It's too late.
The Kuchinawa found me.
It is the most suited for the Master's throne.
It's too painful for a man.
I've only taught Kodama the necessities to live.
What are you doing?
I'm pulling the Mugura off of you.
It's no use.
There's no other way, even if you could do it.
There's got to be something better than this!
What are you going to do about the villagers?
They love you.
They need you.
You said you were a little jealous of me.
I was a little jealous of you too.
So don't kill yourself like this.
Don't do it!
You'll get eaten too!
What the hell?
Mujika?
Mujika!
Hey!
Mujika's here.
Mujika.
Saku.
Welcome back.
Yeah.
Hey, everyone. How's the mountain?
We had some strange things happen this year too.
I'm so glad you came.
Say, Mujika. Why don't you live here with us?
We need you in this village.
I can't.
Why not?
I tend to attract Mushi.
I'll turn the place into a Mushi hive.
Isn't there any way?
Saku... My sister's always been waiting for you to come.
Couldn't you start a family here with her?
There's only one way I could live here.
I'd have to kill the Master, eat its body,
and become the Master myself.
Then I could fend off Mushi from
the mountain at my will.
I want to live here too.
But it wouldn't be acceptable.
I can't find the Master's route map and poison.
Since when?
Saku. Where'd you–
I got a share of some tree peony.
I'll make a pot stew.
Give me a moment.
I'll make it really good.
Saku.
So please.
Please. Stay here.
I had a dream that certainly didn't belong to me.
You were collapsed at the mountain
peak when I got there.
Mujika's gone.
I looked for him everywhere, but I can't find him.
Even his hut was gone.
Not a single person in town remembers him.
That's what it means
to be consumed by a Kuchinawa
and to give up the Master's seat.
Though it seems that the people who were in
the mountain at the time remember him.
Huh?
Did you make this Mushi repellent?
Yep.
Wow. That's pretty good.
It's nothing.
I'm Mujika's student.
Kodama.
There's a tree that they just can't cut
down. Do you have any tricks?
I'll be right there.
I'll be right back.
Yeah, don't worry about me.
It's cold.
There's no other way.
There's got to be something better than this!
Nope, unfortunately.
Sure is amazing.
You don't give a damn about how people feel.
Do you, Kuchinawa?
It let out a roar as if to yawn,
and just rolled over quietly.
The
Sleeping
Mountain
One-Eyed
Fish
One-Eyed Fish.