I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
Mushi-shi?
Ginko is my name.
I hear that you have prophetic dreams.
You're well known around here.
But I think that your dreams could pose a problem.
How so?
It seems that Mushi are involved.
The Mushi in your dreams.
They're the ones causing you to have prophetic dreams.
And you'll have them more frequently.
You should adjust them with this medicine.
How often do you have these dreams right now?
Once or twice every ten days.
Eventually you'll have four or five.
At that point, you should take these.
It's poisonous if you take more.
But if you leave it untreated, at some point
you will not awaken from your dreams.
What's important is moderation.
Be sure to take them, please.
I'll be back by the time they run out.
Until then,
sweet dreams.
The Pillow Pathway
"Do not converse with one talking in their sleep."
That is the wisdom of the world beyond.
It hasn't even been a year since I last came.
What in the world happened here?
You're here.
Mushi-shi.
I've been waiting for you. I want to ask you some things.
Are you alone?
This town... did it...
Yeah, it did.
I'll tell you what happened. Everything.
Damn.
What a pain.
Oh my.
It's a water channel.
We could expand the farm fields with this.
Hey, we found it!
Jin did it again.
Tell the townspeople.
The farmers gave us all this as a gift.
I feel a little guilty.
Yeah.
We can hardly feed her anything good.
We should be thankful.
Yamamomo!
But Jin,
you're having more prophetic dreams.
It's just like that Mushi-shi said.
You really believe him?
That Mushi are giving me these dreams?
I don't know. But what if...
What if he's right?
I get it.
I'll take the medicine.
Will you?
Thank God.
The western cliff collapsed!
Thank you so much.
If it weren't for your dream, we'd all be...
I don't know how to thank you enough.
Kinu, sometimes I get worried.
When what I see in my dream becomes real...
it seems as if I'm the one who made it happen.
That's not true.
Jin-san!
This is for last time. Take it, please.
Hey, have good dreams for us too.
Well, I don't know.
Give him a break, it's a dream after all.
Well, we're counting on you.
Thanks.
It'll be okay, Jin.
You must be receiving the dreams
in order to save everyone.
Everyone seems happy, thanks to you.
There's nothing to be afraid of.
Yeah, I guess.
– is what I told my wife.
But I was still afraid of my dreams,
and I began taking the medicine.
But...
Tsunami!
Mayu...
Our child, on the shore.
Can't be.
I never had such a dream.
I can't believe it.
Why didn't I predict this?
Mayu...
It's all because of this medicine.
That's why I couldn't save Mayu.
So I stopped taking the medicine.
And then I began having more prophetic dreams;
they became more and more accurate.
Look, Jin.
More gifts for us at the door.
We've got to cheer up.
And one day...
You had a dream?
You're sweating.
A bad dream?
No.
I'm just not feeling good.
It wasn't a dream.
And the following day...
Kinu...
It was the exact sickness that I saw in the dream.
Green mold grew from the fingertips...
spread around the whole body... and crumbled like dirt.
And...
I was left alone in the village.
Ginko, was it?
When that dream came true, I realized...
that you had deceived me.
The Mushi don't give me prophetic dreams.
They bring my dreams into reality and infect it.
That green sickness...
It spread to the people around me first.
My wife, my neighbors, across the street...
And the scene in my dreams became
the scene before my eyes.
I wasn't "predicting" anything –
My dreams were making them happen.
Isn't that right?
But why did you lie to me?
Because these Mushi are ineradicable.
Once you've become infected, all you
can do is live with it in moderation.
But if I were to tell you the true nature of the Mushi,
you would have collapsed under the
significance of your creations.
Yeah, and I should have died!
Why did you let such a disaster live?
Why?
I'm sorry.
I'll see to it that I rid you of the Mushi.
Live, please.
Yumeno Noawai.
They live within their host's dreams. But every
so often, they come out of the dreams.
And when that happens, they become
the carriers of their host's dreams.
In other words, they don't turn every dream into reality...
As they multiply, they leave the dreams more often.
And they become capable of realizing
dreams on a higher scale.
The Mushi are frail; they vanish under sunlight.
It's not known why they want to come to the real world.
But it's said that there is a gathering place for the Mushi,
and that they stay there while their host is awake.
If I could find that, I could do something.
But I've never heard of such a fast and enormous case.
The drugs won't help.
But overdose would...
Hey!
The medicine. You took all of them?
Hang in there.
We need an antidote!
Leave me.
Forget it. I can't go on living.
His eyes are moving.
He must be dreaming.
Forgive me.
Sleep talking?
It's not your fault.
Nor was it the Mushi's fault.
You were both just trying to live.
Nobody is guilty.
Don't die.
You've done nothing wrong.
I see geese.
So he was talking in his sleep. He's making no sense.
Where are you right now? Come back quickly.
I'm in a field of reeds.
He responded.
What's this buzzing?
What the hell?
My conversing with him just bridged his dream to reality.
So he thinks these are all geese?
These are all swarms of Yumeno Noawai.
Welcome home, Dad.
Mayu.
Welcome home.
Kinu.
I'm sorry.
I'm sorry, both of you.
You must hate me.
I killed all of you.
It's okay, Jin.
It's not your fault.
You did nothing wrong.
Is someone there?
It's me.
There's something showing on the screen.
Fire?
It's hot.
Someone...
Is that my dream on the screen?
The dream just spread out of my pillow.
That's it!
Here too!
Wake up!
Water...
The dream came from the pillow.
...there is a gathering place for the Mushi,
and that they stay there while their host is awake.
I never thought they'd be here.
Damn filfthy Mushi!
Don't do it!
Why?
Why me?
Looks like your quick aid saved him.
He should be fine.
Did you know this would happen?
I only cut the pillow.
Did you know?
It's said that the word "makura"
comes from "tamashii no kura".
The word "pillow" means a "soul vault".
You spend almost a third of your life on your pillow.
So it was believed that your soul resided in your pillow.
And that is the Yumeno Noawais' nest,
and it was the pathway between your dreams and reality.
I knew that you'd lose something if you were to cut it.
Between dreams and reality is the vault of your soul.
No one could see the "Dream World" without this path.
He later continued working as a blacksmith.
He was well known for his skill...
But in time his mind became poisoned.
At times he'd draw his sword on the streets,
and in the end he faced it towards himself.
People would say...
"He feared sleep."
"He'd say that his soul would slip down into nothing."
He'd not dreamed once since the day he cut his pillow.
The
Pillow
Pathway
The
Traveling
Swamp
The Traveling Swamp.