I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
Are you okay, Hana?
Yeah.
We're almost at the bridge.
Hana!
One-Night Bridge
This is going to be fun.
Guess I'll have to cross it.
This isn't gonna hold!
I made it.
Hey, are you from around here?
Yeah.
This bridge isn't going to last.
I have to cross it again when I leave.
Yeah, you're right. I'll take care of it.
How long are you staying?
Honestly, I don't know.
Do you know who this person is?
Yeah.
Thank you for coming out so far.
Now, this way please.
My daughter, Hana.
She fell from the Kazura Bridge three years ago.
Fortunately she survived, but all she
does now is sit under the sun.
We've had quite a few doctors look at her,
but she doesn't have any head injuries.
We still don't know what happened.
Huh, you're...
How's Hana doing?
Oh, you know her?
I'm the one that did this to her.
Please. Do something for her.
Can you take me to the bottom of the gorge?
And... tell me what happened
when Hana fell to the bottom.
Come on, stop crying.
But I can't refuse a marriage arrangement
with the head family.
I guess we wouldn't receive any more
support in this village if you refused.
Well...
you can't refuse...
Let's run.
But...
My family would get ostracized.
My parents will understand.
Your parents should too, if they really care about you.
You couldn't live the life you want to here.
Let's go past the gulf, past the mountains
to somewhere open and bright.
Let's do that, Hana.
Careful, it's a bit weak there.
Zen.
What's wrong?
I can't do it.
We can't abandon everyone just
so that we can live as we please.
Hana.
I can bear it.
You'll always think of me, right?
I'll always think of you.
Even if I have to hide my feelings.
No.
I don't like it.
Come on, let's just cross the bridge.
Hana.
Hana!
Did you find her?
Nope.
She fell from a fatal height.
Yet she walked home on her own legs.
But... she became hollow inside.
Everyone cried saying that she'd become a "Tanimodori".
"Tanimodori"?
Such people appear every now and then.
They fall into the valley and come out
alive, but their minds are consumed.
Hitoyobashi: One-Night Bridge
They die on the night when the "Hitoyobashi" shows up.
Well, it's just a legend.
"Hitoyobashi"?
People have seen a bridge spanning
across the valley for just one night.
It was a while ago though.
Is something wrong?
No.
They're here.
What are?
The same thing that are possessing Hana.
Hana? Possessed?
By a vine-like Mushi called a Nisekazura.
I don't see anything.
They're not easy to see.
Rather frail for a Nisekazura.
Just like it's said in the scriptures, they're
strong when you tug the other way.
It's already getting dark.
They're all rushing toward the remaining sunlight.
There isn't enough light here.
So, did you find anything?
I've got bad news for you.
Neither the "Tanimodori" nor the
"Hitoyobashi" are legends.
Both can be explained by Nisekazura.
Normally, Nisekazura live on treetops.
The Nisekazura here must be trying to flee
from the gulf by taking over other beings.
They need more light, but they don't have
the energy to climb to the top of the gulf.
Thus, they live in another being's body,
gathering sunlight and strength.
When enough have gathered, they leave
in swarms to head to better places.
That must be the "Hitoyobashi".
I've heard of it before.
That there's a migration of Mushi across
a valley every twenty or so years.
So then, why do the "Tanimodori" die?
Wouldn't they be cured once the
Mushi or whatever leaves?
I looked around, but I didn't see any animal skeletons.
The Nisekazura are most likely infecting onto corpses.
In which case, even if they leave, they'll
just become corpses again.
No way...
Then Hana will eventually...
It's this year.
The last time the "Hitoyobashi" appeared
was the year my grandpa was born.
My grandpa's sixty this year.
Can't we make it longer?
Well...
I'm not asking you to bring her back. I just
want her to live as long as she can.
So please...
Then...
Unfortunately, the best way to keep
her alive is to leave her as she is.
You can rid her of the "Mushi", can't you?
Yes, but chances are nine out of
ten that she will die on the spot.
I don't care.
Do you think she's happy living as she is now?
We might as well...
There's no reason to take such a risk.
If she was alive at the time three years ago,
she will return to normal after the "Hitoyobashi" appears.
Nonsense!
There's no telling if or when such a thing would show up.
We have good arrangements for her if she comes back.
We can't have them waiting any longer.
I don't think I can approve.
She isn't herself anymore.
But she's still being kept alive.
We can't treat her like a thing.
Ginko-san.
Hey, Zen.
Are you leaving now?
I'd like to.
I'll reinforce the bridge by the end of tomorrow.
Why don't you rest at my place for the night?
Are you living here alone?
My family's in the village, but you know, I'm a pariah.
I've been isolated from the villagers.
Haven't you ever thought about leaving by yourself?
Quite a few times, actually.
But Hana was still alive.
I'll probably leave after Hana's gone.
What was that?
So it finally collapsed.
Probably because you crossed it.
No one's been using it lately.
Man, can you hurry up and fix it?
Seriously.
Everyone's really busy though.
It'll take a while.
Shit.
I'm screwed.
Zen.
Zen!
You're hiding the Mushi-shi man, aren't
you? We're not done talking yet.
Give me a break.
Was that a "Tanimodori" too?
Maybe there's more around here.
Hana?
What's wrong? Where are you going?
Hana.
You're warm.
You're still alive, aren't you?
Hey, you're Hana, right?
You've...
just forgotten everything, right?
There she is!
Hana!
Zen! What are you doing?
I told you not to go near Hana!
Hana...
She's not breathing.
Hana! Wake up!
Zen, what happened?
Hana...
died.
A black thread slipped out of her neck.
I see.
Say, Zen, do you want to leave with me?
It'd be for the better.
But...
The "Hitoyobashi" will show up today.
We should be able to cross it from this side.
There's enough excited Nisekazura
around for even you to see.
Decide by midnight tonight.
There's no telling when you'll be able
to leave if you miss this chance.
You're here. You've no regrets, I hope.
You'll fall through if you return.
We'll make it.
Yeah.
Right.
I'll forget it.
I'll be able to forget if I leave.
What?
What are you doing? We can't go back.
I can't go forward. Hana's in here.
No! Hana died three years ago!
She didn't.
I survived these three years because
Hana was alive for me.
It hurt me to see her like that.
But it was still better than now.
I can't step on her and move on.
Don't go back!
I don't know what happened to him since then.
But, he probably...
The next time the Hitoyobashi
will cross the valley again...
will be about twenty years from now.
One-Night
Bridge
Inside
the Cage
Inside the Cage.