I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
A Sea of Writings
Oh.
Ginko. It's you.
Hi.
How's your work?
Same old.
How's Tanyuu?
Same old as well.
She was writing earlier; she's resting now.
Are you going to the archives again today?
Yeah.
Wait there.
What do you want to read?
I read mostly everything up to the last generation.
Then everything from Tanyuu's generation.
They're on the shelves over there.
Thanks a lot.
Oh, right. Give me your tobacco.
I won't smoke it here.
I can't take any risks.
You must not forget that these texts
aren't just treatment references.
I know.
Yes,
these texts are no doubt confidential.
Not just the content,
but even the very reason for its existence is secret.
Foreword:
Birth of the fourth Karibusa Family scribe Tanyuu
by Karibusa Family Mushi-shi Minai Tama.
Can't be.
There's no doubt about it.
The black birth mark.
She is the fourth scribe.
Tanyuu-ojousan.
Please, return to your room.
No!
I want to go play outside too.
Why do I have to keep studying how to read and write?
Why don't my legs move?
I suppose...
you would understand now.
I will explain everything.
The mark on your leg comes from
when a Mushi was contained.
My ancestors contained a forbidden
Mushi in your ancestor's body.
Forbidden?
Yes.
By nature, plants and animals
exist in harmony with Mushi.
Where plants and animals thrive, Mushi also thrive.
Where plants and animals die, Mushi also die.
But when plants, animals and Mushi declined
in a great disaster long ago...
an anomalous Mushi came to be...
and tried to destroy all other life.
What sort of Mushi?
Its appearance, its shape, how it was contained...
not a single record has been found.
What has been passed down in my lineage...
is that the body of your ancestor who contained
the Mushi was covered in black.
The Mushi survived in her body,
but she died after giving birth.
Every few generations since then in the Karibusa family,
a child is born with a black mark on part of their body.
Is it still living in here?
Am I going to die too?
I am here so that you will not.
You are given the ability to quell the Mushi.
I will assist.
When you're a better writer,
come with me to my country home.
There we will drive the forbidden Mushi underground.
Then the mark on your body will be
gone and you will be able to walk.
That is how three of your ancestors
so far have slowly quelled it.
Miss, we have arrived.
That was an old dream.
I was surprised by the remedy that Tama taught me then.
I am going to tell you a story.
Write it down on paper later.
All the stories that Tama told me
were stories of Mushi that she'd defeated
when she was a Mushi-shi.
They were true stories that seemed
almost like fairy tales.
The grandiose stories she told intensely,
the sad stories she told in candlelight.
Distant lands, foreign people.
I was always captivated.
But when I write them on paper, excruciating
pain runs through the mark on my foot.
Are the Mushi coming out of my body?
Yes.
The tales of the Mushi being defeated
are the bane of this Mushi.
It is painful but please bear it.
Tama.
You were forced to become a Mushi-shi
for my sake, weren't you?
Wasn't it painful?
Didn't it anger you?
I've forgotten all such things when I met you.
I am grateful now.
Tell me the rest.
Are you okay?
Yes, I'm okay.
It was when Tama ran out of stories...
and called in other Mushi-shi...
that I began to realize how much effort
she made to make it easier for me.
And to exterminate the pest,
I spread this predacious Mushi all over the mountains.
Within a month, the pests were gone without a trace.
Of course, when that was done,
I exterminated this Mushi as well.
It wouldn't be good for it to become too dominant.
All of the stories I'd heard until then
were in essence all about killing.
The pain in my leg came to bring pain to my mind.
Arrogance towards the minute and inferior life forms.
Murder brought forth by baseless fear of the paranormal.
Those notions became more than noticeable.
Is it necessary to kill them, you ask?
With all due respect, I believe you could only
speak of it if you've dealt with Mushi.
That was the truth.
But there wasn't anything I could do about it.
If only my legs would move.
Say there.
Are you the daughter of the Karibusa family?
Yeah.
Thought so. There aren't any other homes around here.
Oh, so this must be that black birth mark.
You're a Mushi-shi too, huh?
You're collecting Mushi stories, aren't you?
I heard I'd be allowed to browse the
Karibusa Archives if I helped out.
Sorry, leave please.
I'm sick of hearing about killing Mushi.
How about stories about not killing them then?
Ah, I think I have more of those.
That wouldn't do me any good.
Let's start with the story about
the skin mole-eating Mushi.
Moles?
Did you say something?
No, nothing.
Go on.
About that Mushi.
I'm not supposed to let you in
without Tama's permission.
But I doubt she'd want to hire a Mushi-shi like you.
So just for you.
Oh man.
Just handle it carefully.
The Mushi are inside the text.
Yeah, I heard about it.
The forbidden Mushi, right?
I'll be fine.
Damn, this is a Mushi-shi's gold chest.
I guess.
But it's all just a catalog of death.
I want to hear more about animals
and Mushi living together.
I'll persuade Tama.
Could you please come to talk again?
Gladly.
Miss.
Oh, you're awake.
Ginko is here.
Bring him in, please.
What's this?
Shimi eggs.
Shit, here too.
And here.
The text's falling apart.
Has it awakened?
Ginko.
Otama-san, the Shimi's eating the paper!
It's going to break the seals.
Oh no!
Miss!
What's wrong?
Parts of the seals have been broken!
They are headed your way!
This can't be good.
It's fine, there's no getting out.
So you were alive.
No kidding, you'd never think they were
concealed for hundreds of years.
No, I'm talking about you, Ginko.
You don't seem worried.
Can you put them back?
I can contain Mushi too, you know.
Tama.
Yes.
The text stopped moving.
There's special glue on the walls
and ceiling of this room.
Volume 1853.
Chapter one.
Chapter two.
You have it all memorized?
Paper decays after a while whether
or not there's any Shimi.
So the text has to be transcribed little by little.
Though it wouldn't suffice to just copy it normally.
This is the technique that's been
passed down in my family.
Those Shimi are her beloved pets.
I like them, they're cute.
Don't you think they've overbred?
It's fine. So long as I do the transcription properly.
Such a dangerous game.
I won't mess up.
It's my task.
There is a girl living and drowning in a sea of words.
And that's that, huh?
What else?
We should call it a day.
I'm fine.
Not even half of it could go towards
containing the Mushi.
Aren't you tired? You haven't slept.
Take it easy.
Fine.
Ginko, stay here until I'm done please.
Yeah.
There is a girl whose body is eaten away by Mushi...
who appreciates Mushi and who contains Mushi.
Has she finished?
Yeah. Blanket, please.
Ginko.
I don't need to rest.
I want to go outside.
Can you take me?
I wonder when I'll be able to move these legs.
Take your time.
The mark's slowly going away, right?
Very slowly.
If I can't get rid of it by the time I die,
the burden will eventually go to my descendants.
Just as it has until now.
I guess it won't end at my generation.
So...
What are you going to do when your leg heals?
I want to travel with you.
I want to see the Mushi that you've
been telling me about.
Just kidding.
I'll be an old lady by then.
I'm kidding.
Sure.
But only if I survive until then.
You better live.
Nah, I might get eaten by a Mushi tomorrow even.
You better live anyway.
Give me a break.
It'll be fine.
A
Sea of
Writings
Cotton
Changeling
Cotton Changeling.