Build a fire – night comes.
Light the fire – darkness comes.
Hide the fire – flames arisen from corpses creep in.
Mushishi
That flame...
Don't go near that fire, everyone!
This is my punishment.
Had I been mistaken?
Should I have done what that man said?
The Journey to the Field of Fire
I must be close.
Hey,
I heard there's a Mushi-shi in this village.
Mushi-shi?
Maybe he's talking about Yahagi.
She's in the fields with Dad and the others.
These weird weeds started growing.
They're killing all the trees.
It's decided then.
We'll have to cut down all the trees around the village.
Yeah.
Yahagi!
Kids!
I told you not to come here.
Did you hurt yourself again?
I brought a guest here.
Guest?
Don't touch the grass!
I see.
You wouldn't have noticed just one of these.
Though you'd have to notice that they're
Mushi with so many of them now.
Are you a Mushi-shi?
My name's Ginko.
I heard there's a new variety around
here, so I figured I'd investigate.
Unfortunately...
The investigation is already finished.
Ow!
Hold still.
It's fine.
I thought I'd heard the name Yahagi somewhere.
I've read a few of your reports before.
I'm surprised.
Never thought you'd be such a young lady.
Why, thank you.
Your research on that Mushi must be good too.
Do you mind if I take a look?
At what I have so far, sure.
So far?
I thought you said you were finished.
There's no need to investigate anymore.
We're burning the whole mountain tomorrow.
You're burning the mountain?
Yes.
Why? I thought it was just the weeds that were bad.
It's our only option.
Are all the animals going to die?
We drove out as many of them as we could.
But...
We can't let those weeds live.
The mountain and even your lives will be in danger.
You have to understand.
This is our last stand for survival.
Are there really no other options?
We're out of time.
I might be able to help.
Can you tell me what happened so far?
I suppose.
It was two months ago.
We were tilling the soil to plant crops in the field.
That's when we found a huge, black rock.
Being so close to a volcano, there
are a lot of lava rocks here.
As always we just dug it up and
left it at the edge of the field.
Next morning...
There was a weed growing from a crack in the rock.
Back then, we didn't even notice it.
We went back three days later after a long storm
and the weeds had filled all of the newly tilled soil.
We cut them and pulled them, but they must
have been connected at the roots...
They kept growing back.
It was too late by the time I noticed
it involved the paranormal.
The weeds began emitting a poison
from their flower-like attachments
and killing all of the nearby plants.
It was relentless.
We tried everything to exterminate them,
but nothing worked.
The weeds grew all over the mountains.
Now it's approaching the village.
But the whole mountain is too much to sacrifice.
We don't even know what the Mushi is.
There's no telling what sort of repercussions there'll be.
You need to do everything you can to gather
enough people to pull out every single weed.
No matter how long it takes.
We won't survive the winter if we lose our crops.
Our lives are at risk.
That's exactly why.
It's no use panicking.
Are you telling me that it's worth some lives?
I'm telling you to risk only your own lives, if any.
Quite true.
But the frightened villagers would never understand.
So such reasoning holds no meaning.
That goes for you too.
I know you're upset having not noticed the Mushi.
But you can't let yourself be intimidated.
I just want to protect my village.
For that I won't make any compromises.
You can have those reports.
I hope you find them useful for future research.
Please, be on your way now.
They cut down the big cinnamon tree.
The cherry blossoms are gone too.
Hey!
Stop cutting, please.
Who the hell are you?
How much are you putting on
the line for just your village?
Please, calm down and think it over.
We don't want to ruin the mountain either.
But our families' lives are at risk.
You're a Mushi-shi from outside, aren't you?
We already have a good Mushi-shi here.
What would an outsider know about us?
As an outsider, you all look like a bunch
of panicking monkeys to me.
Lost in your own fear, wailing your arms around blindly.
The hell's your problem?
If you're any different from the monkeys,
prove it by overcoming your fear.
That is why man learned to use fire, is it not?
I'm telling you to use your head.
Our use of fire is part of our intellect.
It's half-assed.
That's not the point.
I thought I told you to be on your way.
Get lost!
Everyone, listen carefully.
We found the weeds at the outskirts of the village.
Cut quickly.
We'll have to set fire to the forest tonight.
Ow.
Maybe I said too much.
Sure enough, she's done a good job.
She must regret having to burn it all.
There's nothing I can do.
It's up to you to stop them.
No!
I have a bad feeling about this.
That thing was living inside a lava rock.
They can't give it fire.
I just know it.
Let's burn it.
We can survive now.
Yeah.
It's all gone now though, isn't it...
What's that sound?
Hey, look.
What's that?
Those are...
Kagebi.
Go home everyone, hurry!
Don't let those flames near the village.
Hey!
Close all of your containers!
Tell everyone in your neighborhood.
Hurry up or those fireballs are going to infest.
Do as he says. Hurry!
Everyone, listen carefully.
Those things look like flames, but they're called Kagebi.
They show up on rainy days and on cold days
while they slowly consume the heat of those
who go near expecting it to be fire.
On warm days, they hide in tight
spaces like pots and hollow logs.
There must be a few already lurking in the village.
From now on, be careful when you go near fire.
You might freeze to death if you're near it for too long.
How are we supposed to be careful?
If a fire is cooler than it should
be, it's probably a Kagebi.
In every Kagebi is a Mushi called a "Hidane".
That Mushi is the heart of the Kagebi.
They thrive on human heat.
But it's okay.
As long as you're careful, you'll be safe.
This is a pain in the ass.
I never would have thought that those
weeds were young Hidane.
But we can respond to Hidane.
I've read about it in the past.
Too bad they weren't a new species, huh?
I'm glad we found out what it was though.
Don't take it out on me.
Kagebi are persistent.
You're the only one in this village
that can deal with them.
If it gets out of hand, write me a letter here.
I'll give you a hand.
It's for the reports you gave me.
Don't take it all upon yourself.
Shit, it's cold.
Guess I'll start a fire.
Damn thing won't work.
Embers?
Nice.
Sure is cold today.
The room just isn't warming up.
Looks like the weeds are all gone.
They shouldn't spawn anymore.
Now it's just the Kagebi.
Yahagi-chan!
My child's cold!
My grandpa too!
My neighbors...
Yahagi-chan?
And then?
Seven people died.
And a lot more people got sick after
eating food cooked on Kagebi,
as if they got frostbite in their gut.
I thought I've taken your warning well.
How are things now?
The sick ones should recover with enough rest.
Everyone's become cautious now.
There are no new victims for the time being.
How about the Kagebi?
They've vanished since we killed the Hidane.
They should mostly be gone by now.
Kill the Mushi and the fire burns out, huh?
Just like the records say.
But I found a mode of life that
isn't written in the records.
When one consumes enough heat
and lives its full lifespan,
those weeds are born again from its remains.
So that's what you needed my help with.
No, I can handle that myself.
How?
I just need to go somewhere where there are no people.
I breathed in a Kagebi when we
were burning the mountain.
Human bodies can be containers.
It was inside me slowly consuming my body heat.
I felt like I was freezing the whole
time, but that's stopped now.
Instead, I've started coughing up weeds.
This must be my punishment.
The Hidane is sprouting in my gut.
And it's begun secreting poison.
I've already told everyone that I
won't be here for much longer.
I intend to leave the village and find
a place to die before I'm overtaken.
So I want to leave the village to you.
I trust you not to make such a mistake.
Can't do that.
I don't know if I could have said what
you just did if I were in your shoes.
This is a battle that you people started.
It's not ending any time soon.
You can't just end it by yourself.
I've been thinking since then.
Let me try something.
Catch a Kagebi?
Is that going to cure Yahagi?
Dunno.
Here it comes!
What are you doing?
Hidane are clever, aren't they?
Their poison must have been something
they just happened to have.
But that poison also causes man to set fires.
Once they have access to fire and they reach maturation,
they use the fire to attract people
and consume their heat.
Man, the only species to use fire, are
in turn being used by the fire.
But this fire isn't real, after all.
If you provide a larva with a false
fire, do you think it can mature?
Then...
Perhaps to terminate the weeds, we
need to burn them using Kagebi.
And food cooked on a Kagebi seems
to have the same effect.
And burn my own gut?
Yeah. I ate some too, and it hurt like it was burning.
Well?
Yahagi!
It's burnt.
Give me more!
Don't rush it.
You wouldn't last.
Cure yourself slowly.
Slowly and surely.
She continued to live expelling weeds, burning her gut,
and protecting her village from the paranormal.
There aren't many Kagebi these days, are there?
Maybe because it's getting warm.
Maybe.
But there's no telling where they're still hiding.
Don't be off guard.
It's flying towards the valley.
It's probably searching for a cold place to stay.
And there it'll lie and wait for winter to come.
The
Journey
to the
Field
of Fire
Eye of
Fortune,
Misfortune
Eye of Fortune, Eye of Misfortune.