I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
That must be it.
I covered my ears with my hands, and my
forehead swelled up and grew four horns.
If on a snowy night, you can hear no sound,
talk to someone, or close your ears.
Or your ears will be consumed.
Tender Horns
Thank you for coming.
You're the Mushi-shi... Ginko-san, was it?
Yes.
I'm Shirasawa, the village chief.
I called you here on behalf of the village.
As you can see, we live in the depths
of a vast mountain range.
It's very quiet here; the wind does not pass through.
In particular on a snowy night like
this, it becomes dead silent.
It's said that even voices often vanish.
And when that happens, some people lose their hearing.
In both of their ears?
Just one for most.
The doctors in town just shake their heads.
So I suspected that it may be something paranormal.
Ah, this mucus...
Mushi is the cause.
It's called an Un.
It's consuming all the sound.
Normally they live in the forests, but
the snow is absorbing all the sound.
So they must have come to this
village in search of sound.
Ah, there they are.
It's a big swarm.
They'd be the ones eating all the sound.
So they leave their swarms and infect animal hosts.
It looks like a snail.
They're gone.
They moved.
Did you know that there's an organ in
our ears that looks just like a snail?
A starved Un will leave its shell, infest in
that organ, and consume all sounds.
However, the organ isn't destroyed.
Um...
Is this enough hot water?
Thank you.
Pour this in your ear, and it should...
And just like that.
Hot, what is this?
It's salt.
Salt?
I can hear.
Just spread the rest of that around the attic.
I am impressed.
I've never seen a Mushi-shi at work before.
Just one more left.
There's one more, who has lost hearing in both ears.
My grandson.
His symptons aren't like the others'.
Please don't tell the others how my grandson is.
Shut up.
Be quiet.
His name is Maho.
It began last winter.
These horns grew on his head,
and he lost all ability to hear.
Instead he hears sounds that he's never heard before.
Even on a silent night like this,
he hears sounds from all over.
Whispering sounds, thundering sounds...
He'd close his ears really tight, but it's no use.
The sound's coming in from his horns, he says.
Could this be... an Ah?
Eh?
They live alongside the Un. They consume
the silence created by the Un.
Once you're infected with one, you'll
start picking up any sound you can,
and the sounds from your
surroundings are drowned out.
But they are a very rare Mushi compared to the Un.
There's only one recorded attempt at treatment.
According to that, applying salt water to the ears
didn't have the same effect as on an Un.
Many other medicines were tried,
but none were successful.
By the end of the winter following the infection,
the patient broke down from the endless torrents
of sound rushing in day and night,
and eventually died of weakness.
The winter following...
In any case, we need to know our enemy.
Can you hear me?
Yeah, the noise is a bit quieter.
It got really loud since you came.
My head was about to explode.
Ah, sorry about that.
I seem to be the type to attract Mushi.
They're loud things, aren't they?
I drove them off with this smoke.
Mushi?
This sound?
Most of it, yeah.
Humans have an exceptionally bad sense of hearing.
Other animals can distinguish
a much wider range of sound.
But it's said that there's a range of sounds
that not even animals can hear.
That's the range of the Mushi's voice.
Are the Mushi talking this loud?
Not really.
Each Mushi has a tiny voice.
But there are countless Mushi.
If all those Mushi speak one thing, what happens?
It's said that their voice bellows across the whole world.
The Ah in your ears are consuming your silence.
And then those horns of yours grow, and you
begin to hear all sorts of sounds from them.
That seems to be what's happening.
Your ears look perfectly fine.
How did those horns grow?
I had my hands over my ears.
My mom died last winter.
I remembered that Mom would do it all
the time, so I tried doing the same.
And then my forehead bulged up, and the horns grew.
She held her ears?
Why did she do that?
I don't know.
I can't remember.
Mom had the same sickness.
Holding her ears couldn't have helped at all.
Mom said something.
and held my ears tight with her weakened hands.
But when I try to recall what she said...
I know I remember what she said.
I keep trying to recall it.
But the noise keeps rushing into
my head, and I can't hear.
I see.
We're... rather unfortunate.
To have an example of the exact same symptoms,
means that there must be a key to a treatment.
My daughter's death?
It was very miserable.
She could hardly sleep, because of the sound.
She never said this in Maho's presence,
But she'd often say,
I want to sleep quietly; somewhere where
absolutely no sound can reach.
Just like you explained earlier,
the winter after the attack,
she left for the place which she wished to go.
So she was distressed by the noise until the end?
Yes.
No.
No, that's not right.
She said that day,
Mom, the noise is gone.
It's dead silent.
I can't hear anything.
I'm scared.
I long for that sound that I dreaded so much.
And shortly after, she died.
So right before her death, she lost all hearing.
Yes.
Anything else?
No, but this must be what Maho
was talking about earlier.
I thought it was strange myself.
Why did my child do that?
The silence before death.
Did the Ah anticipate its host's death and flee?
No, then she should have regained hearing.
What does it mean to hear nothing?
And what did she want to shut her ears from?
Where you headed?
Oh yeah, you can't hear.
It's...
It's okay.
I'm just going for a walk.
Don't tell Grandma.
I'm going to go crazy if I stay inside.
Mom...
I keep remembering about the time Mom died.
Fair enough.
He saw his mother pass away with the same illness.
It's snowing.
I shouldn't have let him go.
Maho,
Maho.
Ah, Ginko-san, I can't find Maho.
It's fine.
I know which way he went.
Eh?
You let him go?
I'll go find him.
It's quiet.
But it's not perfectly silent.
Listen carefully and you can even
hear the snow accumulate.
And when it's quiet around you, you
can hear your own heart beating.
But the sounds lose their destinction
when there is too much around you.
And in the extreme –
Could that be the same as sound disappearing?
I see.
I'm sorry.
I was going to go home right away.
I got caught in the snowstorm.
So I was waiting here.
But it's getting stronger...
Huh? His voice...
Hey hey,
quit fighting.
Which one of you is the Ah?
Uns are right-winding, Ahs are left-winding.
There you are.
Maho, can you lend me your hands?
The way your mother did.
Like this?
It melted.
You won't get pure silence by holding your ears.
It's not that your mother wanted to
shut her ears out from anything.
She wanted to hear what she could
hear with her hands over her ears.
Do you hear it?
I hear a tiny rumble.
That's the sound of the muscles in your hands.
In other words, Ah's weakness must be
the sound of another being's vitality.
But that sound is always there
rumbling inside of the living.
That sound must not be comfortable to the Ah.
So it tries to quell the sound.
Whether the Ah melts or the host dies,
is determined in approximately a year.
Your daughter must have come to realize that.
But by then...
she was already too weak.
Maho,
can you hear?
This is your mother's sound.
I saw a mountain erupt, a long time ago with your father.
This sound is just like the sound of the lava.
So when I'm so worried that I could
just vanish, I listen to this sound.
It melts away all my fear and pain,
the way lava melts everything.
Here, you try it too.
There's a stream of lava within you too.
Maho?
Lava...
Maho.
There's bright red lava flowing.
I'll take this as my pay.
Okay.
Is that really all you need?
It's fine.
Isn't that good, Maho?
The world's quiet, isn't it, Maho?
It'll take a while to get used to it, and you'll
crave for the world you just parted with.
But you'll forget by the time spring comes
and it gets lively around here.
I won't forget.
I was always listening to the same sound Mom was.
Sound so beautiful that it gives me chills.
Tender
Horns
The
Pillow
Pathway
The Pillow Pathway.