I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
There are countless fissures in the physical world.
Those who vanish like smoke are lost in such hollows.
Without their memories, without their souls.
A letter.
They're not coming through too well these days.
Maybe it's time I get a new one.
This isn't for me.
Aya Tozawa
Please...
Aya?
Pickers of Empty Cocoons
Aya Tozawa
Village
Wishing for...
...I'm Sorry.
Hey, Aya. What's up?
Ginko.
It's about time to change your Uro-san, right?
Yeah.
Sometimes my letters are torn.
Sometimes I get ones that aren't for me.
You're still at it, huh?
Using our old ones.
Why do you care?
You've got to stop worrying about the past.
The old man must be rolling over in his grave.
Ito-chan's still around somewhere.
But we can't bring her back.
Give it up.
All we can do is hope.
Hey, Aya-chan. This cocoon's empty.
It is. Weird.
Where'd the pupa go?
Aya, Ito. Put that back where you found it.
Don't touch empty cocoons.
Why not?
There's bad things living in them in place of the pupa.
It's the old man from the head house.
He comes a lot these days.
Come here, you two.
Ito and Aya.
Do you two remember the old man in the mountains?
The old man in the mountains?
You've met him when you were two years old.
It is our family tradition to test new
children when they are born.
Seems these two can both see the Uro-san.
I will come for one of them when they're ten.
Jiisama is an Uro-keeper in the mountains.
Jiisama: Old Man
We of the Tozawa family have done
this for many generations,
but it has been long since anyone
has been born capable.
One of you will have to go.
But your parents can't decide.
Which one is Aya, the younger daughter?
Me.
Jiisama, I'll go.
No, you can't!
It's okay.
No!
If Ito-chan's going, I'm going too.
Aya...
I suppose.
It may be hard on you two,
but it would be best for your daughters.
Jiisama will not be here for much longer.
It'd be cruel to have her alone deep in the mountains.
They'll be better off together.
Don't worry.
It's not as if you'll never see them again.
Leave the door a crack open.
You'll get sucked in if there's an Uro-san here.
I'm grateful that you came.
Sit down.
I've waited for a long time for this day to come,
but I never thought there'd be two of you.
You've been living here alone all this time?
Indeed, ever since the lady from
the past generation died.
I've only had the Mushi-shi to talk to,
when they'd come ever so often.
Their stories were the only things
I had to look forward to.
Oh, right.
I've written down piles of their stories for you to read.
Now, come.
Come in.
This cocoon's empty too.
There's more than in the mountains at home.
Do you two know what a double cocoon is?
Yep.
It's a big cocoon that two pupa make together, right?
It is. Find me one that is empty.
I need one for my work.
Normally, a cocoon is made of one string.
But a double cocoon is made by two pupa,
so they are made of two strings.
I take them apart and make them
into two cocoons again.
The "room" gets thin, and so the Uro-san
gets confused and comes out.
Aya, catch it with that.
Good, now put that in here.
One
Now it is concealed.
Nest
Two
One
The Uro-san can only travel between these two cocoons.
Jiisan, mail.
Son fallen ill, vomiting day and night, weakning day by day,
cannot even lift a spoon. Urgently requesting a Mushi-shi.
Now, whose turn was it this time?
What does it say?
It's not for me.
Sometimes it's a request for a Mushi-shi.
Sometimes it's personal mail for a Mushi-shi.
I think I'll choose this one.
Mushi-shi are wanderers.
So if I put a letter in the first cocoon,
the Uro-san will eventually take it to the second
cocoon that the Mushi-shi carries with him.
But they need to be replaced every few years.
Uro-san slowly widen the hole from within their cocoons.
Eventually they pierce into another
closed chamber or into an Uroana.
Uroana: the Hollow
Then the letters don't arrive properly.
Uro-san sounds fun.
Jiisama, I want to do the next letter.
Ito, Aya, don't underestimate the Uro-san.
Uro-san are frightening Mushi that
open fissures in existence.
There are a lot of Uro-san in this area.
They find closed chambers and spawn.
Never ever close the doors.
If you do, don't ever open them.
If you open them and there's an Uro-san inside,
you'll get sucked in when it leaves for an Uroana.
Uro-san can't be outside of closed chambers for long.
What happens if you get sucked in?
They say you'll be trapped wandering
inside the Uroana forever.
Don't worry, just do as I say and you'll be fine.
I've survived for as long as I have.
Don't close.
Don't open.
Aya-chan.
Are you done doing the laundry?
Yep.
Jiichan said we can play until sunset.
Really?
I'm going to go put this away, one second.
Aya-chan,
watch out for the shed door.
Okay.
Nice weather.
Huh?
Ito-chan?
Ito-chan, are you asleep?
Don't lift it.
Ito-chan?
It's because I turned the cloth over.
Because I didn't pin the cloth down.
Aya, it's not your fault.
Where did Ito-chan go?
How can I bring her back?
There's nothing we can do, Aya.
I'm going to bring her back.
Whatever it takes.
I was always with her.
I never even thought about what it'd be like without her.
But it's been five years since then, hasn't it?
And you still don't eat much.
It's time you start thinking about yourself a little.
How about we go into the Uroana then?
I'll go in with you.
See for yourself what it's like.
There.
When an Uro spawns inside a Koumyakusuji tree,
it causes a rejection reaction and forms into a gall.
Hold on to the chain and follow me.
Is this the Uroana?
Just one end of it.
We'll soon be in the great Uroana.
Who put this chain down?
A Mushi-shi from long ago.
This is an old pathway that the
Mushi-shi have been using.
I've heard that some people stayed for
too long and lost their memories.
I don't use it too much myself.
What's wrong, aren't you coming?
It's said that the only hole leading to the
outside is at the end of this chain.
Everything else is connected to some closed chamber
and can't be opened from inside.
There are countless such Uroanas.
It's unlikely that your sister might have even
passed through one of these Uroanas.
There's nothing you can do.
Aya, please, give up.
Close that big hole within you.
Before it's too late to come back.
Ito-chan?
It was a few years since then that something strange
was said to have happened in
a village of silkworm farmers.
A child of man, from a cocoon she appeared.
Perhaps ten years of age, she was without speech.
Someone!
Someone come, quick!
Home she returned, with the letter
in her pocket to guide her.
Pickers
of Empty
Cocoons
Clothes
That
Embrace
the Mountain
Clothes That Embrace the Mountain.