I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
When I was to be wed, I passed
through the forest to the north.
I think... it was probably then that
it had attached itself to me.
Without my noticing...
there was a small green stain upon my head wear.
It wasn't until after the ceremony that I noticed it...
I thought it was quite ominous.
The following year,
I bore my first child...
This is him, our eldest son, Watahiko.
Since these spots appeared,
he has continued to grow weaker...
and whenever I see them, I remember that stain.
lf... I am mistaken, please forgive me...
Did this child have a human shape when he was born?
No.
He was not even a beast.
Cotton Changeling
Not even three months had passed...
I never thought I would be
invited back to that house again.
Ginko!
Thank you for coming.
I read your letter. Is there still time?
Yes... Let's hurry, to the house.
I'm sorry.
I was going to... do as you told us but...
No, that's fine. Thanks for letting me know.
But, to be honest, I never thought
it would come to this so soon.
Yeah...
He has been growing disturbingly quickly lately!
Did this child have a human shape when he was born?
Aki... are you all right?
I'll explain the rest.
Yes, he was not even a beast.
He didn't even give a cry.
He was a strange green mass.
Aki!
It's getting away!
Damn it.
Before we knew it, it had slipped
below the house... and disappeared.
My wife desperately wanted a child but...
Thinking it to be impossible now,
she spent her days shut inside the house.
Then... a year later...
What's that sound?
Is it coming from beneath the house?
I wonder if someone abandoned him?
No. He is that child... our child.
He does look a lot like Aki...
He's grown to be a human since then.
I was afraid deep down.
But I decided to believe that it was so.
That child... Watahiko grew fast.
He liked to eat fresh small fish and fruits from trees,
and in a little over half a year, he grew to be the size of a three-year-old child.
However... his mind was that of an infant.
He didn't show any feelings or utter any words.
Despite that, with his face
increasingly resembling our own,
I, too, became attached.
Then, one night...
A cat? How noisy...
Shoo... shoo...
Yet another child was under our house.
Why, he looks like Watahiko in every way.
We should raise him in the same way.
I wonder if we'll have more.
Don't say scary things like that.
That premonition was proved correct.
Watahiko continued to multiply,
sprouting up every half a year.
No matter how many times I dug up
the ground beneath the house,
I could never find anything strange.
Then... from the beginning of this year,
our eldest son's health began to deteriorate.
He would sleep most of the day...
and his green eruptions would increase.
Doctors threw in the towel...
Then, I heard about people like yourself...
Unfortunately...
even we, mushi-shi, have no way to save this child.
He's reached the end of his lifespan.
There is a mushi called Watahaki.
It has a green form that looks like
cotton and floats in the air.
It enters the body of a pregnant woman
and becomes parasitic upon the ovum.
When it's born, it's in the form of slime,
and quickly escapes below the floors or into the ceiling.
After a year, it sends a hitotake in the shape of a baby to its parents...
That and the rate of his multiplying
exactly match the records of it.
However, just to be sure, would it be all right to take a look beneath your house?
No thanks, I don't need any lighting...
It's here, and it's grown quite large.
There's no mistake. It's a Watahaki.
That can't be!
There's nothing there!
Take a good look at this soil in the sunlight.
The hitotake are connected to the main body of this mushi by thread-like things.
They're nothing more than a part of the mushi to send the main body nourishment.
It cant' be...
That child will soon end his purpose, and will die.
At the moment he dies, he will cough up a lot of seeds.
Before that happens, we must kill him.
Wha...
What're you saying?!
Why do you think we called you here?
That child... please save him from
that mushi or whatever it's called.
There is no longer any "child" I can save.
Those "children" are mushi
wearing the skin of your child.
And they are the very ones who killed your child who was supposed to be born.
Please... understand.
I'm sorry.
It's... all right to hate me.
Thanks for persuading your wife.
She still won't talk to me, though...
We raised him for more than three years...
It can't be helped.
But she wants to keep the other
children with us at any cost.
I'm begging you, too.
Please leave them alone.
Until they show symptoms, they're of no harm.
In exchange... I'll be sure to kill the second eldest
and the next born before they cough up seeds...
The lifespan of a Watahaki spans
anywhere from ten to thirty years.
I cannot tell how many more years it will continue
or how many more "children" you'll have to kill.
Are you okay with that?
Yes... I promise!
You told me that you were afraid of them.
And yet you're saying you wish to raise them?
I just don't want to make my wife sad.
Aki calls the remaining four Watahiko and adores them.
If we lose all of them, I don't know what will happen.
Long ago, she married into the family of a prominent merchant from a town beyond the mountains.
There, she gave birth to the awaited heir,
but before he was even a year old,
it seems he died of something trivial.
That was why they got divorced.
Why, why must these cruel things happen to her...
Until now, it seems that "Watahaki children"
were all immediately killed as soon as it was understood what they were.
That way, they let the roots run dry.
There's no record of letting its offspring live,
since they will become dangerous later on.
We cannot say for sure that they will not pose a threat in the future.
B-but...
Then again...
they may not.
Exterminating the ones I'm not sure
of is brash and I don't like it.
I have reasons I can't continue to keep watch here,
but I will return in three months to see how things are.
If anything happens, send me a letter to that address.
Yes. I'm indebted to you.
The letter arrived before even three months had passed.
There... He came. It's him.
We're going to be killed.
It'll be all right.
Don't worry.
Hm? Watahiko?
He's coming.
Yes...
It seems my wife has consented.
We're raising something unnatural.
We must at least follow our agreement.
Aki, Ginko has arrived.
Thank you for coming.
Sure.
Ginko, this way.
Okay.
Ginko?
Ginko!
You are awake.
Owowowowow...
You should stay in bed...
Darn... I want to go home...
I really have no way to make up for this.
I'll keep her in the sleeping room until everything is over.
Yeah... please do that.
I thought... she'd understood.
It seems that the situation has changed quite a bit.
Yes.
I was going to tell you sooner,
But those children...
it's not only that their growth has speeded up.
One time, my fourth son was peeling a chestnut,
which is something I taught only to my second son.
Although my second son finally
learned it after much effort,
my fourth son might have learned it by watching...
It seemed that they were gradually getting smarter.
My, you've gotten soaked by the rain haven't you?
I'll get you a change of clothes, okay?
Daddy...
Hm?
Daddy... I'm hungry.
Aki... He... He talked!
I see! I see!
I'll get you something right away.
Then our second son began to show those symptoms.
It's still too early...
It was just recently that this happened to our eldest...
We have to do this.
This... is our duty.
Daddy, I'm afraid of dying.
Don't kill me... Save me...
I still want to live.
It's already become like a person.
Even though they're responsible for our child's death,
we can no longer...
How can this be?
It's now gained the ability to think.
No, it's always had this function.
Could it be that it sensed danger
because of the eldest son's death?
Not only that, but the information gained by one is circulated among all of them.
Each one is part of the main body and connected to the others at the base.
They all receive information for five people at once.
They learn quickly.
But... they're ''human-like things''?
No.
What lives within them... is a fungus that thinks.
We've failed.
We're going to be killed. We're going to be killed.
We have to protect the seeds.
I think there was a way...
We've forgotten. We've forgotten.
When we learned how to speak, we lost our memory of...
how to... how to protect our seeds...
How do you feel?
Yeah... well, I can somehow get up.
I see... thank goodness.
Your second son is in the back room, right?
Yes.
I'll go take care of him.
Afterwards, I'm going to remove the roots and take the remaining children with me.
I can no longer leave them with you.
Save me, don't kill me.
I don't want to die.
It's useless.
Why must you kill us?
Because you eat human children.
It's not our fault.
It's not our fault either...
But we're stronger.
That's why you are going to die without leaving seeds.
I see... well then...
It can't be helped...
Let's do it...
Are they trying to burn the house along with the roots under the house?!
I get it, could it be that you...
It was written in the scrolls that you brought.
Normally, we'd be able to do this unconsciously.
This is the only way to protect our seeds.
We win.
Ginko!
Don't come this way. Get out!
Watahiko! Where are they?!
They're the ones who set the fire!
Get out of the way!
They'll do anything for their seeds!
That's the kind of mushi they are!
They're already my children!
Aki!
Watahiko... Watahiko!
Watahiko...
The roots have completely disappeared.
When a Watahaki plunges into
a crisis, such as disasters,
it cuts its hitotake off from its roots and tries to at least let the seeds escape.
The hitotake change their form
and go into a long hibernation.
Is this... it?
I don't know when they'll be reborn...
It could be after you both pass away.
Whatever the case, until that time comes, I'll leave it with both of you.
I understand.
We'll always carry it with us...
What did you give them?
A mineral.
It was part of my livelihood's provisions.
A complete loss...
Why did you do that?
You sure are a mysterious creature.
Look who's talking.
Weren't you supposed to hibernate?
That's what all the records said you would do.
I don't care, I'm not tired.
What about you?
Why aren't you killing me now
while you have the chance?
Because the end of your life hasn't come yet.
What a mysterious creature you are...
That's enough. Go to sleep already.
Cotton
Changeling
Shrine
in the
Sea
Shrine in the Sea.