I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
The sun rises today and sets again.
A flower bloomed in the morning, falls from its stem.
The sun sets today and rises again.
Flowers bloom to fill the land,
but not the flowers of yesterday.
Yo, are we there yet?
We're almost there.
You must be a doctor, since a doctor
introduced me to you, right?
Nope, I'm a Mushi-shi.
Don't be so shocked.
From what I've been told, it sounds
like I'm the right man for the job.
Sorry, I didn't know.
There it is.
Those Who Inhale the Dew
Akoya, did you know?
There's a land across the sea. An open, beautiful land.
People live there really happily.
Let's go there sometime. I'll take you there.
So don't be so sad.
Okay.
There you go.
Hey, why are you staring at the island?
The tides are turning soon.
The currents are complicated here, and really strong.
You can only get onto the island during the high tide.
I see, doesn't look easy to get there.
Watch your head.
Are you a fisherman or something?
There are no fishermen on this island,
since there's only one day each month
when it's safe to set out to sea.
Nothing but rocks.
Yeah, there's not much soil. It's a poor island.
Everyone's just getting by,
with the "Ikigami" for hope.
Ikigami?
People, hide!
Sorry, you can't eat this.
We have to give it to the Ikigami and
have your sickness taken care of.
Now, get on my back.
You'll get better soon.
Hey, why do we have to be so sneaky?
The "Ikigami" she just mentioned
is who I want you to see.
She was just a normal human being.
Please, help her.
Everyone's being deceived.
That's her.
That's her father beside her; the family head.
She receives a "miracle" each day.
Today's the day they can "worship" her.
She's not even breathing.
Did you see that?
Huh?
You can't see it?
Now breathe in those fumes.
They shall rid your body and soul of illness.
It is the divine power of the immortal Ikigami-sama.
Now she returns to her normal self.
By dawn she wakes up as if nothing ever happened.
It's just as I heard, but that was still shocking.
It cures people's sickness, huh?
Those are all lies!
My mom died; it didn't help her.
We gave the Ikigami almost all of the harvest.
Her father's family began the Ikigami cult on this island.
It was his ancestors that first made it to this island.
Ever since then...
there have been Ikigamis in his
family for each generation.
People have slowly began gathering to this
island when they learned of the "miracle".
When one Ikigami dies, a new one appears.
In less than six months even.
It's been said that
there have been people who've been cured
of incurable diseases with the Ikigami's fumes.
I could never believe it.
But...
Akoya,
are you playing with an outsider again?
Come, I have something important for you.
It was about a month after the previous Ikigami died.
I remember that it was on the day
of the high tide, like yesterday.
And that was it.
She's become someone else, who can't even speak
or recall what happened the day before.
What that meant – I learned after a short while.
So there's been another person who's been cured.
Amazing how people can be cured
by nothing but suggestion.
Akoya was never a good daughter, but she
must be glad to have made herself useful.
I couldn't forgive them.
I had to find someone who could cure her.
I left saying I wouldn't be back.
The family head would be suspicious
of me if he found out that I'm back.
To be honest you're in trouble too.
I shouldn't have come here.
Please I can't give up.
Well, I'll lend you a hand.
Hurry up and lead me to her.
Her pulse is abnormally fast.
Her body temperature is much higher than normal.
It's almost time.
Light, please.
Excuse me.
There it is, it's a Mushi.
It gave birth and died.
What did you see?
The cause is a parasitic Mushi in her nasal passage.
But I don't know if she'll be back
to normal by removing it.
Is she the only subject?
There are a few others.
They're all being isolated at the cape over there.
They're all the same as Akoya.
They show up once in a while.
The family heads of each generation
have them live here in honor...
as devoted followers who came
close to becoming Ikigami.
Their families are rejoicing,
saying that "one of their relatives have
been released from all the suffering".
So there was nothing new to be learned.
Hey, it was a high tide on the
day she became sick, right?
Yeah.
Can you think of a place that you
can only get to on a high tide?
The cave at the end of the cape.
Somewhere around there.
Are you looking for something?
Found one!
Look, it's infected too.
There must be more.
Look around this area for me.
I found two more.
Okay, leave them there.
Nagi,
I found a remedy.
It'll be okay.
Akoya, calm down.
It'll be over in a second.
Here.
Akoya.
Nagi.
I'm so glad.
Really.
I see, why did Father...
Akoya, let's leave the island.
We have three days until the next high tide.
We have to pretend you haven't been cured.
But I like this island.
I'm sure Father would apologize too.
If I run, someone else will have to become the Ikigami.
You can tell them the truth.
So that you can stop Mushi from
being abused on this island.
Do you remember what happened on
the day you became the Ikigami?
I was called up by my father that day...
Akoya, I picked this for you.
It's pretty.
Doesn't it smell nice? Smell it.
A strong scented flower that looks like bindweed...
We saw them at the cave at the cape.
They were there blooming in the dark.
That was the cause...
Three days, huh?
Yeah.
Let's just be careful not to get caught.
Akoya, play the Ikigami until then.
What's up, can't get back on track?
I can't help but feel anxious.
When I was the Ikigami, the sun would
set, I'd shrivel up and fall asleep.
I always closed my eyes feeling so content.
But now I'm scared.
I'd wake up, and it'd be a continuation
of yesterday's existence.
My legs tremble at the long length of time ahead of me.
You were probably living by the Mushi's time.
That Mushi synchronizes its host's
internal clocks with its own.
Every species has its own longevity,
but it's said that they all live for roughly the same number of heartbeats.
Which means time is more dense
for some than it is for others.
That Mushi has a lifespan of about a day.
You were experiencing that every day.
Ah. That must be why.
Every day,
every minute...
was so breathtakingly fresh.
I couldn't think fast enough to keep up.
My heart was so full.
We should be able to go in half an hour.
Akoya.
Oh, how strange.
You should be weakening by now.
Father, I got better for some reason.
Shut up.
Nagi is back, I hear.
You know where he went, right?
Ah, today's the high tide, was it?
Bindweed in the dark... it really smells.
So this portion is the Mushi's hive.
They must have a better chance of creating
offspring when they nest here.
Ginko-san.
Ikigami-sama, where are you going?
Tell me where the cave at the cape is. Please.
Hey, she talked.
I'm sorry. I'll explain.
Please.
Help Nagi.
What are you doing here, Nagi?
You damn...
Hold it, what do you plan to do?
Leave them, they won't last long.
Men who use Mushi recklessly will slowly go mad.
You'll all eventually be ruined.
You're unfit to deal with Mushi.
I hope he has a plan in provoking them.
Now, Nagi.
Run!
After them.
Yes!
Make sure their remains will not be found.
Well then...
He had a flower.
Just like Akoya-dono said.
Outrageous.
We've lost them, but the tide's rising.
Shit...
We've got maybe a half hour left.
People!
We found them, it's Nagi!
Hey, stand back, we're gonna open the hole.
I...
killed him.
Father.
I picked this for you.
Don't be so sad.
Doesn't it smell nice?
Smell it.
Akoya!
Why?
Sorry, Nagi.
I can only live on the other side.
It's infected deeper than the first time.
We won't be able to...
It's fine.
The only time Akoya looked happy
from the bottom of her heart,
was when she was the Ikigami.
The sun rises today and sets again.
A flower bloomed in the morning, falls from its stem.
The sun sets today and rises again.
Flowers bloom to fill the land.
Not the flowers of yesterday,
but beautiful flowers still.
That day,
Ginko-san missed the high tide, so he
stayed on the island for a month.
In that time, he cured all the people on the cape.
But...
Every time the high tide came and the cave opened,
someone became an "Ikigami" again.
Some people don't appreciate being cured.
They'll eventually sniff the flower again.
Akoya said it.
I'm scared.
My legs tremble at the long length of time ahead of me.
We're practically the same.
We don't know what we've got to live for.
Just live normally.
You'll be better off if you can catch some fish.
Dig up the cave so that you can
set sail whenever you need to.
It wouldn't be easy.
But you've got an endless amount of time ahead of you.
Those
Who
Inhale the
Dew
Raindrops and Rainbows
Raindrops and Rainbows.