I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
Mushishi
I reached... for you
Hey, kid.
Are you dead?
One-Eyed Fish
You can see the Mushi, huh?
Don't be afraid.
The ones that are still exposed
to light aren't very dangerous.
Or is it me that you're afraid of?
Drink this. It'll be good for your wounds.
Get well and leave quickly. I'm
not letting you stay for long.
Mom.
Mom!
Strange, we must have come the wrong way.
What's wrong, Yoki?
Are you seeing strange things again?
Don't worry. Those are illusions.
Be strong.
Don't be afraid.
I can move a lot better now.
I wonder what type of fish that is.
Pale white with green eyes.
Each one of them has only one eye.
It's because of the Mushi in the pond.
Don't go near the pond at night or in the morning.
Those things aren't illusions, are they?
You couldn't say that they exist like we
do nor that they're only illusions.
But they do affect us.
Are they completely different from us?
They exist in a different form, but
they're completely unrelated.
They are a different manifestation of life.
Really...
I see.
I can walk without a cane now.
Yoki,
your foot is better now, isn't it?
You have a place to return to, don't you?
I don't have a place to go back to.
I traveled with my mom, selling things.
Besides, my foot still hurts when I walk.
I see.
Hey, the Mushi in the pond, what's it like? Tell me.
Sure.
Its appearance can only be described as "darkness".
Darkness?
Yeah, there are two types of darkness.
One is inside a shed; a moonless night;
or when you close your eyes.
It's the darkness that is made when you obstruct light.
Toko no Yami: eternal darkness
The other is the "Toko no Yami".
It stays in the shade during the day, but at night
it leaves the pond to eat small Mushi.
Why did your hair, your eyes and
the fish all become like that?
At dawn, the pond often shines silver.
It must be reducing consumed Mushi to light.
This seems to be the result of being
exposed to it too many times.
Wouldn't you lose your other eye then, if you stay here?
You've seen the fish in the pond, haven't you?
Strangely, there are no fish missing both eyes.
That must be the way it works.
Now, it's getting dark. Let's go inside.
What is the Mushi called?
The dark ones are called "Tokoyami".
The ones that give off light seem to be a different
type of Mushi living on the Tokoyami.
I don't know if they have a name.
Personally, I call them "Ginko".
How about this?
Can't eat it.
This one then.
Try taking a bite.
Don't swallow it.
Hot!
What the heck?
It won't kill you.
Keep it up and you'll have a strong stomach.
That's mean.
They're all lumped together.
Did you scatter them?
They'll bunch up again.
It's always like this where I go.
Hey, can I do it too?
I'm not doing it for fun.
I know.
It's a bit bitter.
Nui.
Let's light the lamp.
Ah, sorry.
I forgot, I can see well in the dark.
Because of the Ginko?
Probably. Well, it's useful.
Say, Yoki.
When you walk the paths alone at night,
sometimes the stars and the moon
lighting your way disappear,
and you become disoriented.
That's normal.
But if when that happens you can't remember
your name or your own past,
it's because a Tokoyami is close by.
It's said that you can escape if
you can somehow remember.
And if you can't remember at all?
Give yourself a name – any name
that comes to mind, they say.
You sure that works?
However, they say you won't remember anything
from when you had your past name.
Hey.
Can I ask you why you're here?
Yeah, I don't mind.
Beyond this mountain is my home village.
It's isolated, but it's a beautiful village.
I was born with a tendency to attract Mushi.
I couldn't stay in one place, so I traveled
through villages as a "Mushi-shi".
Yet, I made frequent trips home.
To meet my parents, my friends... and
most of all, my husband and my child.
But...
My husband and child were missing in the mountains
along with my father, my friends and other
villagers that went looking for them.
I ran through the mountains to find them and
eventually learned that living in this pond...
is a Tokoyami.
I've learned from other Mushi-shi what happens
when you're taken by a Tokoyami,
and what you should do.
So I stay here, in hopes that they're
still wandering somewhere.
How long have you been here?
Six years, more or less.
All alone?
Those people... I wonder if they all look like you now.
Yeah, they have to.
I'll help you look for them. Can't I?
So let me stay...
No!
Why not? Why can't I?
I want to do this alone.
That's all.
Don't make it an excuse to stay here.
Speak of it again...
and I'll throw you out immediately.
Nui's hiding something.
There must be a reason I can't be here.
Come out, Tokoyami, Ginko.
What's that fish?
It's losing its eye.
It's gone.
Yoki.
What are you doing? I told you not to go near the light.
Nui.
The reason the fish only have one eye... is because
they vanish once both of their eyes are gone.
You knew, didn't you?
They aren't vanishing.
The light that the Ginko give off
turns them into Tokoyami.
That's the same thing!
Why'd you just leave it here?
You're a Mushi-shi, aren't you? Why are
you letting such a horrible Mushi live?
Don't let yourself be blinded by fear or anger.
Everything is only as it is.
We should just use our conscience
to escape from what we can.
That is what we Mushi-shi have been
studying to do since long ago.
I kept many records of the Ginko.
And by the time I discovered the fate of the fish...
I'd already been exposed to the light too many times.
I've tried moving the one-eyed fish from the
pond to keep them away from the light.
Once it started, they eventually lost both eyes
and became the Tokoyami.
No.
Then you're...
Yet I still couldn't accept the fact that my husband
and child had become the Tokoyami.
I roamed in search, always avoiding the light.
But... some time ago, I came to
realize that everything is here.
It's too late.
Yoki, leave now, if you understand.
No!
There's got to be something we can do. Let's leave here.
Don't be a fool!
There's nothing that can be done, and
I was always content with that.
But with you here, it's been nothing but painful.
Leave. Please.
You'll be able to live your life traveling.
You're fortunate not to have a place to call home.
No!
My home is here.
I've been here the longest.
It's not. This is the place for the Tokoyami and I.
It's not your place to be.
This is how it should be, right?
The pond...
Nui!
Don't go! Don't go!
Nui?
Wait!
Don't go!
Nui!
What have you done?
Nui? It's you, isn't it?
Go back!
What about you?
I... will soon...
The Ginko are going to awaken soon.
Go as far away as you can.
Now, hurry!
Your hand has no heat.
It's neither cold nor warm.
Your hand is still warm.
Not just your hand.
I no longer have eyes but when your eyes look
this way they are as warm as the sun.
How nostalgic that was, in the darkness by the pond.
Now, Yoki, close one eye for the rest of the way.
Give the other one to the Ginko so that
you can escape from the Tokoyami.
But shut the other one tightly so that
you may see the light of day.
Oh no.
The Ginko are going to awaken.
That's the Ginko.
The eyeless fish in the pits of the Tokoyami.
Don't let yourself be blinded by fear or anger.
Everything is only as it is.
I can smell the dirt.
The moon again.
How many times has it been now?
I can't remember.
My name...
What was I supposed to do when this happens again?
The next morning,
my right eye saw the light of day.
What's up with you? I haven't seen you around.
Hey!
Yo, I'm home.
You sure you should be up? Don't strain yourself.
Yeah.
How're you doing now?
Have you remembered anything other than your name?
No.
Well that's fine. You can live here if you want.
Let's go see the village chief tomorrow, okay?
But...
My left eye was dark even under sunlight, as
if it was replaced with a scoop of darkness.
It attracted strange things.
I had the feeling that they'd bring disaster
if I continued to draw them here.
Hey, Ginko, time for breakfast.
Ginko, hey!
Where'd he go off to?
One-Eyed
Fish
One-Night
Bridge
One-Night Bridge.