I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
When all are sheltering within,
there comes an imitation of spring.
Linger in bliss for too long
and your flesh will soon be frozen.
Huh?
There's flowers.
It's a butterfly.
Pretense of Spring
Who's there?
I got caught in the snow. Do you
mind if I spend the night here?
Come in.
Huh?
Miharu?
Damn, where'd he wander off to?
Did he leave?
What's he up to?
Oh shit.
No, don't!
Miharu!
Hey, that kid...
You should teach him not to touch weird things.
But that was a rare one.
You did it again, didn't you?
You idiot!
Ow!
Excuse me,
can you see those things he's seeing too?
We call them Mushi.
There are those who fear them and those who like them.
Seems he's quite the latter.
Yes, he's always liked animals. He'd catch
them and bring them home all the time.
Three years ago, ever since he
began to see those things,
he's been doing the strangest things.
That winter, he disappeared in the mountains.
There was a blizzard for the next few days.
Let's go back.
We've done all we can.
We had lost all hope.
But...
Miharu?
He wandered back home in the spring.
Ever since, he'd run after the strange
things he insisted he saw.
Every time we were about to run out of food
for the winter, he'd just disappear.
We'd find him passed out at the outskirts of the village,
and he'd sleep all the way until spring.
And he'd always have with him
a bag of fruits and vegetables that don't
normally grow during the winter.
When I ask him where he'd been –
I don't remember.
Don't open the bag outside. It'll
be a pain if people find out.
That's all he'd ever say.
The two of us live alone, so I can understand
that he's trying to help out.
But I just can't get it off of my mind.
It just doesn't make any sense.
That might be a "Harumagai".
Harumagai?
It's said that there's a Mushi called Usobuki,
that has the appearance of a flower blooming on a tree.
It emits a special stimulating scent to animate
hibernating plants and animals.
And then it consumes the energy
of the animals that it attracts,
causing them to continue sleeping until spring.
That's all I know about them.
So what exactly are Mushi?
Not all of them are dangerous.
They're usually harmless as long
as you don't mess with them.
But that kid...
I could teach him which ones to watch out for.
Yo, Miharu.
That one over there. That one's not so safe.
Hey, listen to me!
Look, see, there's tons of them here.
Don't bring them out.
Settle down a little.
Damn it, I shouldn't have made that offer.
Oh yeah, where do you find those vegetables?
Dunno.
I'm not going to steal them from you.
Take me there, please?
You're going to tell my sister, aren't you?
I just want to investigate.
You know you've got your
sister worried, don't you?
Why don't you at least tell her where you get them?
Then she'd come after me.
I can understand you wanting to be helpful.
But don't you think you're just being selfish if
you don't think about how your sister feels?
You've got a place to go home to.
Don't stray too far.
I've seen this one.
Oh? How 'bout these ones?
Dunno them.
Miharu, you better take it seriously!
Okay.
Ginko-san, could you please continue tomorrow too?
Fine with me. I don't have any other plans.
How long can you stay then?
I wonder... it depends on the area.
Well, I think I could stay until
he learns most of the Mushi.
He's a fast learner.
Maybe ten more days.
Depends on the area?
I have a tendency to attract Mushi.
I can't stay too long in places where
there are too many Mushi.
It isn't good to have too many of them around.
Judging from the types of Mushi that Miharu
is finding, it's probably not that rich.
I could probably stay for a while.
You can stay for as long as you can then.
It's hard traveling in the winter, isn't it?
You should stay 'til spring.
Well... it'll depend on the mountain.
What's that?
A cocoon?
It was around there somewhere.
It looked like a Mushi.
Are they gathering in now?
Thought so; there's more than before.
I might have stayed for too long.
Ginko, I have some errands to run in town.
Take care of Miharu, please.
He's sleeping inside.
All right.
Take care.
Hey, Miharu.
Damn kid, wandering off again.
How far did he go?
Shit, where'd he go?
Miharu!
Maybe I should go home first.
Miharu! Hey!
Could he have...
Harumagai?
Come on, Suzu, cheer up.
It's the same as always, right?
He'll be awake by spring.
I'd like to stay until then, but I have to go.
But... Miharu's going to be sad when he wakes up.
I'm sorry.
I'll come visit again.
When all calls for an awakening,
the imitation lays to rest.
And someone in the winter mountain
pretends that it's spring.
Hey, Suzu.
Gin...
He's been asleep for a whole year?
I don't know what happened.
We'll have to find out where Miharu was going.
But you might end up like Miharu.
He was supposed to wake up by spring, right?
There's something he needs to wake up.
I should know what that is, if I go there.
If I don't come back, search for
me north of the mountain.
Miharu's footsteps went this way last year.
Shit.
Where is it?
That was in Miharu's bag...
Smells sweet.
Over there!
I'm getting dizzy.
I've got to leave quickly. "Usobuki" look
like flowers on trees, as I recall.
They all look like normal flowers.
I need some hints.
It's losing its body heat.
The air smells different.
What the?
I'm getting cold.
My hands...
won't move.
Why are those butterflies...
That's it!
Damn it...
I finally figured it out,
and I'm falling asleep.
Idiot.
Ginko, you idiot.
What am I supposed to do?
What'll wake them up?
What?
Did something...
just come out?
What's this smell?
Ah,
it's already spring.
What's that?
Ginko!
Where's Miharu?
Miharu?
Miha...
Sis?
Since then,
the flower-like thing on the roof emitted
a strong aroma for the next few days,
and changed into a familiar form.
I never thought the thing I saw
back then was an "Usobuki".
So you were using the Usobuki's metamorphosis
to signal the Harumagai...
Yeah.
If you hadn't let it out, it would have become
a butterfly by springtime and woken me up.
You should have told me earlier.
I wanted to keep it secret, because I like them the most.
They give us food during the winter,
and they look really pretty flying around in the snow.
But they're just doing their thing,
gathering food to survive.
Oh? I see you're getting the hang of it now.
Right, they're in no way your friends.
They're just an odd neighbor.
Don't get too friendly with them.
Though, you can like them if you want.
Yeah.
Hey, why don't you stop by at my place first?
No, I've stayed here too long.
I should leave as soon as I can.
My sister's gonna be sad.
Tell her I said "thanks".
Hey, you'll come again, right?
Who knows, well, not during the winter.
Why not?
People are weak during the winter too.
Phantom springs blooming on frozen mountains.
Homes illuminated along snowy paths.
Such are the allure of long stays.
Animals, insects and people alike.
Pretense
of Spring
Sunrise
Serpent
Sunrise Serpent.