I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
It'll be fine. Sensei's taking care
of my grandma right now.
See, lots of weird stuff.
Cool.
Wow, what's this?
Such a pretty inkstone.
The White Which Lives Within the Ink Stone
Sensei!
Sensei! Come, please!
Sensei! Sensei!
My kid...
Earlier tonight, she started complaining that it's cold.
Her friends next door are in the same condition.
What's this?
Her temperature's really low.
Mom, it's cold.
Give me another blanket.
One minute.
Even her breath is cold.
Sensei.
Ice?
Sensei, I'm sorry.
I went into your shed...
Did you touch anything?
I'm sorry, an inkstone.
Inkstone?
Yo, I'm here.
Hey, over here, Ginko.
I'm so glad you came.
I should have known.
I've been careful not to let the villagers
see the stuff in the shed.
How's the patient?
Weakening.
I'm giving them hot water to keep them warm, but...
This.
I bought it from a collector friend of mine.
It's a beauty, of course, but apparently
it has the fossil of a Mushi in it too.
Mushi fossil?
Is there even such a thing?
They seldom leave any remains.
Quit buying stuff that you're not even sure of.
It's a pain in the ass.
Don't forget that your passion is
of something of the paranormal.
Sorry, I just...
This isn't a fossil.
It's a living Mushi.
And what were the patients doing?
What'd you do with the inkstone?
We grinded some ink...
Is something wrong?
What's that?
It's just an inkstone.
No, it's gotta be something special.
Hey, there's water over there.
Let's try using it.
You shouldn't.
Sensei's going to get angry.
Just a little bit.
Did something cold just come out?
Yeah, I inhaled it.
It regenerates by being used, enters
the body and cools them inside out.
It's hard to identify the Mushi with
only that much to work from.
I see.
Doesn't the former owner know anything about it?
My friend says he doesn't know anything more.
The owners before that have all used it and died.
All that remains is the craftsman that made it.
It's got an inscription. We should
be able to find the crafter.
I'll give it a try.
I'm going to take this with me.
Thanks.
Yeah.
It's quite a long trip.
It should be around here somewhere.
Oh, over there, but she's not
making any more inkstones.
Why not?
Who knows.
She quit completely.
She's got no relatives but she sure was talented.
Do you need something?
Did you make this?
Yes, this is my inscription.
So what?
There are people who are suffering
because of this inkstone.
I want you to tell me everything you know.
Thank you so much for coming.
I was looking for this. For this inkstone.
For so long.
As far as I know, three people have used it.
I heard they all died within a month.
It was some time after my inkstone
craftsman father fell sick.
I had a fiancé.
He was a client of my father's inkstones.
Both he and his parents were against
me following my father's footsteps.
Tagane, no matter what?
I thought you'd understand.
Only my father and I can dig out the stones here.
I don't want to let it end.
You couldn't take on it alone.
Your workshop is getting less and less orders.
Someday I'll make one as good as my father's.
So please...
I'll come again.
I've...
got to make something that he'll approve of.
And then... I threw myself into
inkstone crafting even more.
But I couldn't make anything that I was happy with.
And one day, I dug up that stone.
Strangely I was attracted to the stone,
and carved the stone intently.
The finished inkstone was a masterpiece.
It looks good.
Now, try grinding on it.
What was that?
What's wrong?
Some cloudy thing came out of the inkstone.
Look, over there!
Where?
The texture is good too.
I'm confident that I can leave the workshop to you.
It's been a few days since I inhaled
that smoke, but I seem to be fine.
I'm the only one who saw it anyway.
If he'd just reconsider on seeing this inkstone...
All right.
Can I keep this?
I'll try to convince my parents.
Really?
Yeah. I'll send you a letter as soon as they're convinced.
But the letter I received a month later
was one that notified me of his death.
Ever since the day I gave him the inkstone
he complained that it was cold.
He became sick witih an illness that
continually reduced his body heat.
The inkstone was accused of being sinister
and was sold off to a pawn shop.
By the time I approached the shop, it was already sold,
and I had no way of knowing where it went.
I was just left with the rumors that came
from brokers and pawn shops.
"Another one died using that inkstone."
My father died shortly thereafter,
and I stopped making inkstones.
I wish I could be of help, but that's all I know.
Actually, that was quite helpful.
Thanks a lot.
What do you mean?
Sorry, I'm in a hurry.
Wait!
That inkstone... can I buy it off of you?
I want to destroy it with my own hands.
This isn't mine.
Why don't you come with me then?
Don't forget that your passion is
of something of the paranormal.
I'm sure I knew that.
Looks like it's really getting to you.
You're back.
You better have something to be running your mouth–
They'll be fine.
I'll help them.
Coal, stove...
Pot.
And, do you have a packboard?
Sure.
The Mushi in the inkstone is called a "Kumohami".
It looks like a towering cloud.
Like the name says, it consumes clouds –
the ice and water particles in the air...
and makes it rain down snow and hail.
So then from the ground it looks as
if it's hailing without any clouds.
It's weak and immobile without wind, though.
When there's long periods without clouds it shrivels
down and freezes itself into asphyxia.
The inkstone must have just solidified into
stone, over tens of thousands of years.
It was brought back to the surface as an inkstone
and over time was revived with water.
So what are we doing now?
Tagane-san, you said you passed a mountain
when you delivered the inkstone.
That must be why you weren't affected by the smoke.
We're taking the patients to the
tallest mountain in the area.
This isn't good. Give her some warm water.
Okay.
It's already getting cold.
We'll go ahead and boil some water.
Thank you.
Sensei, are we still going higher?
It's getting hard to breathe.
The kids look painful too.
Ginko.
Any time now.
Everyone, hold your breath!
Your face, you look...
It's not cold anymore.
Her body heat's returning.
It's gone now.
Thank God.
But how?
Air pressure.
That thing lives in the atmosphere where clouds do,
meaning it must be of the same weight as the clouds.
It'd get sucked up if it got close enough.
You've always lived on high ground.
The smoke you've been inhaling must
have gradually been fading away.
It must have gone away completely when you passed
over the mountain to deliver the inkstone.
Thank God.
It was a mistake to allow such a dangerous
thing be subject to curiosity.
I will take responsibility and see it destroyed.
We know how to deal with it now, so it's not a big deal.
Can you really say all the other stuff there is safe too?
That's none of your business, is it?
Come on, Ginko, say something.
To destroy the inkstone would mean to
kill the Mushi inside too, wouldn't it?
Well, I guess so.
See, the Mushi is innocent.
Besides, that inkstone is too beautiful to destroy.
Isn't it like your own child to you?
But...
It's yourself that you can't forgive, for bringing
that Mushi-bearing inkstone into the world.
Then why don't you free the Mushi from the inkstone?
Wait, this is my inkstone!
You've a good bit of the responsibility,
Adashino, for what just happened.
Face it, this is your punishment.
It's still a top notch inkstone.
Use it well.
What the?
It's hailing.
I don't see any clouds.
Where is it coming from?
It's gonna cost a fortune to fix all the roofs in the village.
I'll pay for it.
Even if it takes me my entire life.
But how?
Make inkstones again.
You'll be able to establish yourself soon enough.
I can't...
Mind if I order one off you too?
I'll even take one with Mushi in it.
Get over it, man.
I suppose.
It'll take me a while though.
Geez, when is it going to stop?
It's been a while since its last meal.
The
White
Which
Lives
Within
the
Ink
Stone
The
Sleeping
Mountain
The Sleeping Mountain.