I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
Give birth to me once more.
I want to meet you once more.
I want to see this beautiful ocean once more.
Shrine in the Sea
Who is he?
I don't really know.
He came asking about the "Rebirths".
Really?
How did he hear about it?
I come so far and find nothing.
Islanders are sure hard to deal with.
Well, I'll take my time.
What is that light over there?
They seem too bright to be Umibotaru.
Umibotaru: Sea Fireflies (Vargula Hilgendorfii)
And it's too small to be fishing lights.
I don't know either.
You can see it, huh?
Do you know much about those things?
Yeah.
Well, it's how I make a living.
Mom!
Grandpa's back. Let's have dinner.
It's that man from earlier.
Would you like to join us?
There's too many snakes to camp out.
Grandpa!
We have a guest.
Well now, that's rare.
Who is he, Mana?
That's Isana.
Ah sorry, Mio.
I don't think it'll show up anymore.
The moon's rising.
Oh yeah?
Ginko-san.
Did you come here to find out about the "Rebirths"?
Do you know anything about it?
That light always appears by that boulder.
There's a deep chasm there that we call the "Ryuuguu".
Everyone who dies there is reborn exactly the same.
Ginko-san.
Did Isana look like a normal child?
Don't tell me...
She is...
the Rebirth of my mother.
Dad!
Dad, don't!
She's still alive.
Mio, no one has ever survived this sickness.
We have to submerge her while she's
still alive or she can't come back.
No!
Forgive me...
Mio.
I'm afraid of vanishing.
I want to sleep knowing I'll be back here again.
Please.
Mom...
Mom!
Mio, it's the full moon tomorrow.
Please!
Don't you want to see Mom again?
I want to see her and so do our relatives.
Everyone's waiting for Mana to come back.
I'm sure it's been difficult for you to have
lost both your husband and mother.
But that's why it'll be even better
for you if you bear a child.
Please, Mio!
You're the only one who can.
All right.
If seeing her will make everyone happy,
I'll give birth to her.
But that child isn't Mom.
Promise me that we won't call her Mana.
One is enough.
Any one?
Yeah. If you become pregnant,
it'll become the child that was
submerged within the month.
And that's how Isana was born.
Couldn't it have been your dead husband's child?
It was two years before Isana was
born that my husband died.
I want to know what that child is.
I can't say just yet,
but she seems like a normal human being.
No doubt, she's the child that
you pained yourself to bear.
Why don't you think of her as
her grandmother's look-alike?
Mio,
what's wrong?
Can't sleep?
Here's what I do when I can't sleep.
I pretend I'm a big fish
and that I'm diving down into a deep, blue sea.
And before I know it, I'm asleep.
Mom,
what's wrong?
It's nothing.
Good night, Isana.
Don't worry.
Yup, that's right.
I'm Grandma's "Rebirth".
There's a lot of us.
Hey, over there too.
He was reborn after he almost died from a snake bite.
That lady over there too.
She was attacked by a shark right after she got married
and her husband waited over ten years to wed her again.
Everyone's living happily after being reborn.
Are you happy too?
It bothers me a little when people call me Mana.
But it's okay.
Mom doesn't call me that.
I'm happy that I was born to Mom.
I like this island and the sea too.
Nothing.
It can't be safe approaching the light at night.
I guess I'll wait for the spawning on the full moon.
So are you staying here until then?
Yeah.
Wow. Look, it's pretty.
An island where lost loved ones can be brought back.
Forever, if desired – never to part.
Then this must be utopia.
Yet...
I thought she resembled my mother
when she was a baby.
I don't know what my mother looked
like when she was a child.
But as she grows older, her face changes...
her character, even her little habits.
Everything becomes more and more
like the mother that I used to know.
I swear I'd parted with my mother.
Yet here she is looking just like
her, calling me her mother.
I gave birth to this child and raised her...
but I can't think of her as my daughter.
It's from deep inside the "Ryuuguu".
I'm certain it's a Mushi creating those grains.
I'm not sure, but here's my theory.
What I found inside the grain was the
"embryos" of various creatures –
the very fundamental form of every animal.
For those who consume it to bear children
identical to those that were submerged...
must mean that the Mushi has the ability to restore
an organism to its original embryological form.
Does that mean that...
Your child is physically identical to your mother.
She'll become even more like your mother in the future.
However, she was raised by you.
So she'll never become your mother.
You're her mother, no matter what.
You're right.
I've got to pull myself together for her sake.
Ginko!
I'll be leaving tomorrow if it's safe to set sail.
I won't know what to do if I stay here any longer.
I don't have the right to take away your happiness.
Thanks, Ginko.
I'm going to give birth to Mom if she's about to die too.
I can't imagine my mom being gone.
You should think it over for today.
It might be a typhoon.
Well, shoot.
It's raining pretty bad.
You have trouble sleeping sometimes too, huh?
Of course. But I know a good trick.
If you can't sleep,
try pretending that you're a big
fish diving deep into the sea.
You go past the corals, beyond the suckerfish...
Go deep, deep into the sea.
That'll make you really...
Mom?
Sorry,
I'm a bit thirsty.
I'm fine. Just stay here.
I have to pull myself together.
It's going to get washed away out here.
Mio!
Hey! Mio!
I can't find my boat!
No. She couldn't have...
Hey, over there!
Over there!
Wait, Isana!
Don't go near that light. You'll be eaten!
Don't rush off like that.
We're going to go carefully.
Mom, over here!
They're surrounding the boat.
What should we do?
Isana!
Don't come!
Please!
Wait! Isana!
Are you okay?
Isana, how about you?
I'm okay.
Get up, quick!
Shit...
I'm really hopeless.
Is it going to consume and restore me to an embryo?
To the point before everything begins?
Ah, that's not a nice thought.
I'm being pulled away.
Get on, hurry!
The storm's settled.
Why did it suddenly...
Right...
The moon.
I've only learned a little bit about the Mushi.
It attracts prey with its light, consumes them,
and then restores them back to their basic form.
You could call it a Mushi that "consumes
the days of its prey's life".
In any case, you know about it quite well.
I'm sure you can sort out all your problems over time.
Yes.
Oh yeah, Isama. You weren't thinking when
you jumped in there, were you?
I almost got a heart attack, seriously.
Sorry.
Even though you could have met your
mom again if you gave birth to her.
Yeah,
but then it would've eaten all the
time that Mom lived, right?
That's too sad.
If she's going to have everything
in her life taken away from her,
I'd rather she died while she's still Mom.
You're just like Mom.
You sure are my kid.
I assume there'll be more "Rebirths" at the island.
To comfort the dying.
To fill in the gaps for their survivors.
To die without wishing for such
may be a priceless joy.
Shrine
in the
Sea
The
Sound of
Rust
The Sound of Rust.