I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
I thought I heard a sullen, unusual
sound ring through the cold air.
Am I hearing things?
No.
Again. Over there.
Someone's voice?
Rust?
What is this?
The voice stopped.
The Sound of Rust
So how long has this sickness affected the town?
It's been fourteen years now.
Everyone looks fine but their skin
becomes dreadfully hard,
and they become unable to move their limbs.
My long-time friends have the worst case.
They can't even sit up.
Where are these friends of yours?
The couple at the west end of town.
The townspeople all say that their daughter
is the cause of the sickness.
Her name is Shige.
Ever since she was born, the people
around her became sick, they say.
That is the truth, but...
We've tried for fourteen years to find the cause.
Shige eventually stopped speaking
and now everyone is nothing but suspicious.
Here, that's all for this month.
Damn Chief.
Giving her so much pity just because
her parents are close friends.
He should give us all a raise instead.
Oh dear, that's a big hole.
Sorry, I don't have any more.
Shige.
Here, use this.
The people here never get sick of it, do they?
Why don't you say something to them?
That rumor is just crap, isn't it?
Even if it were true,
it's not like you got your friends
and family sick on purpose.
My village too.
I lost half of my friends and family
after the storm a couple of years ago.
So I decided I'd stay here and make
money in my dad's place.
You decided you've got no other choice too, didn't you?
I think you're doing good.
Hey.
Can I ask you about that girl?
Are you another doc the Boss hired?
I don't know anything. She won't say a word.
Tetsu! Get back to work!
Yes, sir!
I see.
Welcome home.
Thanks, dear.
Shige, right?
You see the "rust", don't you?
My name's Ginko. I was called here to treat the sickness.
I'm not going to hound you.
We can cure the sickness.
Tell me about it.
There we go.
You can talk in here.
I don't want to rust myself.
See, it's fine.
You can see the rust too?
Yeah.
Her voice...
My voice is terrifying.
I want to lose it.
was nothing you'd expect from her small body.
A deep, cracked voice.
My voice became like this after
I kept screaming in that cave.
But with a bittersweet ring.
But it doesn't matter how much my voice changes.
It still makes rust.
It was a mind boggling voice.
Shige!
Dad, welcome home.
Yeah.
Who's that doll?
She's my sister.
Yeah? Awesome.
Whenever I spoke, rust grew on everything
and everyone around me.
That was normal to me.
Hey, Shige, sing a song for us.
I'd even sing my favorite songs
for everyone unsuspectingly.
But no one else saw it.
I only realized that it was a bad thing when I was four –
everyone started becoming crippled.
I told my parents about it.
Shige, don't tell anyone what you just told us.
We'll have no place here if you do.
We can't work anymore.
We're only getting by because
the village chief is kind to us.
Let's live.
Live by cheating on everyone. Buying pity from everyone.
Until some day we can pay them back,
don't ever speak, Shige.
I haven't said a word to anyone since then.
It's been ten years since I've spoken to anyone.
It's not their fault that everyone hates me.
I chose to survive with my parents.
I see.
The more I hear, the stranger it gets.
How can you make such a voice?
It's mixed with the sound of a pitch
that no human could produce.
It might sound a bit different to yourself,
but there's a sound that bears a close
resemblance to your voice.
This isn't rust.
It's a Mushi called "Yasabi", and it's alive.
Mushi?
Some can see it, some can't.
It's a being of a different existence.
Yasabi are normally harmless creatures
that decompose dead things.
And when they do, they emit a sound.
Your voice is like that sound,
a few hundred times louder.
When you speak, Yasabi from all throughout
the mountains gather expecting food.
But, there's nothing to eat.
That's probably why they're attaching
to the living as well.
If that's the case, we just need to scatter them.
We can?
And then we may be able to get your voice back.
It's all over the place.
Not exactly a picky eater.
The whole place is rust colored.
Hey.
What's up? It's cold here.
Nothing.
Say, aren't you afraid of Shige?
It's only been two years since I came to this town.
I just don't get the feeling that Shige
is the cause of the sickness.
Later.
Yeah.
Is that why there isn't a single Yasabi on him?
It's the ocean.
Could it be...
I knew it.
If my voice comes back and I can speak again,
I can say thank you to Tetsu-san.
I can say it with my own voice.
Yeah.
We'll use your voice to rid the Mushi.
But you won't be safe living here after that.
Okay.
You can fix the sickness, right?
I'll do anything.
But...
There's one thing I want to ask of you.
Teach me how to write.
Hey.
Oh, a facecloth.
Thanks.
Hey.
What?
You found the cause?
What about Shige?
Yeah, that was all just a rumor.
Maybe it's like this?
Here, I'll read it for you.
Give it back!
"You'll get sick if I spoke to you.
I'm sorry for everything. Thank you."
Tetsu, who wrote this?
Shige?
No, give it back!
Nope, you seemed to have sympathy for her.
Of course it's her.
I'm telling the Chief.
No!
Why'd you do that, Tetsu?
Thank you and goodbye.
Tetsu!
Forget about him!
Hurry up and clean the furnace.
That Shige. She's not getting away with this.
Shige!
Run somewhere, Shige.
Everyone's coming here.
There's no telling what they'll do.
No.
Ginko-san hasn't told me how to rid the Mushi yet.
Shige.
Get out of here for now.
Wait over at that mountain pass.
I'll persuade everyone and then
tell you how to rid the Mushi.
I'll go too.
I can't stay in this town either.
That pass is in the same direction as my home village.
She can't be safe alo–
I'm counting on you.
You can do it, right, Shige?
Ginko-san! Why are you defending Shige?
Bring Shige out!
Make her pay!
Banishing her won't cure the sickness. It's not her fault.
Shige was a normal girl.
She spoke, laughed and sung like any other.
Her voice just happened to have the
stuff to bring about the sickness.
We don't give a damn.
I'm saying, how is she supposed to apologize
to everyone who got sick?
She's been apologizing for the past ten years.
If she broke her pledge and spoke some bluffs,
no one would have been suspicious of her.
She's been paying for her crime the whole time.
That doesn't mean we can forgive her.
My child is her age, and she can't even walk.
Mine too.
Of course, she will have to pay.
If it was her voice that brought the sickness,
it's her voice that can get rid of it.
Isn't that enough to call it even?
Everyone affected by the sickness
suffered just the same.
Shige, that letter.
It sounded like you were leaving the village.
Are you going to do that once the sickness is gone?
Do you have anywhere to go?
Why don't you come to my town then?
We've lost most of the houses and
ships, but it's still a fishing village.
We're all chipping in to rebuild it.
It'll be fine. All right?
Shige!
She's not here.
Did something happen?
I have to call for help.
My voice...
If I scream from this distance...
...we can cure the sickness.
Shige!
Tetsu!
Her unmistakable voice echoed
throughout the mountains.
My legs feel lighter.
Mine too.
Shige! Are you okay?
Where's Tetsu?
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
I got Tetsu-san sick too.
He's fine. He just lost consciousness.
He can't get sick.
Shige!
You're okay?
Look, my legs!
So you ended up doing pretty much just what
I was going to tell you to do anyway.
Echo your voice across the neighboring mountains
and scatter all the Yasabi that gathered in the village.
Except it had to be there at that pass,
where the sea was right behind it.
That's because Yasabi don't like saltiness.
The rust at the edge of the village where the
sea breeze passed through wasn't Yasabi.
That was just normal rust.
Tetsu never got sick probably because he was
raised by the sea, and he went home often.
You, too, can live a normal life by the sea.
But you only scattered a small portion of the Mushi.
You'll have to keep it up for several years to come.
Though, you might really lose your voice first.
That's fine.
I vaguely remember –
the village before there wasn't much rust.
I loved this village back then.
If I can bring back the old village even just a little...
And ever since the girl left the village,
the sickness slowly ceased.
Shige.
The pass?
Yeah.
I'll come with you.
But even now, the villagers say
they can hear the broken but strangely
beautiful, familiar singing
echo throughout the mountains.
The
Sound of
Rust
The
Journey
to the
Field
of Fire
The Journey to the Field of Fire.