I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
An odd man approached me while
I was resting in the bamboo forest.
Excuse me, are you a traveler?
Yeah, I am.
You must be leaving the mountain then.
Yeah, I'm headed west.
That's great.
Do you mind if I walk with you?
Are you lost?
Yeah. I just can't get out of the forest.
You must have a really bad sense of direction.
It's been troubling me.
It's been three years since anyone came by.
Three years?
Yeah. I know it's weird, but I haven't been
able to leave here the whole time.
Inside the Cage
I'm from the village at the base of the mountain.
Oh, you're a local then.
It's not like you can't see the sun.
I don't see how you could get lost.
I don't understand either.
Wow, this is a huge forest.
Shit. We're back here again.
What the hell's happening? My compass isn't broken.
We were headed west at first.
But we gradually wandered off track...
and ended up doing a full lap.
Exactly. You can't go where you want.
What the hell?
You must've been caught too.
You wanna live here with us for now?
No way, damn it.
There's others here, too?
Yeah, there was a family that was living here.
Kisuke.
The mother's not alive anymore,
but her daughter is my wife now.
We've known each other since we
were little. I guess it's not all bad.
Yeah?
He's a traveler. We were just chatting.
She's my wife, Setsu.
Sorry to make you put up with this, Ginko-san.
I'm going to go home now.
You wanna rest with us?
No, I'm going to see if I can figure something out.
All right.
Well then, take care.
"Take care"?
Rather odd.
I made it out.
That sucked.
Need something?
No, you came out of the forest, did you?
Yeah.
Did you see a man inside?
Yeah, is he being teased or something?
What's wrong with him?
He's been possessed by a monster.
You're lucky you're safe.
A monster?
There's a white bamboo tree growing...
Stop that!
You're ruining the village's reputation.
Ginko-san.
You couldn't get out?
No, I just came back because I wanted to see something.
I heard in the village there's
a white bamboo tree here.
And I'm a bit curious about you and your wife.
What do you intend to do when you see it?
If it happens to be in my area of expertise,
I'd want to hear more about it.
It's a really rare phenomenon.
I might even be able to find a way to get you out of here.
Unless you don't want me to
barge in; then I'll do it alone.
This way.
There's four more aside from this one.
Yeah, it's a "Magaridake".
First, can you tell me everything that happened here?
This is a story that the kids in
my village were raised with.
A young couple lived in the bamboo forest here.
They've been trying for years to have children,
and the husband often left home.
The wife was a strange woman
who would talk to the plants.
At night she would wander through the forest.
Then there was a time when she said she was pregnant.
Suspicious, her husband followed her.
And...
He found her vacantly clinging
onto a white bamboo tree.
He ran away frightened, but he was berated
by the villagers, and returned home.
There he found his wife embracing a bamboo
sprout as if it were her baby.
She gave birth to a bamboo sprout?
That's what he said, apparently.
She wasn't just trying to irritate her husband?
He ran from the village in the end, so we thought so too.
In reality, when we saw the "bamboo child",
she just looked like any other girl.
That was Setsu.
Her mother was gone by then,
so me, my sister and my friends often
played here to keep her company.
We did think Setsu was unusual, though.
She'd only drink water, and she'd never leave the forest.
But we all liked her.
At some point, we were trapped in the forest.
We wandered around, and eventually,
one by one, the others disappeared.
All of a sudden, I was alone.
Everyone came looking for me the day after,
but they just couldn't leave when I was with them.
You knew I was going to get trapped, didn't you?
Sorry. I was curious if outsiders might get trapped too.
I lived at Setsu's place ever since.
I had no relatives other than my sister.
The villagers all helped us out with food and such.
My sister and I were pretty much raised by the villagers.
We were all like family. It was a nice village.
But the longer we lived like that,
the less people came to visit.
Kisuke, are you lonely?
No.
That's good.
In time, Setsu became pregnant.
But...
That's when I first realized...
what Setsu really was.
The midwife ran back to the village,
and no one's come here since.
I know it's hard to believe.
Well, I'm surprised.
So what's this "Magaridake" you speak of?
Contrary to its name, it's not a plant.
A bamboo forest shares a single root.
All together they make up a whole.
Or, you can say they're different members of the same family.
Magaridake are "Mushi" that infect the roots
and play on as members of the family.
They consume nutrients from the root,
but they also return chemicals that
cause the bamboo to grow.
They expand the forest and create new stocks.
Your wife is half Mushi, half human.
We Mushi-shi call such a person an "Oniko".
They are rare "hybrids".
It's bothering you, isn't it?
No.
I've already seen our daughter be born.
No matter what her mother was, Setsu is herself.
The villagers don't seem to think so, but I
think they'd understand if they met her.
We might be able to live in the village, the three of us.
So that's why you're trying to get out of the forest.
Yeah.
Besides, I'm worried about my sister.
She might be having a hard time because of me.
I've got an idea.
Connecting all the points where
we change direction unwillingly,
it forms a near-perfect circle.
You can't go where you want.
The center of the circle is that tree.
Is that your "Water of life"?
Yes.
Could I have some?
I'm sorry, my mother told me
not to share it with anyone.
Not even with Kisuke?
I did give it to him once.
Back when we were children.
Hey, does it bother you that the villagers hate you?
It does.
But I'm happy so long as I have
Kisuke and our daughter.
I sympathize with Kisuke because he can't get out.
But I'm glad for it.
Forgive me for doing this.
I knew it, I can't get out.
This is a problem.
The leaves are gonna fall this year too.
Your bamboo mommy's giving you leaf
meals so that you can grow big.
Which one is Mommy?
Every one of them.
Everyone is raising their children.
Daddy remembers the village
around this time of the year.
It's open, and so bright.
It's a lively village.
I wish I could show it to you too.
It'll be okay, won't it?
Kisuke will be fine.
So you know what the cause is?
Yeah.
Mushi, unlike plants, have consciousness.
They command the various parts of
their body to carry out their will.
The body for this Mushi is the whole
forest surrounding this one tree.
And it's this water that Setsu drinks
that passes on the will.
Normal water doesn't respond to the tree.
Just holding this water makes you
affected by the Mushi's will.
Of course, anyone who drinks the water,
and anyone near such a person are affected as well.
It's hot today.
I'm getting thirsty.
I'll give you a sip.
I don't think Setsu would have known.
Yeah.
But then what should we do?
We probably have to get the water out of your body,
but honestly, I can't think of a way to do it.
There's one more way...
But I wouldn't want to do it.
There's no telling what kind of
adverse effect it might cause.
I... see.
I see.
Then I can finally give up.
You...
held Kisuke back for me.
Thank you.
I'm sorry.
Why?
You wouldn't be able to do it.
You're its progeny.
You're part of its body.
Just like your arms and legs can't deny your mind's will.
Were you listening the whole time?
Kisuke... it's my fault.
But Kisuke wasn't misfortunate.
Kisuke brought me happiness despite what I am.
Yet I stole his village from him.
He even told me,
"Whatever my mother is, I'm me."
Stop!
Setsu!
Where'd she go?
It's the village!
Hey, it's me, Kisuke!
I finally got out!
Brother?
Yeah, how have you been?
Is that the kid?
Yeah.
Go back!
Listen to me!
Don't bring that thing here!
I have a child too.
Don't make my child miserable.
Hey, where's Mommy?
Yeah.
Let's go back.
They lived happily for some time after.
But half a year later,
when I went to see the effect of having
cut down the mother stock...
Not a single Magaridake.
It's you.
All the white trees wilted away one after another.
They lived on that water.
They were in pain.
By the time I buried them here,
they crumbled like dead trees.
Setsu shouldn't have done it.
It was Setsu's mother.
I made her do it.
Because I couldn't give up on the village.
It's that time of the year again, huh?
A white tree. Since when?
Babies' voices.
It's coming from their graves.
Inside
the Cage
Pretense
of Spring
Pretense of Spring.