I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
The rain is stopping.
It's close.
Don't go.
Please don't go.
Please stay there.
Raindrops and Rainbows
Mind if I join?
Sure.
This is bad.
Yeah.
You can hardly see what's up ahead.
When's it going to stop raining?
It'll be at least half an hour.
Are you a tradesman?
Can you sell me food?
The rain ruined all of mine.
Nope, this barrel's empty, and I'm not a tradesman.
Huh?
What are you putting in there then? That's a huge barrel.
A corpse, man, a corpse.
A rainbow.
I'm traveling to take a rainbow home with me.
Oh?
That's nice.
Tell us about it, tell us why.
I just happen to be bored.
Yeah, sure.
Back when I was a kid...
Honey!
Kenrou, grab Dad!
Not again Pops, cut it out!
Here comes the rain.
Here comes the rainbow.
Honey! Honey!
For as long as I could remember, my dad would
change when he felt the rain coming.
He'd run around the mountains in joy,
and he wouldn't come back for days.
He was troublesome.
Days later he'd be found stuck in mud,
or he'd have come home by himself.
And on days that it wouldn't rain,
he'd chug down tons of water.
It's so embarrassing.
You might as well not come home.
I don't know what's happened to me either.
Ever since I've seen that rainbow.
There is no such rainbow! You've gone crazy!
Hey Pops,
is it fun running around in the rain?
Yeah, it's too fun to describe.
I'm doing it too then.
You can't. Mom will throw a fit.
Well then, tell me about the rainbow again.
All right.
But don't tell Mom.
That day...
It was the day before you were born,
right after the flood finally settled.
Damn.
We spent so much effort on it.
It couldn't be helped.
Guess we need to think it over some more.
But that's about as tough a bridge as we can make.
A rainbow.
It's rather clear.
I took a closer look.
It was rooted in the riverbed.
They say there's treasure at the end of the rainbow...
Ever since then, the rainbow would
always show itself after any rainfall.
It would entertain my dad with different
shapes each time he saw it,
but to everyone else it was invisible.
I was the only one that seemed to notice it.
One day it showed up at a distance,
and I haven't seen it since.
My throat's been dry since then
no matter how much I drink.
My body gets tingly at times when it's about to rain.
By the time I come to, I'm running
around all over the place.
I long for the rainbow so much
when I'm normal like now.
I want it... I just can't help but want it.
I want to go look for it sometime.
But...
my father became ill and spent his time in bed.
Yet he'd try to run wild when it was about to rain.
Eventually he became too weak to stand.
Dad, water.
I want to see the rainbow.
So here I am traveling, trying to find the rainbow for him.
And you're going to nab that rainbow
with your two hands, are you?
I won't know 'til I see it for myself.
True enough.
Oh, the rain's settling down.
Guess I'll get going.
Your story was a bit loose at the end.
Later.
Well then, I'm leaving too.
Hey, wait up.
You should go that way if you're looking for the rainbow.
You didn't just make that story up, did you?
What your dad saw is a Mushi called Kouda.
I've only seen it once before,
but I never got a chance to see it at the root.
So I'll tag along if you don't mind.
You can pay me in food.
That barrel of yours... just sell it.
I doubt it'll be useful.
So, are we going?
First off,
you can only see a normal rainbow when
you're facing away from the sun.
But Kouda can appear anywhere regardless.
That, and the colors are backwards.
You'll be wasting your time running around
unless you keep that in mind.
Hey, Ginko, was it?
There's a reason you're traveling too, isn't there?
Why are you helping out a stranger like me?
Like I said, I just want to see it too.
I don't have a specific reason to be traveling.
But I guess I can't be chasing a Kouda around forever.
I'll say...
I'll give up if we can't find it by the first day of spring.
That's fine with you, right?
Apparently  they're like normal rainbows
in that they appear after rainfall.
We've gotta anticipate where it's gonna rain.
I've gotten pretty savvy at that.
It doesn't look like it'll rain here for a while.
That mountain over there has a "hat".
It's going to rain there tomorrow.
It's not like I've been wandering around blindly.
There!
No, that's just a rainbow.
That's not it either.
I did expect it, but it's going to be hard to find it.
How long have you been traveling for?
It's been five years.
Five years...
Yo, that story of yours.
About wanting to show it to your ill dad.
You lied, didn't you?
It's hard to believe you'd leave your family
with an ill man for five years to travel.
It's true that I want to show it to my dad.
But that might not have been why I started doing this.
I haven't told you my name, have I?
Nope.
Kourou is the name.
It's a name that traps me to the shame
of my father's rainbow chasing fits.
I was the laughingstock of the village because of it.
There's a river in the country up north,
famous for its turbulent waters.
I'm from a family of engineers that've been
building bridges across it for generations.
As many times as we'd build bridges, they'd
get destroyed during the high tides.
Everyone had high hopes for my dad.
My older brother took his place with his brilliance.
He'd design a sturdier bridge each time it broke.
I didn't have a speck of the talent that he had.
I lost coordination in my left hand
ever since I cut a tendon.
I'm useless even as a carpenter.
Before I knew it, I had no place
in the village except by my dad.
I couldn't bear it, so I ran off.
So then why is it that you're looking for the rainbow?
I couldn't help but go after it every time I saw one.
Don't go.
For one I wanted to see if what my dad said was true,
and I wanted to prove to the people in town
that it was all because of the rainbow.
But it doesn't matter where I go, I'm still a failure.
I can't even stay alive without a reason.
A reason, huh?
You said you're traveling without a reason.
Well, you must have a reason though.
Traveling isn't easy.
You couldn't go on traveling without reason.
Yeah, sometimes I want to take a break.
Then I just make a reason, like now.
That way breaks just come naturally.
You don't have "breaks" when you're just "staying alive".
I'm taking all this seriously, and you think it's a vacation.
I'm taking it seriously too, aren't I?
I'm talking about your attitude.
The hell is that?
Taking a break is important to living.
Besides, I think it's a better motive than what you have.
You're just condemning yourself to chasing
a rainbow so you can drown out your guilt.
Pathetic.
You should have just settled down somewhere
and forgotten your past.
I know.
I'm here now because I couldn't do that.
But maybe it's time I quit.
Maybe I'll quit when spring comes.
Hey, wait up.
Hey.
Oh, you've got good eyes, sir.
Those are a mermaid's nails. Mix them
in water and you'll have a love potion.
I'll make it cheap.
Isn't there anything to make it rain?
I wish.
All these back to back sunny
days are drying up the crops.
I'd have used it myself if there were such a thing.
Yo,
keep watch on the sky.
It's about time it rains.
I'm thirsty.
I can't even sweat anymore.
Here comes the rain.
Here comes the rain, here comes the rain.
Here comes the rainbow.
Ginko!
Look over there.
The sun's under the rainbow.
Hey, wait. The love potion...
Sorry man, it's closing time.
Hey, don't rush off so fast.
Damn it.
Where'd it go?
It's around here somewhere.
It still looks like it's going to rain.
It might not have gone too far.
Let's wait here for today.
I knew where it was going to rain without even looking.
Was it like this for Dad too?
Kourou,
you must be getting to despise me
and the name I gave you by now.
I wanted to give you the name of the
most beautiful thing in the world.
I'm sorry.
You get laughed at by your friends because of it, right?
Take this.
I thought of a better name for you.
Call yourself by it from tomorrow on.
No.
Don't say that.
I'm not going to give in.
I'm going to become an even better engineer than you.
Hey, wake up.
It's raining.
There.
Hurry, it's close.
Amazing.
...the name of the most beautiful thing in the world.
It's beautiful.
Stop!
Dad wasn't lying.
I gotta take this home.
Idiot.
Are you all right?
Yeah.
I wasn't sure until now, but it's tingling on my skin.
It's a type of Nagaremono.
Nagaremono?
Even though it has life,
it's a thing close to being a natural phenomenon.
Other than having life, it's the same as the "rainbow"
phenomenon caused by light and rain.
The Kouda must have been created
by light and rain containing Kouki.
Kouki?
It's the origin of Mushi's life.
Nagaremono are like floods and typhoons.
There's a reason that they're created,
but they bear no purpose.
They arise just to flow.
Interrupted by nothing, they leave
only their influence, and are gone.
You'll be infected when you touch such a Mushi.
For an instant, I felt like I was inside of it.
I wonder if Dad was engulfed by that rising stream?
I guess I don't have any power over it.
I feel like there's a hole in me.
It's almost refreshing.
What are you doing next?
Dunno, I'll think it over.
You?
Just like this guy, huh?
Just flowing away somewhere.
I have no idea what happened to the man since.
But I was told that an indestructible bridge
was built on the violent river of the north.
They'd detach one pillar form each bridge
piece and let each flow freely.
And when the water settles, they'd reconnect them.
It's been given the name "Nagarebashi"
after one man's invention.
Raindrops and Rainbows
Where
Sea
Meets
Man
Where Sea Meets Man.