I walk ten thousand miles,
Ten thousand miles to see you
And every gasp of breath I grabbed at just to find you
I climbed up every hill to get to you,
I wandered ancient lands to hold just you
And every single step of the way,
And every single step of the way, I pay
Every single night and day,
I searched for you
Through sandstorms and hazy dawns,
I reached...
I reached... for you
Mushishi
Many amusing things wash up on the beach.
Plants and sea shells from the
south. Giant deep-sea fish.
Sometimes even people.
Or even empty ships.
Where Sea Meets Man
Let's go over there.
Hey there,
I heard there's a transport from here to across the bay.
Am I wrong?
Everyone's probably out fishing.
Ah, okay.
I should just wait 'til lunch then, I presume.
What are you doing here?
I'm waiting too.
I lost my wife under strange circumstances on this shore.
Well, I guess you wouldn't want to hear about it.
No, I would.
Oh yeah?
All right then.
It was around two and a half years ago.
It stinks like fish.
I never thought you were born so
far out in the middle of nowhere.
Come on, let's go home.
Shut up damn it, what "home"?
Let's just beg Dad.
It's not right that you got fired.
It's no use.
Why?
The shop was already about to go out of business.
They were just looking for an excuse to get rid of me.
Then why does it have to be you?
They were going to have you follow in their footsteps.
They were quite pissed at me for being engaged to you.
They must have been told a lot of crap.
I doubt they thought you'd follow me out so far.
Honestly, I didn't think you would either.
What's that supposed to mean?
You aren't the eldest daughter. You
must have had some plans too.
You can go home if you want. This
isn't the right place for you.
Aren't you getting on, ma'am?
Michihi.
I'll tell her I'm sorry when we get there.
Sea snakes?
It's getting foggy all of a sudden.
No big deal, we can still see the shore.
Hey, where are you going?
That's the coast over there.
I don't know, I can't steer.
Forget the ship, come over here.
Michihi, you too.
I can't. There are snakes.
Where?
Don't mind them, just come here.
Hurry!
Here? Where?
Where are you?
Michihi! Michihi!
Follow them, quick. Please!
The boat overturned...
...and I ended up here.
We never found any debris of
the boat that my wife was on.
Perhaps because of the tides in the area, things
from offshore arrive on the beach all at once.
If my wife's boat tipped over too, some of
the cargo should have shown up here.
Supposing she floated offshore, she's probably not alive.
But I just can't move on until I find some proof.
Snakes...
Nothing.
And now you've been waiting for two and a half years?
On the bright side,
whether there's any evidence or not,
she's not alive anymore, right?
In the off-chance that she survived,
she must be living a new life now.
Shouldn't you start worrying about yourself now too?
Sorry to be rude.
Well, see you later.
Fog...
Snakes...
Sounds familiar...
Here you go, as always.
Thank you again.
Are you going to trade that in town?
Yeah, why?
For that price, huh?
You're taking too much of a cut because
she doesn't know the market price.
You can ask for twice as much, you know.
You speak as if you know something.
I've been working for a wholesale dealer for a while.
It's because of you middlemen that
the fishermen here are poor.
This should do it, even with the handling fee.
That'd take it all the way to the next town.
Fine then, how's this?
Well...
That's as far as I can go.
You can ask for that much from now on.
Really?
I can have this much?
Thanks for helping.
You can tell everyone else the same.
Thank you.
I'm sorry, I always thought you were a weird guy.
Yeah, we got a good deal today.
Thank you.
This isn't much, but have it please.
You know, you should leave your
lodging and come live next to us.
You should live here.
That'd be great. Don't you think?
Hey!
Shark!
There's a shark in the water!
What, where?
I don't see anything.
What's the matter, Shiro? You sure scared us.
Was yesterday the high tide?
No.
I wonder, the tide's so high.
He's not here.
Hey, that man who was here waiting
for his wife... is he gone now?
He's living with us here now.
I don't know who you are, but leave him alone, please.
What's wrong?
Nothing.
What do you mean, "nothing"?
I'm just scared.
You've been saying weird things,
and the tide keeps rising.
So many strange things.
You still gaze off into the sea sometimes.
So I wonder if you might just wander off into the tide.
Oh come on.
I'm not going anywhere.
This is just like last time, when the tide rose so high.
About three years ago, was it?
Yeah, it was foggy just like it is now.
We shouldn't go out to fish until it's over.
I heard some boats don't come back
when they go out into the fog.
And then about three years later
their boats come back empty.
Empty boats...
come back.
There are no waves.
It couldn't get back to shore even if it did come back.
Is it still bothering you?
You again.
I was thinking about that story you
told me. I did some research on it.
According to that, it should return soon.
That swarm of snakes you mentioned...
No one else saw it, right?
Yeah.
Thought so.
Those must have been Mushi.
You've heard of the phrase "a thousand in the sea,
a thousand in the mountains", haven't you?
That a snake living in the sea
for a thousand years and in the mountains for a thousand years will become a dragon.
This Mushi holds something in common with that.
Well, not that there's any way to
know how long they've lived for.
The ones that emit a fog-like mist
and live in swarms in the ocean,
and the ones that live quietly deep in the mountains.
Both look no different from a snake.
When the time comes,
the ones in the mountains come down, and the
ones in the ocean come up to a nearby sea.
They gather at a single spot on the shore, and a
thousand days later, they merge into a single Mushi.
So then... that same thing from
the swarm must be back here.
I've got to go out to sea.
Wait.
I'll be fine.
That fog...
I couldn't see anything from outside,
yet I could see clearly from inside.
Have you ever wondered why only your
wife got consumed by the fog?
Only those who have the desire to return
to land can see or return to shore.
Last time I saw you,
you looked as if you would have had no reason
to live even if you did find your wife's remains.
That's not true anymore.
Looks like it.
Well, that's that.
So if you'll keep that in mind, I'll go with you to spectate.
You're prepared, right?
Yeah.
It's true.
You can see the shore so well that it's almost bizarre.
Don't tell me you can't see it.
I can.
It's here.
There's so many...
Over there.
That's the boat!
Looks like the body's there too.
I'll be fine.
Pull up next to it.
Dear?
Michihi?
You're okay?
What's going on?
I almost gave up.
You're late.
You left me for so many days.
It's been at least three days, hasn't it?
Three days?
What's going on?
I'm sorry.
I was horrible.
You're right, you said horrible things to me.
But it's okay.
Now that you're here.
I complained too much also.
I wasn't serious though.
I want to see your village.
Yeah, let's go.
Now, come on.
Wait.
Can you see the shore?
Yeah it's okay, I can.
See, over there.
It's time.
Your home is this way.
That isn't human anymore.
The Mushi are undergoing metamorphosis.
We won't be safe here.
Now, get away from it.
Shiro?
Hey, did you find him?
Nope.
Maybe it's over.
Hey, it's a tidal wave.
Watch out!
The fog's clearing up, isn't it?
By the time we got back to shore, the villagers
had already given up on our survival.
We thought that we were only gone for two-three hours.
Shiro!
But a month had gone by on shore.
Time must have been passing at
the Mushi's pace within the fog.
She's fortunate.
She had to deal with the loneliness for only three days.
Yeah.
You're right.
The following day, his wife's boat
washed up on the beach.
Wow, such a nice kimono.
Are you okay with that?
Yeah.
The owner's not around anymore.
Shiro.
Look at this.
Yeah, it's pretty.
Where
Sea
Meets
Man
The
Heavy
Seed
The Heavy Seed.