Old Tools
What is it this time?
This short kimono coat.
Wow! This lining is amazing!
It's the work of a genius painter who made a name for himself a while back.
There's someone cooking in the mountains here.
Sometimes when you look at it,
You can see white smoke rising up in places.
It's as if the smoke's wafting slowly
upward from peoples' homes...
Clothes That Embrace the Mountain
You know, someone must be living up in those mountains.
Huh? No one lives beyond here.
But I see lots of smoke rising.
Then someone must be burning charcoal or something.
The mountain god is cooking his meal.
Gods cook, too?
How else are they going to eat?
Gods don't get hungry.
Mushishi
Then he must be heating his bath.
Hey, you two!
Head on home now and cook our meal!
Alright!
Okay!
Come on.
Back then, there were mysterious
things in the mountains...
The mountains look the same as they did then,
but they're no longer the same.
Until that time, our hometown certainly felt as if it were wrapped in a soft cloth...
Sis... what's this?
I made it so that you can make yourself presentable to your art teacher.
It's woven from silk thread from
silkworms from the mountains
and dyed with plants found in the mountains.
Kai, if you can't return... that's okay.
If you become successful, Father will forgive you.
But look at this sometimes, and think of home...
Thank you, Sis...
I will absolutely become a fine artist...
I so wish I could start painting soon...
I wonder how Sis and the others are doing...
You there...
Rinse those plates.
Yes, sir.
It's getting warmer...
Hey, give me a hand here.
Coming!
This your coat?
This lining... whose work is it?
M-mine...
Forgive me! I wanted to paint so badly...
You drew this?
Yes...
I don't like it...
I don't like it at all...
Master!
From tomorrow, I want you in the studio.
Though there isn't much I can teach you...
Oh no... I'm out of paint...
when I'm so close to finishing...
Sir!
How's it coming?
The delivery date is coming up soon.
Yes, don't worry, it'll be ready.
Now... what can I do?
There isn't anyone else I can borrow money from...
And I have nothing left to sell...
Hock Shop
It's badly tattered... I can't give you much.
Please! I'll come right back to redeem it.
This is truly magnificent.
I can see why your master had such confidence in you.
To think someone with your talent is still an unknown...
Yes! I like it.
What do you say?
I know this is short notice, but can you paint another one by next month?
My grandson's wedding is coming up.
It'll also be a good opportunity
to make a name for yourself.
By all means! Let me do it!
No... I have no time to sleep...
You work was tremendously popular.
I've got all these orders for you.
You did me proud. Good luck to you.
I did it!
Let's see... what shall I paint next?
Hock Shop
Master, here are today's letters.
Oh, just leave them there.
More deadline reminders.
Don't they ever get tired?
Might as well save themselves the trouble.
Was I ever scared...
It was a huge landslide.
I heard that an entire village was swept away.
I was almost caught in that.
It was out west, at the foothills
of Mt. something or other...
There's no way it could be our village...
This is no time to be worrying about other things...
This is an important time for me.
I'm going to make a bigger and bigger name for myself.
Yes indeed... you are indeed a master...
But... have you not been well, sir?
What?
The paintings I had seen you do before seemed so truly full of life, but now...
Well, I might be worrying about nothing...
Darn... what's wrong with me?
It appears to be fatigue.
Take your medicine and rest a while.
But...
What's the rush? Your reputation is now solid.
Kai, how're you feeling?
Drink this. It'll make you feel better.
Sis...
How many years has it been
since she left to get married?
I wonder if she's doing well...
I wonder if Father will forgive me now?
Ten years have already passed since then...
It's selfish of me to think of
them only at times like this...
But I want to see them...
I want to walk through the scent of my hometown...
What's there to be afraid of?
They're my family...
Once I see them, I'll be able to create
good paintings once again...
Oh no... It can't be...
Auntie!
Is that you, Kai?
Whatever in heaven's name...
Didn't you get your sister's letter?
You didn't read it?
Three years ago, was it?
There was a terrible landslide...
The homes, the fields... just about
everything was swept away.
We got together and asked her
to write a letter to you...
asking you to help the village
since you became famous.
What happened to Father and Sis?
Your father was killed in the landslide.
Your sister also died after giving birth to this child the following year.
I'm saying this for your own good... Go back to town...
Don't ever come back.
He was quite a popular artist.
But one day, he suddenly vanished
and never came back...
That painting alone would fetch a good price.
Is that so...
What do you think?
It's a thin cloth, but it's unusually heavy...
It definitely smells of mushi.
Then you could probably sell it for a good price to that doctor who likes rare goods.
How's this price sound?
You say it's caused no trouble so far,
but without knowing the true nature of this mushi, I can't ask for a high price.
I'll take it at half price.
You jest.
You probably bought it for the price of a rag.
Well, I'm sure you could learn its true nature and resell it at a high price.
I don't want to deal with troublesome mushi...
No mushi-shi would fork over a
fortune for something like this.
Wait! All right.
I have one more piece to the puzzle.
They say these mountains are in the artist's hometown.
Now, that will help your investigation, right?
At half price it will.
Okay, you win.
I'm very sorry to hear that...
But you must come back.
I can't go back.
I can't paint anything anymore...
Even when I hold the brush, nothing inspires me...
Today again... the mountains look so foreign to me...
Just as I have become a stranger
to the people of my hometown...
Maybe I should go to live somewhere unknown to me...
What's this?
The taste of... homegrown...
I don't feel dizzy nowadays...
And I have energy, too.
Hi, Toyo... All by yourself today?
I'm just on my way over to deliver these.
Is your granny at home?
Granny turned cold...
What will we do about the child?
She had relatives on her father's side, didn't she?
They live far away, but let's have them take her in...
Let me... Let me take her in!
Please!
She's developing slowly both mentally and physically...
You can't raise her.
I vow to raise her with all my love...
So please, don't send her away.
Toyo, hold this for a minute.
Good job.
Not like that. Let me do that.
The way you're doing it, it'll topple right over.
Here you go. Don't spill it, okay?
She's already five, but she's still a baby...
Yum.
Here, thank you for your hard work.
These are for your niece.
She'll love these...
They're back to normal...
The mountains are back to normal...
That smoke... what could it be?
What's this?
Damn...
I thought I was a goner...
Never should've bought that thing...
Wh-who are you?!
No one you need to worry about...
It's gotten lighter...
That's... my coat...
So I came looking for the mountains to learn the true nature of the mushi that live in this coat.
But something odd happened when
I set foot on the mountain.
What?! My pack is getting heavier...
What's going on?!
And when I finally managed to escape from the mud,
the mushi seemed to have left the coat.
Well, that was enough for me.
The mushi in the coat were ubusuna native to this area.
Ubu... suna?
Mud-like mushi unique to each region.
But they're like that only when they're in the ground.
Above ground, they take a smoke-like form.
I hear there was a big landslide in this area...
A large number of ubusuna
were probably also swept away.
The ubusuna then found this coat
and made it their home.
Apparently, quite a huge number were living there.
They might've gathered since ubusuna can't survive outside their own region.
This fabric... it was woven from the
materials in this area, wasn't it?
Yes... My older sister made it completely from things found on the mountains...
Around the time I left home,
wearing this reminded me of the scents and sounds of the mountains.
Ubusuna congregate at the scents of home...
They exist in small amounts in all plants that grow there.
And by eating the plants, animals become hosts to the ubusuna, as well.
As ubiquitous as they are, these
mushi have very little influence,
and if the host leaves the region,
they completely lose their power.
Once he returns to the region where he was born,
they'll try protecting him for life from other minor mushi.
Do they have something to do with
a child's slow development?
That might happen, if the child didn't get enough ubusuna during its weaning period.
If that was the case, now that a huge number of ubusuna have returned,
she'll probably gradually catch up
if you feed her plenty of local foods.
I see...
Say, you don't need this coat anymore, right?
Won't you sell it back to me?
Well... I was planning on selling it off no matter what, so...
Please! This coat means a lot to me.
All right. But I have one condition.
A coat in which ubusuna live?
That is very interesting.
Yes... And once in a great while,
smoke rises from the mountains in the painting.
Once in how long a while?
Maybe about once every ten years or so.
That's truly a rare occurrence.
Hmm... This painting is also quite a work of art...
Isn't it?
It's the work of a mysterious artistic genius.
Whoa! I can't wait for the smoke to appear...
Since I almost got myself killed,
I suppose I can be forgiven for this...
What? On this?
That's right. The exact same painting.
No paints?
No, I still have them.
Whoa! You're good...
Mountains...
That's right, Toyo. They're our mountains.
Paint some more...
Okay, I will!
Clothes
That
Embrace
the
Mountain
String
from the
Sky
String from the Sky.