When I was a kid,
I was always curious about the
people beyond the valley fog.
They always showed up before the summer rainy season,
and vanished from the mountains by
the time the storms had passed.
The Sound of Footsteps on the Grass
Sir!
I knew you'd be here.
Your father's calling.
'kay.
It's a pretty purple today.
It only looks white to me.
Mushishi
You sure are a strange child.
Oh yeah?
It's already that time that they show up, huh?
We gotta fix the windows.
Are you sure, Dad?
You're just going to let them do
whatever in our mountains?
It's fine, they wouldn't do any harm.
They've been coming here for a long time.
They even hang out with the mountain patrollers.
What exactly do they do?
I don't know what they do for a living.
But they don't seem to be beggars.
I never got to know them that well.
I heard they know a lot about different places,
and that they've always got interesting stories.
But it's hard to know who they are, you know?
Those people might take the basin water.
Come on, they're just travelers and it's just water.
They're not like the villagers who
wanted to send it to their crops.
But I don't like it when outsiders go near there.
Taku, you're going to be running our business,
aren't you? Don't be so stingy.
Think of them as passing birds.
Just let them be.
Hey, catch any?
The fish can see you there.
Don't take so many fish!
This is my mountain.
Yours?
So are you the Master here?
I'm the Master's son.
The Master's son?
Here, then.
Although I'm just kidding.
We're hungry too.
Could you spare us one each?
Well, I guess.
Thanks.
I'll give the rest back to the Master then.
I'm Isaza of Watari.
I'll be here for a while this year
too, so I'll see you around.
You're an odd one, though.
You're the Master's son and you suck at fishing.
Oh my, that's a big catch.
Should we boil them or grill them?
What's his problem?
It's not like every mountain owner's
kid is good at fishing.
They're all over the place.
Hey, you! You liar.
I heard from Grandpa.
You aren't the Master's son.
I'm not a liar!
My ancestors spent a long time buying this mountain!
You bought it?
And you think you're the Master now?
You can't just do anything you want here.
I'm not just doing anything.
This mountain's special, I know.
This mountain's the reason the land here is so rich.
That's why my familiy's been protecting it.
Dad's the one stopping
the townspeople from damming the waterfall and carrying the water to the village.
Did a Mushi-shi tell you to do that?
Yeah, I think so.
They told our ancestors.
Or the mountain would get sick.
I see.
So it's precious to you too.
Well, fine then.
I was going to get you to pay for that fish from yesterday.
My bad.
Later.
Wait.
I'll pay you back if you gave them to me by mistake.
I don't need your charity.
Hurry up.
Just hold on.
I already got today's catch. Forget it.
I said hold on.
Hey,
that "Master" you talked about, what is it?
A huge catfish in this basin, apparently.
Who decided that's the Master?
The mountain.
The Master is born with grass on its body.
That's the marker.
I've seen it before! It's a huge
catfish with grass on its head.
Really? Nice.
So hey,
have you seen the fog change
color and twist like it's alive?
Of course, I have.
It's a Koumyakusuji here.
Koumyakusuji: Koumyaku channel
The source of life flows through this land.
It mixes with the water and evaporates
and turns into fog.
So the fog here is alive.
That's why it looks different depending on the day.
You can tell how well the land is by looking at it too.
Hurry, hurry! Stay calm.
Shut up!
That's not quite enough, but...
Later.
I told you a lot of stuff that I know,
so now it's your turn to tell me stuff.
I don't really know anything special.
Tell me normal stuff.
I want to hear about what happens in the village.
Hey, Taku-bocchan.
What brings you here?
I wanted to hear some interesting stories.
Well, you're in luck.
I was telling the chief about my travels.
Come on, sit down.
Is that for real?
Who knows.
My uncle always exaggerates a little.
And, oh yeah.
He saw a strange kid two mountains down south.
He's about ten years old, white hair, green eyes.
And he only has one.
Yeah?
What is he, a foreigner?
He says he didn't seem like it.
Two mountains down south, huh?
That's the same route we go. Maybe I'll see him.
Oh yeah, the rainy season's over soon.
When are you leaving?
No idea.
Grandpa looks at the fog every morning and decides.
How?
The mountain's energy is settled
when there's a blue tint.
When it's reddish, it's the opposite.
And when it's gold, the mountain's in a good
mood, so it's a good time to set out.
Sounds so carefree.
Are you jealous?
My whole future is set.
I'm going to live fighting over the mountain like Dad.
Yeah, I'm jealous.
It's a map of the Koumyakusuji's
course over the past few years.
Ah. I'll have that map then.
Thanks.
Hey, Isaza.
Thanks for that "rumor" of yours. It came in handy.
I'll ask you again sometime.
Sure.
That's what we do for a living.
We sell Mushi-shi information about potential
Mushi cases and Koumyakusuji changes.
No one would keep us fed if we just wandered around.
You could've told me earlier.
Then I would have listened for more suspicious stories.
That wouldn't work.
If I didn't know what's normal in the village,
I wouldn't know what's odd about it.
Plus I like hearing about the village.
Forget it.
What do you mean, "forget it"?
I get it, all right?
You're still pissed, aren't you?
Shut up, quit following me.
I'm not apologizing. This is how I do things.
I never asked you to.
It flashed!
The rainy season's finally over after this storm, huh?
So hot.
Isaza?
It's gold.
And next year,
they showed up at the same time of the year.
But it wasn't the same gang of people.
Yeah, we adopted him.
It was true what you told me.
He was wandering around town; said
he didn't have anywhere to go.
He looks a bit odd, but he's cool.
His name's Ginko.
Yeah?
But he probably won't be with us for long.
He tends to attract Mushi.
He can't stay by the Koumyakusuji for too long.
Either he or the Koumyaku would get hurt.
He'll probably get handed over to a Mushi-shi soon.
Fumi, what's wrong?
Sir,
your father...
But it says in his will that the whole
mountain goes to Taku.
I understand, but Aunt,
do you think Taku can play the right cards by himself?
The village is overcrowded; they need water.
We need to carry water somehow.
Well, just leave it to us. We'll take care of it.
Taku.
Hey, Taku.
I heard from the patrollers.
Your dad... Sorry to hear.
You haven't come out to the mountains lately.
Are you okay?
I couldn't protect the mountain.
My relatives took it all.
They're going to dam the waterfall
and ruin the mountains.
I'm sorry.
Taku, listen.
Something's wrong with the mountains.
It's really upset.
The ground's hot and it smells weird.
There's less animals and the Koumyaku is shifting.
We're going to move too.
You guys be careful.
Are you never coming here anymore?
I don't know.
Hey, let me in your group.
I don't want to be here anymore.
Take me like that Ginko guy.
I can see the fog's color too.
I don't have to be related to you, do I?
None of us are related by blood.
Grandpa decides whether to take people or not.
I'll ask him.
Come to the waterfall tomorrow morning.
The fog's plain white.
Something really is wrong.
This never happened before.
Where's Isaza?
He already left.
Liar. He...
The Koumyaku started moving overnight.
They had no choice.
Isaza told me to tell you he said "sorry".
They can't go against the Koumyaku.
Watari is a place where people gather when they
get driven out of their homes by Mushi.
You did too; you'll see him.
People like you, huh?
Hey, you.
We're leaving.
I lost my work again, too.
Oh yeah, one more thing he said.
"You guys should leave too."
From that day on, the mountain's
fog never took on a color.
And six months later...
The mountain spewed fire.
Those who had a place to go went.
The mountain burned and the waterfall dried up,
but the basin remained in the form of a swamp.
One day, I saw the shadow of a huge catfish.
But the grass that was once on its head wasn't there.
Over the next ten-some years,
I shoveled ash and planted trees.
The mountain slowly revived,
but it never returned to its former vitality.
Many children were born frail.
Isaza would have had some ideas.
It must have something to do with the Koumyaku.
But what exactly was I to do?
How was I supposed to even find him?
Even now, I jump when I hear the sound
of someone stepping through grass.
I keep thinking that they might have come back.
Taku!
Taku, hurry!
There's someone in the village
who says he can cure the kids.
Now keep making this drug like we just did,
and give him one dose each day.
You!
This land used to be a Koumyakusuji,
but it got abandoned.
Many of the Mushi migrated along with it.
Only the ones that coexist with humans remained.
Is that why the kids are so weak?
Wow, you sure know a lot.
That's about right.
You guys were born with the Koumyaku's blessings.
But not the kids.
I gave them nutrients and Mushi repellents.
They'll need it for a while.
I see.
Hey, you.
You don't seem to remember, but I've met you before.
Yeah? Sorry, I can't remember.
Do you remember Isaza?
Yeah, you know him?
I'm still good friends with him.
I came here because he told me about this place.
Said it's about time you'll be needing medicine.
He's still at it.
I see.
That's good then.
That's good.
This huge catfish, the shape of this swamp...
I've been here before.
Oh.
Him.
He and the mountain sure have changed.
Don't you think,
ex-Master?
The
Sound
of
Footsteps
on the
Grass
The World is filled with life unknown to man.